<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 19:19:49 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-05-27 11:27:44 -0600</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP04086</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>9675</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>NRK 1</synonym>
    <synonym>Nicotinic acid riboside kinase 1</synonym>
    <synonym>NmR-K 1</synonym>
    <synonym>RNK 1</synonym>
    <synonym>Ribosylnicotinamide kinase 1</synonym>
    <synonym>Ribosylnicotinic acid kinase 1</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>NMRK1</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in ATP binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Catalyzes the phosphorylation of nicotinamide riboside (NR) and nicotinic acid riboside (NaR) to form nicotinamide mononucleotide (NMN) and nicotinic acid mononucleotide (NaMN). The enzyme also phosphorylates the antitumor drugs tiazofurin and 3-deazaguanosine.
</specific_function>
  <pathways>
    <pathway>
      <name>NAD(+) biosynthesis</name>
      <smpdb_id/>
      <kegg_map_id/>
    </pathway>
    <pathway>
      <name>Nicotinate and nicotinamide metabolism</name>
      <smpdb_id/>
      <kegg_map_id>map00760</kegg_map_id>
    </pathway>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00902</accession>
      <name>NAD</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00855</accession>
      <name>Nicotinamide riboside</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01132</accession>
      <name>Nicotinic acid mononucleotide</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB06809</accession>
      <name>Nicotinate D-ribonucleoside</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00538</accession>
      <name>Adenosine triphosphate</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01341</accession>
      <name>ADP</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB59645</accession>
      <name>beta-nicotinamide D-ribonucleotide</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB59646</accession>
      <name>nicotinate beta-D-ribonucleotide</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>catalytic activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>transferase activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>transferase activity, transferring phosphorus-containing groups</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>phosphotransferase activity, alcohol group as acceptor</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>nucleoside binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>purine nucleoside binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>adenyl nucleotide binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>adenyl ribonucleotide binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>atp binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>Molecular function</category>
      <description>ATP binding</description>
      <go_id>GO:0005524</go_id>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>Molecular function</category>
      <description>metal ion binding</description>
      <go_id>GO:0046872</go_id>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>Molecular function</category>
      <description>ribosylnicotinamide kinase activity</description>
      <go_id>GO:0050262</go_id>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>Molecular function</category>
      <description>uridine kinase activity</description>
      <go_id>GO:0004849</go_id>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>Biological process</category>
      <description>NAD biosynthetic process</description>
      <go_id>GO:0009435</go_id>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>Biological process</category>
      <description>UMP biosynthetic process</description>
      <go_id>GO:0006222</go_id>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>9</chromosome_location>
    <locus>9q21.13</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;600 bp
ATGAAAACATTTATCATTGGAATCAGTGGTGTGACAAACAGTGGCAAAACAACACTGGCT
AAGAATTTGCAGAAACACCTCCCAAATTGCAGTGTCATATCTCAGGATGATTTCTTCAAG
CCAGAGTCTGAGATAGAGACAGATAAAAATGGATTTTTGCAGTACGATGTGCTTGAAGCA
CTTAACATGGAAAAAATGATGTCAGCCATTTCCTGCTGGATGGAAAGCGCAAGACACTCT
GTGGTATCAACAGACCAGGAAAGTGCTGAGGAAATTCCCATTTTAATCATCGAAGGTTTT
CTTCTTTTTAATTATAAGCCCCTTGACACTATATGGAATAGAAGCTATTTCCTGACTATT
CCATATGAAGAATGTAAAAGGAGGAGGAGTACAAGGGTCTATCAGCCTCCAGACTCTCCG
GGATACTTTGATGGCCATGTGTGGCCCATGTATCTAAAGTACAGACAAGAAATGCAGGAC
ATCACATGGGAAGTTGTGTACCTGGATGGAACAAAATCTGAAGAGGACCTCTTTTTGCAA
GTATATGAAGATCTAATACAAGAACTAGCAAAGCAAAAGTGTTTGCAAGTGACAGCATAA
</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>199</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>20152.76</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>4.63</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Nicotinamide riboside kinase 1
MKTFIIGISGVTNSGKTTLAKNLQKHLPNCSVISQDDFFKPESEIETDKNGFLQYDVLEA
LNMEKMMSAISCWMESARHSVVSTDQESAEEIPILIIEGFLLFNYKPLDTIWNRSYFLTI
PYEECKRRRSTRVYQPPDSPGYFDGHVWPMYLKYRQEMQDITWEVVYLDGTKSEEDLFLQ
VYEDLIQELAKQKCLQVTA</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>7020749</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>Q9NWW6</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>NRK1_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>2P0E</pdb_id>
    <pdb_id>2QG6</pdb_id>
    <pdb_id>2QL6</pdb_id>
    <pdb_id>2QSY</pdb_id>
    <pdb_id>2QSZ</pdb_id>
    <pdb_id>2QT0</pdb_id>
    <pdb_id>2QT1</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AK000566</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>NRK1</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>NRK1</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:26057</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bieganowski P, Brenner C: Discoveries of nicotinamide riboside as a nutrient and conserved NRK genes establish a Preiss-Handler independent route to NAD+ in fungi and humans. Cell. 2004 May 14;117(4):495-502.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15137942</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ota T, Suzuki Y, Nishikawa T, Otsuki T, Sugiyama T, Irie R, Wakamatsu A, Hayashi K, Sato H, Nagai K, Kimura K, Makita H, Sekine M, Obayashi M, Nishi T, Shibahara T, Tanaka T, Ishii S, Yamamoto J, Saito K, Kawai Y, Isono Y, Nakamura Y, Nagahari K, Murakami K, Yasuda T, Iwayanagi T, Wagatsuma M, Shiratori A, Sudo H, Hosoiri T, Kaku Y, Kodaira H, Kondo H, Sugawara M, Takahashi M, Kanda K, Yokoi T, Furuya T, Kikkawa E, Omura Y, Abe K, Kamihara K, Katsuta N, Sato K, Tanikawa M, Yamazaki M, Ninomiya K, Ishibashi T, Yamashita H, Murakawa K, Fujimori K, Tanai H, Kimata M, Watanabe M, Hiraoka S, Chiba Y, Ishida S, Ono Y, Takiguchi S, Watanabe S, Yosida M, Hotuta T, Kusano J, Kanehori K, Takahashi-Fujii A, Hara H, Tanase TO, Nomura Y, Togiya S, Komai F, Hara R, Takeuchi K, Arita M, Imose N, Musashino K, Yuuki H, Oshima A, Sasaki N, Aotsuka S, Yoshikawa Y, Matsunawa H, Ichihara T, Shiohata N, Sano S, Moriya S, Momiyama H, Satoh N, Takami S, Terashima Y, Suzuki O, Nakagawa S, Senoh A, Mizoguchi H, Goto Y, Shimizu F, Wakebe H, Hishigaki H, Watanabe T, Sugiyama A, Takemoto M, Kawakami B, Yamazaki M, Watanabe K, Kumagai A, Itakura S, Fukuzumi Y, Fujimori Y, Komiyama M, Tashiro H, Tanigami A, Fujiwara T, Ono T, Yamada K, Fujii Y, Ozaki K, Hirao M, Ohmori Y, Kawabata A, Hikiji T, Kobatake N, Inagaki H, Ikema Y, Okamoto S, Okitani R, Kawakami T, Noguchi S, Itoh T, Shigeta K, Senba T, Matsumura K, Nakajima Y, Mizuno T, Morinaga M, Sasaki M, Togashi T, Oyama M, Hata H, Watanabe M, Komatsu T, Mizushima-Sugano J, Satoh T, Shirai Y, Takahashi Y, Nakagawa K, Okumura K, Nagase T, Nomura N, Kikuchi H, Masuho Y, Yamashita R, Nakai K, Yada T, Nakamura Y, Ohara O, Isogai T, Sugano S: Complete sequencing and characterization of 21,243 full-length human cDNAs. Nat Genet. 2004 Jan;36(1):40-5. Epub 2003 Dec 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14702039</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Humphray SJ, Oliver K, Hunt AR, Plumb RW, Loveland JE, Howe KL, Andrews TD, Searle S, Hunt SE, Scott CE, Jones MC, Ainscough R, Almeida JP, Ambrose KD, Ashwell RI, Babbage AK, Babbage S, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Banerjee R, Barker DJ, Barlow KF, Bates K, Beasley H, Beasley O, Bird CP, Bray-Allen S, Brown AJ, Brown JY, Burford D, Burrill W, Burton J, Carder C, Carter NP, Chapman JC, Chen Y, Clarke G, Clark SY, Clee CM, Clegg S, Collier RE, Corby N, Crosier M, Cummings AT, Davies J, Dhami P, Dunn M, Dutta I, Dyer LW, Earthrowl ME, Faulkner L, Fleming CJ, Frankish A, Frankland JA, French L, Fricker DG, Garner P, Garnett J, Ghori J, Gilbert JG, Glison C, Grafham DV, Gribble S, Griffiths C, Griffiths-Jones S, Grocock R, Guy J, Hall RE, Hammond S, Harley JL, Harrison ES, Hart EA, Heath PD, Henderson CD, Hopkins BL, Howard PJ, Howden PJ, Huckle E, Johnson C, Johnson D, Joy AA, Kay M, Keenan S, Kershaw JK, Kimberley AM, King A, Knights A, Laird GK, Langford C, Lawlor S, Leongamornlert DA, Leversha M, Lloyd C, Lloyd DM, Lovell J, Martin S, Mashreghi-Mohammadi M, Matthews L, McLaren S, McLay KE, McMurray A, Milne S, Nickerson T, Nisbett J, Nordsiek G, Pearce AV, Peck AI, Porter KM, Pandian R, Pelan S, Phillimore B, Povey S, Ramsey Y, Rand V, Scharfe M, Sehra HK, Shownkeen R, Sims SK, Skuce CD, Smith M, Steward CA, Swarbreck D, Sycamore N, Tester J, Thorpe A, Tracey A, Tromans A, Thomas DW, Wall M, Wallis JM, West AP, Whitehead SL, Willey DL, Williams SA, Wilming L, Wray PW, Young L, Ashurst JL, Coulson A, Blocker H, Durbin R, Sulston JE, Hubbard T, Jackson MJ, Bentley DR, Beck S, Rogers J, Dunham I: DNA sequence and analysis of human chromosome 9.  Nature. 2004 May 27;429(6990):369-74.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15164053</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Sasiak K, Saunders PP: Purification and properties of a human nicotinamide ribonucleoside kinase.  Arch Biochem Biophys. 1996 Sep 15;333(2):414-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8809081</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Tempel W, Rabeh WM, Bogan KL, Belenky P, Wojcik M, Seidle HF, Nedyalkova L, Yang T, Sauve AA, Park HW, Brenner C: Nicotinamide riboside kinase structures reveal new pathways to NAD+.  PLoS Biol. 2007 Oct 2;5(10):e263.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17914902</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Khan JA, Xiang S, Tong L: Crystal structure of human nicotinamide riboside kinase.  Structure. 2007 Aug;15(8):1005-13.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17698003</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
