<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 18:59:35 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 18:59:35 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP01805</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>7163</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Enzyme</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Beta-3-endonexin</synonym>
    <synonym>CENP-R</synonym>
    <synonym>Integrin beta-3-binding protein</synonym>
    <synonym>Nuclear receptor-interacting factor 3</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>ITGB3BP</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in protein C-terminus binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Transcription coregulator that can have both coactivator and corepressor functions. Isoform 1, but not other isoforms, is involved in the coactivation of nuclear receptors for retinoid X (RXRs) and thyroid hormone (TRs) in a ligand-dependent fashion. In contrast, it does not coactivate nuclear receptors for retinoic acid, vitamin D, progesterone receptor, nor glucocorticoid. Acts as a coactivator for estrogen receptor alpha. Acts as a transcriptional corepressor via its interaction with the NFKB1 NF- kappa-B subunit, possibly by interfering with the transactivation domain of NFKB1. Induces apoptosis in breast cancer cells, but not in other cancer cells, via a caspase-2 mediated pathway that involves mitochondrial membrane permeabilization but does not require other caspases. May also act as an inhibitor of cyclin A- associated kinase. Also acts a component of the CENPA-CAD (nucleosome distal) complex, a complex recruited to centromeres which is involved in assembly of kinetochore proteins, mitotic progression and chromosome segregation. May be involved in incorporation of newly synthesized CENPA into centromeres via its interaction with the CENPA-NAC complex</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01830</accession>
      <name>Progesterone</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Isoform 4:Cytoplasm</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>1p31.3</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;534 bp
ATGCCTGTTAAAAGATCACTGAAGTTGGATGGTCTGTTAGAAGAAAATTCATTTGATCCT
TCAAAAATCACAAGGAAGAAAAGTGTTATAACTTATTCTCCAACAACTGGAACTTGTCAA
ATGAGTCTATTTGCTTCTCCCACAAGTTCTGAAGAGCAAAAGCACAGAAATGGACTATCA
AATGAAAAGAGAAAAAAATTGAATCACCCCAGTTTAACTGAAAGCAAAGAATCTACAACA
AAAGACAATGATGAATTCATGATGTTGCTATCAAAAGTTGAGAAATTGTCAGAAGAAATC
ATGGAGATAATGCAAAATTTAAGTAGTATACAGGCTTTGGAGGGCAGTAGAGAGCTTGAA
AATCTCATTGGAATCTCCTGTGCATCACATTTCTTAAAAAGAGAAATGCAGAAAACCAAA
GAACTAATGACAAAAGTGAATAAACAAAAACTGTTTGAAAAGAGTACAGGACTTCCTCAC
AAAGCATCACGTCATCTTGACAGCTATGAATTCCTTAAAGCCATTTTAAACTGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>177</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>20194.0</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>9.7</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>NRIF3</name>
        <pfam_id>PF06729</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Centromere protein R
MPVKRSLKLDGLLEENSFDPSKITRKKSVITYSPTTGTCQMSLFASPTSSEEQKHRNGLS
NEKRKKLNHPSLTESKESTTKDNDEFMMLLSKVEKLSEEIMEIMQNLSSIQALEGSRELE
NLIGISCASHFLKREMQKTKELMTKVNKQKLFEKSTGLPHKASRHLDSYEFLKAILN</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>6002985</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>Q13352</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>CENPR_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AF175306</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>ITGB3BP</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>ITGB3BP</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:6157</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shattil SJ, O'Toole T, Eigenthaler M, Thon V, Williams M, Babior BM, Ginsberg MH: Beta 3-endonexin, a novel polypeptide that interacts specifically with the cytoplasmic tail of the integrin beta 3 subunit. J Cell Biol. 1995 Nov;131(3):807-16.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7593198</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Li D, Desai-Yajnik V, Lo E, Schapira M, Abagyan R, Samuels HH: NRIF3 is a novel coactivator mediating functional specificity of nuclear hormone receptors. Mol Cell Biol. 1999 Oct;19(10):7191-202.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10490654</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ota T, Suzuki Y, Nishikawa T, Otsuki T, Sugiyama T, Irie R, Wakamatsu A, Hayashi K, Sato H, Nagai K, Kimura K, Makita H, Sekine M, Obayashi M, Nishi T, Shibahara T, Tanaka T, Ishii S, Yamamoto J, Saito K, Kawai Y, Isono Y, Nakamura Y, Nagahari K, Murakami K, Yasuda T, Iwayanagi T, Wagatsuma M, Shiratori A, Sudo H, Hosoiri T, Kaku Y, Kodaira H, Kondo H, Sugawara M, Takahashi M, Kanda K, Yokoi T, Furuya T, Kikkawa E, Omura Y, Abe K, Kamihara K, Katsuta N, Sato K, Tanikawa M, Yamazaki M, Ninomiya K, Ishibashi T, Yamashita H, Murakawa K, Fujimori K, Tanai H, Kimata M, Watanabe M, Hiraoka S, Chiba Y, Ishida S, Ono Y, Takiguchi S, Watanabe S, Yosida M, Hotuta T, Kusano J, Kanehori K, Takahashi-Fujii A, Hara H, Tanase TO, Nomura Y, Togiya S, Komai F, Hara R, Takeuchi K, Arita M, Imose N, Musashino K, Yuuki H, Oshima A, Sasaki N, Aotsuka S, Yoshikawa Y, Matsunawa H, Ichihara T, Shiohata N, Sano S, Moriya S, Momiyama H, Satoh N, Takami S, Terashima Y, Suzuki O, Nakagawa S, Senoh A, Mizoguchi H, Goto Y, Shimizu F, Wakebe H, Hishigaki H, Watanabe T, Sugiyama A, Takemoto M, Kawakami B, Yamazaki M, Watanabe K, Kumagai A, Itakura S, Fukuzumi Y, Fujimori Y, Komiyama M, Tashiro H, Tanigami A, Fujiwara T, Ono T, Yamada K, Fujii Y, Ozaki K, Hirao M, Ohmori Y, Kawabata A, Hikiji T, Kobatake N, Inagaki H, Ikema Y, Okamoto S, Okitani R, Kawakami T, Noguchi S, Itoh T, Shigeta K, Senba T, Matsumura K, Nakajima Y, Mizuno T, Morinaga M, Sasaki M, Togashi T, Oyama M, Hata H, Watanabe M, Komatsu T, Mizushima-Sugano J, Satoh T, Shirai Y, Takahashi Y, Nakagawa K, Okumura K, Nagase T, Nomura N, Kikuchi H, Masuho Y, Yamashita R, Nakai K, Yada T, Nakamura Y, Ohara O, Isogai T, Sugano S: Complete sequencing and characterization of 21,243 full-length human cDNAs. Nat Genet. 2004 Jan;36(1):40-5. Epub 2003 Dec 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14702039</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gregory SG, Barlow KF, McLay KE, Kaul R, Swarbreck D, Dunham A, Scott CE, Howe KL, Woodfine K, Spencer CC, Jones MC, Gillson C, Searle S, Zhou Y, Kokocinski F, McDonald L, Evans R, Phillips K, Atkinson A, Cooper R, Jones C, Hall RE, Andrews TD, Lloyd C, Ainscough R, Almeida JP, Ambrose KD, Anderson F, Andrew RW, Ashwell RI, Aubin K, Babbage AK, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Beasley H, Bethel G, Bird CP, Bray-Allen S, Brown JY, Brown AJ, Buckley D, Burton J, Bye J, Carder C, Chapman JC, Clark SY, Clarke G, Clee C, Cobley V, Collier RE, Corby N, Coville GJ, Davies J, Deadman R, Dunn M, Earthrowl M, Ellington AG, Errington H, Frankish A, Frankland J, French L, Garner P, Garnett J, Gay L, Ghori MR, Gibson R, Gilby LM, Gillett W, Glithero RJ, Grafham DV, Griffiths C, Griffiths-Jones S, Grocock R, Hammond S, Harrison ES, Hart E, Haugen E, Heath PD, Holmes S, Holt K, Howden PJ, Hunt AR, Hunt SE, Hunter G, Isherwood J, James R, Johnson C, Johnson D, Joy A, Kay M, Kershaw JK, Kibukawa M, Kimberley AM, King A, Knights AJ, Lad H, Laird G, Lawlor S, Leongamornlert DA, Lloyd DM, Loveland J, Lovell J, Lush MJ, Lyne R, Martin S, Mashreghi-Mohammadi M, Matthews L, Matthews NS, McLaren S, Milne S, Mistry S, Moore MJ, Nickerson T, O'Dell CN, Oliver K, Palmeiri A, Palmer SA, Parker A, Patel D, Pearce AV, Peck AI, Pelan S, Phelps K, Phillimore BJ, Plumb R, Rajan J, Raymond C, Rouse G, Saenphimmachak C, Sehra HK, Sheridan E, Shownkeen R, Sims S, Skuce CD, Smith M, Steward C, Subramanian S, Sycamore N, Tracey A, Tromans A, Van Helmond Z, Wall M, Wallis JM, White S, Whitehead SL, Wilkinson JE, Willey DL, Williams H, Wilming L, Wray PW, Wu Z, Coulson A, Vaudin M, Sulston JE, Durbin R, Hubbard T, Wooster R, Dunham I, Carter NP, McVean G, Ross MT, Harrow J, Olson MV, Beck S, Rogers J, Bentley DR, Banerjee R, Bryant SP, Burford DC, Burrill WD, Clegg SM, Dhami P, Dovey O, Faulkner LM, Gribble SM, Langford CF, Pandian RD, Porter KM, Prigmore E: The DNA sequence and biological annotation of human chromosome 1.  Nature. 2006 May 18;441(7091):315-21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16710414</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Fujimoto TT, Katsutani S, Shimomura T, Fujimura K: Novel alternatively spliced form of beta(3)-endonexin.  Thromb Res. 2002 Jan 1;105(1):63-70.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11864709</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kashiwagi H, Schwartz MA, Eigenthaler M, Davis KA, Ginsberg MH, Shattil SJ: Affinity modulation of platelet integrin alphaIIbbeta3 by beta3-endonexin, a selective binding partner of the beta3 integrin cytoplasmic tail. J Cell Biol. 1997 Jun 16;137(6):1433-43.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9182673</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ohtoshi A, Maeda T, Higashi H, Ashizawa S, Yamada M, Hatakeyama M: beta3-endonexin as a novel inhibitor of cyclin A-associated kinase.  Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2000 Jan 27;267(3):947-52.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10673397</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Li D, Wang F, Samuels HH: Domain structure of the NRIF3 family of coregulators suggests potential dual roles in transcriptional regulation. Mol Cell Biol. 2001 Dec;21(24):8371-84.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11713274</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Besta F, Massberg S, Brand K, Muller E, Page S, Gruner S, Lorenz M, Sadoul K, Kolanus W, Lengyel E, Gawaz M: Role of beta(3)-endonexin in the regulation of NF-kappaB-dependent expression of urokinase-type plasminogen activator receptor. J Cell Sci. 2002 Oct 15;115(Pt 20):3879-88.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12244126</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Li D, Das S, Yamada T, Samuels HH: The NRIF3 family of transcriptional coregulators induces rapid and profound apoptosis in breast cancer cells. Mol Cell Biol. 2004 May;24(9):3838-48.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15082778</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Talukder AH, Gururaj A, Mishra SK, Vadlamudi RK, Kumar R: Metastasis-associated protein 1 interacts with NRIF3, an estrogen-inducible nuclear receptor coregulator. Mol Cell Biol. 2004 Aug;24(15):6581-91.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15254226</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Okada M, Cheeseman IM, Hori T, Okawa K, McLeod IX, Yates JR 3rd, Desai A, Fukagawa T: The CENP-H-I complex is required for the efficient incorporation of newly synthesized CENP-A into centromeres. Nat Cell Biol. 2006 May;8(5):446-57. Epub 2006 Apr 16.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16622420</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Foltz DR, Jansen LE, Black BE, Bailey AO, Yates JR 3rd, Cleveland DW: The human CENP-A centromeric nucleosome-associated complex.  Nat Cell Biol. 2006 May;8(5):458-69. Epub 2006 Apr 16.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16622419</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Daub H, Olsen JV, Bairlein M, Gnad F, Oppermann FS, Korner R, Greff Z, Keri G, Stemmann O, Mann M: Kinase-selective enrichment enables quantitative phosphoproteomics of the kinome across the cell cycle. Mol Cell. 2008 Aug 8;31(3):438-48.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18691976</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Dephoure N, Zhou C, Villen J, Beausoleil SA, Bakalarski CE, Elledge SJ, Gygi SP: A quantitative atlas of mitotic phosphorylation.  Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2008 Aug 5;105(31):10762-7. Epub 2008 Jul 31.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18669648</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
