<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 19:08:28 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 19:08:28 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP02836</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>8343</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Enzyme</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>GD</synonym>
    <synonym>PAEG</synonym>
    <synonym>PEG</synonym>
    <synonym>PP14</synonym>
    <synonym>Placental protein 14</synonym>
    <synonym>Pregnancy-associated endometrial alpha-2 globulin</synonym>
    <synonym>Progestagen-associated endometrial protein</synonym>
    <synonym>Progesterone-associated endometrial protein</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>PAEP</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in transport</general_function>
  <specific_function>This protein is, quantitatively, the main protein synthesized and secreted in the endometrium from mid-luteal phase of the menstrual cycle and during the first semester of pregnancy</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00131</accession>
      <name>Glycerol</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>transporter activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>establishment of localization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Secreted</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:9</chromosome_location>
    <locus>9q34</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;568 bp
CTCAGAGCCACCCACAGCCGCAGCCATGCTGTGCCTCCTGCTCACCCTGGGCGTGGCCCT
GGTCTGTGGTGTCCCGGCCATGGACATCCCCCAGACCAAGCAGGACCTGGAGCTCCCAAA
GTTGGCAGGGACCTGGCACTCCATGGCCATGGCGACCAACAACATCTCCCTCATGGCGAC
ACTGAAGGCCCCTCTGAGGGTCCACATCACCTCACTGTTGCCCACCCCCGAGGACAACCT
GGAGATCGTTCTGCACAGATGGGAGAACAACAGCTGTGTTGAGAAGAAGGTCCTTGGAGA
GAAGACTGAGAATCCAAAGAAGTTCAAGATCAACTATACGGTGGCGAACGAGGCCACGCT
GCTCGATACTGACTACGACAATTTCCTGTTTCTCTGCCTACAGGACACCACCACCCCCAT
CCAGAGCATGATGTGCCAGTACCTGGCCAGAGTCCTGGTGGAGGACGATGAGATCATGCA
GGGATTCATCAGGGCTTTCAGGCCCCTGCCCAGGCACCTATGGTACTTGCTGGACTTGAA
ACAGATGGAAGAGCCGTGCCGTTTCTAG</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>180</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>20624.0</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>5.26</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Lipocalin</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00061</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>1-18</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Glycodelin
MLCLLLTLGVALVCGVPAMDIPQTKQDLELPKLAGTWHSMAMATNNISLMATLKAPLRVH
ITSLLPTPEDNLEIVLHRWENNSCVEKKVLGEKTENPKKFKINYTVANEATLLDTDYDNF
LFLCLQDTTTPIQSMMCQYLARVLVEDDEIMQGFIRAFRPLPRHLWYLLDLKQMEEPCRF
</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>4884164</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P09466</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>PAEP_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AL050169</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>PAEP</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>PAEP</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:8573</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Julkunen M, Seppala M, Janne OA: Complete amino acid sequence of human placental protein 14: a progesterone-regulated uterine protein homologous to beta-lactoglobulins. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1988 Dec;85(23):8845-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3194393</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Vaisse C, Atger M, Potier B, Milgrom E: Human placental protein 14 gene: sequence and characterization of a short duplication. DNA Cell Biol. 1990 Jul-Aug;9(6):401-13.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2206398</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Garde J, Bell SC, Eperon IC: Multiple forms of mRNA encoding human pregnancy-associated endometrial alpha 2-globulin, a beta-lactoglobulin homologue. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1991 Mar 15;88(6):2456-60.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2006183</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bechtel S, Rosenfelder H, Duda A, Schmidt CP, Ernst U, Wellenreuther R, Mehrle A, Schuster C, Bahr A, Blocker H, Heubner D, Hoerlein A, Michel G, Wedler H, Kohrer K, Ottenwalder B, Poustka A, Wiemann S, Schupp I: The full-ORF clone resource of the German cDNA Consortium.  BMC Genomics. 2007 Oct 31;8:399.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17974005</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Humphray SJ, Oliver K, Hunt AR, Plumb RW, Loveland JE, Howe KL, Andrews TD, Searle S, Hunt SE, Scott CE, Jones MC, Ainscough R, Almeida JP, Ambrose KD, Ashwell RI, Babbage AK, Babbage S, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Banerjee R, Barker DJ, Barlow KF, Bates K, Beasley H, Beasley O, Bird CP, Bray-Allen S, Brown AJ, Brown JY, Burford D, Burrill W, Burton J, Carder C, Carter NP, Chapman JC, Chen Y, Clarke G, Clark SY, Clee CM, Clegg S, Collier RE, Corby N, Crosier M, Cummings AT, Davies J, Dhami P, Dunn M, Dutta I, Dyer LW, Earthrowl ME, Faulkner L, Fleming CJ, Frankish A, Frankland JA, French L, Fricker DG, Garner P, Garnett J, Ghori J, Gilbert JG, Glison C, Grafham DV, Gribble S, Griffiths C, Griffiths-Jones S, Grocock R, Guy J, Hall RE, Hammond S, Harley JL, Harrison ES, Hart EA, Heath PD, Henderson CD, Hopkins BL, Howard PJ, Howden PJ, Huckle E, Johnson C, Johnson D, Joy AA, Kay M, Keenan S, Kershaw JK, Kimberley AM, King A, Knights A, Laird GK, Langford C, Lawlor S, Leongamornlert DA, Leversha M, Lloyd C, Lloyd DM, Lovell J, Martin S, Mashreghi-Mohammadi M, Matthews L, McLaren S, McLay KE, McMurray A, Milne S, Nickerson T, Nisbett J, Nordsiek G, Pearce AV, Peck AI, Porter KM, Pandian R, Pelan S, Phillimore B, Povey S, Ramsey Y, Rand V, Scharfe M, Sehra HK, Shownkeen R, Sims SK, Skuce CD, Smith M, Steward CA, Swarbreck D, Sycamore N, Tester J, Thorpe A, Tracey A, Tromans A, Thomas DW, Wall M, Wallis JM, West AP, Whitehead SL, Willey DL, Williams SA, Wilming L, Wray PW, Young L, Ashurst JL, Coulson A, Blocker H, Durbin R, Sulston JE, Hubbard T, Jackson MJ, Bentley DR, Beck S, Rogers J, Dunham I: DNA sequence and analysis of human chromosome 9.  Nature. 2004 May 27;429(6990):369-74.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15164053</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bell SC, Keyte JW, Waites GT: Pregnancy-associated endometrial alpha 2-globulin, the major secretory protein of the luteal phase and first trimester pregnancy endometrium, is not glycosylated prolactin but related to beta-lactoglobulins. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1987 Nov;65(5):1067-71.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3667877</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Huhtala ML, Seppala M, Narvanen A, Palomaki P, Julkunen M, Bohn H: Amino acid sequence homology between human placental protein 14 and beta-lactoglobulins from various species. Endocrinology. 1987 Jun;120(6):2620-2.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3569148</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Vigne JL, Hornung D, Mueller MD, Taylor RN: Purification and characterization of an immunomodulatory endometrial protein, glycodelin. J Biol Chem. 2001 May 18;276(20):17101-5. Epub 2001 Mar 5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11278680</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Dell A, Morris HR, Easton RL, Panico M, Patankar M, Oehniger S, Koistinen R, Koistinen H, Seppala M, Clark GF: Structural analysis of the oligosaccharides derived from glycodelin, a human glycoprotein with potent immunosuppressive and contraceptive activities. J Biol Chem. 1995 Oct 13;270(41):24116-26.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7592613</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Morris HR, Dell A, Easton RL, Panico M, Koistinen H, Koistinen R, Oehninger S, Patankar MS, Seppala M, Clark GF: Gender-specific glycosylation of human glycodelin affects its contraceptive activity. J Biol Chem. 1996 Dec 13;271(50):32159-67.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8943270</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Koistinen H, Koistinen R, Dell A, Morris HR, Easton RL, Patankar MS, Oehninger S, Clark GF, Seppala M: Glycodelin from seminal plasma is a differentially glycosylated form of contraceptive glycodelin-A. Mol Hum Reprod. 1996 Oct;2(10):759-65.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9239694</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Glycerol</name>
        <accession>HMDB00131</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Overington JP, Al-Lazikani B, Hopkins AL: How many drug targets are there?  Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2006 Dec;5(12):993-6.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17139284</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Glycerol</name>
        <accession>HMDB00131</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Imming P, Sinning C, Meyer A: Drugs, their targets and the nature and number of drug targets.  Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2006 Oct;5(10):821-34.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17016423</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Glycerol</name>
        <accession>HMDB00131</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Berman HM, Westbrook J, Feng Z, Gilliland G, Bhat TN, Weissig H, Shindyalov IN, Bourne PE: The Protein Data Bank.  Nucleic Acids Res. 2000 Jan 1;28(1):235-42.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>10592235</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
