<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:04:28 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:04:28 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP07954</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13665</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>BMPG</synonym>
    <synonym>EMBP</synonym>
    <synonym>Eosinophil granule major basic protein</synonym>
    <synonym>MBP</synonym>
    <synonym>Pregnancy-associated major basic protein</synonym>
    <synonym>Proteoglycan 2</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>PRG2</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Cytotoxin and helminthotoxin. Also induces non-cytolytic histamine release from human basophils. Involved in antiparasitic defense mechanisms and immune hypersensitivity reactions. The proform acts as a proteinase inhibitor, reducing the activity of PAPPA</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>immune system process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>immune response</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Eosinophil granule major basic protein:Cytoplasmic vesicle</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>secretory vesicle</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>11q12</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;669 bp
ATGAAACTCCCCCTACTTCTGGCTCTTCTATTTGGGGCAGTTTCTGCTCTTCATCTAAGG
TCTGAGACTTCCACCTTTGAGACCCCTTTGGGTGCTAAGACGCTGCCTGAGGATGAGGAG
ACACCAGAGCAGGAGATGGAGGAGACCCCTTGCAGGGAGCTGGAGGAAGAGGAGGAGTGG
GGCTCTGGAAGTGAAGATGCCTCCAAGAAAGATGGGGCTGTTGAGTCTATCTCAGTGCCA
GATATGGTGGACAAAAACCTTACGTGTCCTGAGGAAGAGGACACAGTAAAAGTGGTGGGC
ATCCCTGGGTGCCAGACCTGCCGCTACCTCCTGGTGAGAAGTCTTCAGACGTTTAGTCAA
GCTTGGTTTACTTGCCGGAGGTGCTACAGGGGCAACCTGGTTTCCATCCACAACTTCAAT
ATTAATTATCGAATCCAGTGTTCTGTCAGCGCGCTCAACCAGGGTCAAGTCTGGATTGGA
GGCAGGATCACAGGCTCGGGTCGCTGCAGACGCTTTCAGTGGGTTGACGGCAGCCGCTGG
AACTTTGCGTACTGGGCTGCTCACCAGCCCTGGTCCCGCGGTGGTCACTGCGTGGCCCTG
TGTACCCGAGGAGGCTACTGGCGTCGAGCCCACTGCCTCAGAAGACTTCCTTTCATCTGT
TCCTACTGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>222</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>25205.3</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>6.75</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Lectin_C</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00059</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>1-16</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Bone marrow proteoglycan
MKLPLLLALLFGAVSALHLRSETSTFETPLGAKTLPEDEETPEQEMEETPCRELEEEEEW
GSGSEDASKKDGAVESISVPDMVDKNLTCPEEEDTVKVVGIPGCQTCRYLLVRSLQTFSQ
AWFTCRRCYRGNLVSIHNFNINYRIQCSVSALNQGQVWIGGRITGSGRCRRFQWVDGSRW
NFAYWAAHQPWSRGGHCVALCTRGGHWRRAHCLRRLPFICSY</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>34476</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P13727</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>PRG2_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1H8U</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>Y00809</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>PRG2</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>PRG2</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:9362</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Barker RL, Gleich GJ, Pease LR: Acidic precursor revealed in human eosinophil granule major basic protein cDNA. J Exp Med. 1988 Oct 1;168(4):1493-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3171483</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Barker RL, Loegering DA, Arakawa KC, Pease LR, Gleich GJ: Cloning and sequence analysis of the human gene encoding eosinophil major basic protein. Gene. 1990 Feb 14;86(2):285-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2323577</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>McGrogan M, Simonsen C, Scott R, Griffith J, Ellis N, Kennedy J, Campanelli D, Nathan C, Gabay J: Isolation of a complementary DNA clone encoding a precursor to human eosinophil major basic protein. J Exp Med. 1988 Dec 1;168(6):2295-308.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3199069</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Yoshimatsu K, Ohya Y, Shikata Y, Seto T, Hasegawa Y, Tanaka I, Kawamura T, Kitoh K, Toyoshima S, Osawa T: Purification and cDNA cloning of a novel factor produced by a human T-cell hybridoma: sequence homology with animal lectins. Mol Immunol. 1992 Apr;29(4):537-46.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1565101</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Li MS, Sun L, Satoh T, Fisher LM, Spry CJ: Human eosinophil major basic protein, a mediator of allergic inflammation, is expressed by alternative splicing from two promoters. Biochem J. 1995 Feb 1;305 ( Pt 3):921-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7531438</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Taylor TD, Noguchi H, Totoki Y, Toyoda A, Kuroki Y, Dewar K, Lloyd C, Itoh T, Takeda T, Kim DW, She X, Barlow KF, Bloom T, Bruford E, Chang JL, Cuomo CA, Eichler E, FitzGerald MG, Jaffe DB, LaButti K, Nicol R, Park HS, Seaman C, Sougnez C, Yang X, Zimmer AR, Zody MC, Birren BW, Nusbaum C, Fujiyama A, Hattori M, Rogers J, Lander ES, Sakaki Y: Human chromosome 11 DNA sequence and analysis including novel gene identification. Nature. 2006 Mar 23;440(7083):497-500.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16554811</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shikata Y, Hayashi Y, Yoshimatsu K, Ohya Y, Seto T, Fukushima K, Yoshida Y: Pro-major basic protein has three types of sugar chains at the pro-portion. Biochim Biophys Acta. 1993 Jun 4;1163(3):243-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8507662</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Oxvig C, Sand O, Kristensen T, Gleich GJ, Sottrup-Jensen L: Circulating human pregnancy-associated plasma protein-A is disulfide-bridged to the proform of eosinophil major basic protein. J Biol Chem. 1993 Jun 15;268(17):12243-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7685339</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Oxvig C, Haaning J, Kristensen L, Wagner JM, Rubin I, Stigbrand T, Gleich GJ, Sottrup-Jensen L: Identification of angiotensinogen and complement C3dg as novel proteins binding the proform of eosinophil major basic protein in human pregnancy serum and plasma. J Biol Chem. 1995 Jun 9;270(23):13645-51.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7539791</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wasmoen TL, Bell MP, Loegering DA, Gleich GJ, Prendergast FG, McKean DJ: Biochemical and amino acid sequence analysis of human eosinophil granule major basic protein. J Biol Chem. 1988 Sep 5;263(25):12559-63.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3410852</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gabay JE, Scott RW, Campanelli D, Griffith J, Wilde C, Marra MN, Seeger M, Nathan CF: Antibiotic proteins of human polymorphonuclear leukocytes.  Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1989 Jul;86(14):5610-4.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2501794</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Weller PF, Ackerman SJ, Smith JA: Eosinophil granule cationic proteins: major basic protein is distinct from the smaller subunit of eosinophil peroxidase. J Leukoc Biol. 1988 Jan;43(1):1-4.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3422083</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kristensen T, Oxvig C, Sand O, Moller NP, Sottrup-Jensen L: Amino acid sequence of human pregnancy-associated plasma protein-A derived from cloned cDNA. Biochemistry. 1994 Feb 15;33(6):1592-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7508748</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wasmoen TL, McKean DJ, Benirschke K, Coulam CB, Gleich GJ: Evidence of eosinophil granule major basic protein in human placenta.  J Exp Med. 1989 Dec 1;170(6):2051-63.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2584934</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Oxvig C, Haaning J, Hojrup P, Sottrup-Jensen L: Location and nature of carbohydrate groups in proform of human major basic protein isolated from pregnancy serum. Biochem Mol Biol Int. 1994 May;33(2):329-36.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7524900</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Oxvig C, Gleich GJ, Sottrup-Jensen L: Localization of disulfide bridges and free sulfhydryl groups in human eosinophil granule major basic protein. FEBS Lett. 1994 Mar 21;341(2-3):213-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8137941</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bonno M, Oxvig C, Kephart GM, Wagner JM, Kristensen T, Sottrup-Jensen L, Gleich GJ: Localization of pregnancy-associated plasma protein-A and colocalization of pregnancy-associated plasma protein-A messenger ribonucleic acid and eosinophil granule major basic protein messenger ribonucleic acid in placenta. Lab Invest. 1994 Oct;71(4):560-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7526035</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Overgaard MT, Oxvig C, Christiansen M, Lawrence JB, Conover CA, Gleich GJ, Sottrup-Jensen L, Haaning J: Messenger ribonucleic acid levels of pregnancy-associated plasma protein-A and the proform of eosinophil major basic protein: expression in human reproductive and nonreproductive tissues. Biol Reprod. 1999 Oct;61(4):1083-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10491647</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Overgaard MT, Haaning J, Boldt HB, Olsen IM, Laursen LS, Christiansen M, Gleich GJ, Sottrup-Jensen L, Conover CA, Oxvig C: Expression of recombinant human pregnancy-associated plasma protein-A and identification of the proform of eosinophil major basic protein as its physiological inhibitor. J Biol Chem. 2000 Oct 6;275(40):31128-33.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10913121</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Overgaard MT, Sorensen ES, Stachowiak D, Boldt HB, Kristensen L, Sottrup-Jensen L, Oxvig C: Complex of pregnancy-associated plasma protein-A and the proform of eosinophil major basic protein. Disulfide structure and carbohydrate attachment. J Biol Chem. 2003 Jan 24;278(4):2106-17. Epub 2002 Nov 5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12421832</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ulrich M, Petre A, Youhnovski N, Promm F, Schirle M, Schumm M, Pero RS, Doyle A, Checkel J, Kita H, Thiyagarajan N, Acharya KR, Schmid-Grendelmeier P, Simon HU, Schwarz H, Tsutsui M, Shimokawa H, Bellon G, Lee JJ, Przybylski M, Doring G: Post-translational tyrosine nitration of eosinophil granule toxins mediated by eosinophil peroxidase. J Biol Chem. 2008 Oct 17;283(42):28629-40. Epub 2008 Aug 11.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18694936</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Swaminathan GJ, Weaver AJ, Loegering DA, Checkel JL, Leonidas DD, Gleich GJ, Acharya KR: Crystal structure of the eosinophil major basic protein at 1.8 A. An atypical lectin with a paradigm shift in specificity. J Biol Chem. 2001 Jul 13;276(28):26197-203. Epub 2001 Apr 23.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11319227</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Sjoblom T, Jones S, Wood LD, Parsons DW, Lin J, Barber TD, Mandelker D, Leary RJ, Ptak J, Silliman N, Szabo S, Buckhaults P, Farrell C, Meeh P, Markowitz SD, Willis J, Dawson D, Willson JK, Gazdar AF, Hartigan J, Wu L, Liu C, Parmigiani G, Park BH, Bachman KE, Papadopoulos N, Vogelstein B, Kinzler KW, Velculescu VE: The consensus coding sequences of human breast and colorectal cancers.  Science. 2006 Oct 13;314(5797):268-74. Epub 2006 Sep 7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16959974</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
