<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:02:19 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:02:19 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP07753</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13462</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>BK channel subunit beta-1</synonym>
    <synonym>BKbeta</synonym>
    <synonym>BKbeta1</synonym>
    <synonym>Calcium-activated potassium channel subunit beta</synonym>
    <synonym>Calcium-activated potassium channel, subfamily M subunit beta-1</synonym>
    <synonym>Charybdotoxin receptor subunit beta-1</synonym>
    <synonym>Hbeta1</synonym>
    <synonym>K(VCA)beta-1</synonym>
    <synonym>Maxi K channel subunit beta-1</synonym>
    <synonym>Slo-beta</synonym>
    <synonym>Slo-beta-1</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>KCNMB1</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in calcium-activated potassium channel activity</general_function>
  <specific_function>Regulatory subunit of the calcium activated potassium KCNMA1 (maxiK) channel. Modulates the calcium sensitivity and gating kinetics of KCNMA1, thereby contributing to KCNMA1 channel diversity. Increases the apparent Ca(2+)/voltage sensitivity of the KCNMA1 channel. It also modifies KCNMA1 channel kinetics and alters its pharmacological properties. It slows down the activation and the deactivation kinetics of the channel. Acts as a negative regulator of smooth muscle contraction by enhancing the calcium sensitivity to KCNMA1. Its presence is also a requirement for internal binding of the KCNMA1 channel opener dehydrosoyasaponin I (DHS-1) triterpene glycoside and for external binding of the agonist hormone 17-beta-estradiol (E2). Increases the binding activity of charybdotoxin (CTX) toxin to KCNMA1 peptide blocker by increasing the CTX association rate and decreasing the dissociation rate</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15242</accession>
      <name>Miconazole</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>transporter activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>transmembrane transporter activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>substrate-specific transmembrane transporter activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ion transmembrane transporter activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ion channel activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>cation channel activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>calcium activated cation channel activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>calcium-activated potassium channel activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>establishment of localization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>ion transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>cation transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>monovalent inorganic cation transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>potassium ion transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>cell part</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>membrane</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Membrane</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Multi-pass membrane protein</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:5</chromosome_location>
    <locus>5q34</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;576 bp
ATGGTGAAGAAGCTGGTGATGGCCCAGAAGCGGGGAGAGACACGAGCCCTTTGCCTGGGT
GTAACCATGGTGGTGTGTGCCGTCATCACCTACTACATCCTGGTCACGACTGTGCTGCCC
CTCTACCAGAAAAGCGTGTGGACCCAGGAATCCAAGTGCCACCTGATTGAGACCAACATC
AGGGACCAGGAGGAGCTGAAGGGCAAGAAGGTGCCCCAGTACCCATGCCTGTGGGTCAAC
GTGTCAGCTGCCGGCAGGTGGGCTGTGCTGTACCACACGGAGGACACTCGGGACCAGAAC
CAGCAGTGCTCCTACATCCCAGGCAGCGTGGACAATTACCAGACGGCCCGGGCCGACGTG
GAGAAGGTCAGAGCCAAATTCCAAGAGCAGCAGGTCTTCTACTGCTTCTCCGCACCTCGG
GGGAACGAAACCAGCGTCCTATTCCAGCGCCTCTACGGGCCCCAGGCCCTCCTCTTCTCC
CTCTTCTGGCCCACCTTCCTGCTGACCGGTGGCCTCCTCATTATCGCCATGGTGAAGAGC
AACCAGTACCTGTCCATCCTGGCGGCCCAGAAGTAG</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>191</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>21797.3</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>9.16</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>CaKB</name>
        <pfam_id>PF03185</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>19-39</region>
      <region>158-178</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Calcium-activated potassium channel subunit beta-1
MVKKLVMAQKRGETRALCLGVTMVVCAVITYYILVTTVLPLYQKSVWTQESKCHLIETNI
RDQEELKGKKVPQYPCLWVNVSAAGRWAVLYHTEDTRDQNQQCSYIPGSVDNYQTARADV
EKVRAKFQEQQVFYCFSAPRGNETSVLFQRLYGPQALLFSLFWPTFLLTGGLLIIAMVKS
NQYLSILAAQK</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id/>
  <uniprot_id>Q16558</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>KCMB1_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>U25138</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>KCNMB1</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>KCNMB1</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:6285</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Meera P, Wallner M, Jiang Z, Toro L: A calcium switch for the functional coupling between alpha (hslo) and beta subunits (KV,Ca beta) of maxi K channels. FEBS Lett. 1996 Mar 11;382(1-2):84-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8612769</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Dworetzky SI, Boissard CG, Lum-Ragan JT, McKay MC, Post-Munson DJ, Trojnacki JT, Chang CP, Gribkoff VK: Phenotypic alteration of a human BK (hSlo) channel by hSlobeta subunit coexpression: changes in blocker sensitivity, activation/relaxation and inactivation kinetics, and protein kinase A modulation. J Neurosci. 1996 Aug 1;16(15):4543-50.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8764643</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Tseng-Crank J, Godinot N, Johansen TE, Ahring PK, Strobaek D, Mertz R, Foster CD, Olesen SP, Reinhart PH: Cloning, expression, and distribution of a Ca(2+)-activated K+ channel beta-subunit from human brain. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1996 Aug 20;93(17):9200-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8799178</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Mazzone JN, Kaiser RA, Buxton IL: Calcium-activated potassium channel expression in human myometrium: effect of pregnancy. Proc West Pharmacol Soc. 2002;45:184-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12434576</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ota T, Suzuki Y, Nishikawa T, Otsuki T, Sugiyama T, Irie R, Wakamatsu A, Hayashi K, Sato H, Nagai K, Kimura K, Makita H, Sekine M, Obayashi M, Nishi T, Shibahara T, Tanaka T, Ishii S, Yamamoto J, Saito K, Kawai Y, Isono Y, Nakamura Y, Nagahari K, Murakami K, Yasuda T, Iwayanagi T, Wagatsuma M, Shiratori A, Sudo H, Hosoiri T, Kaku Y, Kodaira H, Kondo H, Sugawara M, Takahashi M, Kanda K, Yokoi T, Furuya T, Kikkawa E, Omura Y, Abe K, Kamihara K, Katsuta N, Sato K, Tanikawa M, Yamazaki M, Ninomiya K, Ishibashi T, Yamashita H, Murakawa K, Fujimori K, Tanai H, Kimata M, Watanabe M, Hiraoka S, Chiba Y, Ishida S, Ono Y, Takiguchi S, Watanabe S, Yosida M, Hotuta T, Kusano J, Kanehori K, Takahashi-Fujii A, Hara H, Tanase TO, Nomura Y, Togiya S, Komai F, Hara R, Takeuchi K, Arita M, Imose N, Musashino K, Yuuki H, Oshima A, Sasaki N, Aotsuka S, Yoshikawa Y, Matsunawa H, Ichihara T, Shiohata N, Sano S, Moriya S, Momiyama H, Satoh N, Takami S, Terashima Y, Suzuki O, Nakagawa S, Senoh A, Mizoguchi H, Goto Y, Shimizu F, Wakebe H, Hishigaki H, Watanabe T, Sugiyama A, Takemoto M, Kawakami B, Yamazaki M, Watanabe K, Kumagai A, Itakura S, Fukuzumi Y, Fujimori Y, Komiyama M, Tashiro H, Tanigami A, Fujiwara T, Ono T, Yamada K, Fujii Y, Ozaki K, Hirao M, Ohmori Y, Kawabata A, Hikiji T, Kobatake N, Inagaki H, Ikema Y, Okamoto S, Okitani R, Kawakami T, Noguchi S, Itoh T, Shigeta K, Senba T, Matsumura K, Nakajima Y, Mizuno T, Morinaga M, Sasaki M, Togashi T, Oyama M, Hata H, Watanabe M, Komatsu T, Mizushima-Sugano J, Satoh T, Shirai Y, Takahashi Y, Nakagawa K, Okumura K, Nagase T, Nomura N, Kikuchi H, Masuho Y, Yamashita R, Nakai K, Yada T, Nakamura Y, Ohara O, Isogai T, Sugano S: Complete sequencing and characterization of 21,243 full-length human cDNAs. Nat Genet. 2004 Jan;36(1):40-5. Epub 2003 Dec 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14702039</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Meera P, Wallner M, Toro L: A neuronal beta subunit (KCNMB4) makes the large conductance, voltage- and Ca2+-activated K+ channel resistant to charybdotoxin and iberiotoxin. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2000 May 9;97(10):5562-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10792058</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Valverde MA, Rojas P, Amigo J, Cosmelli D, Orio P, Bahamonde MI, Mann GE, Vergara C, Latorre R: Acute activation of Maxi-K channels (hSlo) by estradiol binding to the beta subunit. Science. 1999 Sep 17;285(5435):1929-31.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10489376</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Orio P, Rojas P, Ferreira G, Latorre R: New disguises for an old channel: MaxiK channel beta-subunits.  News Physiol Sci. 2002 Aug;17:156-61.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12136044</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Fernandez-Fernandez JM, Tomas M, Vazquez E, Orio P, Latorre R, Senti M, Marrugat J, Valverde MA: Gain-of-function mutation in the KCNMB1 potassium channel subunit is associated with low prevalence of diastolic hypertension. J Clin Invest. 2004 Apr;113(7):1032-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15057310</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Miconazole</name>
        <accession>HMDB15242</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Hatton CJ, Peers C: Effects of cytochrome P-450 inhibitors on ionic currents in isolated rat type I carotid body cells. Am J Physiol. 1996 Jul;271(1 Pt 1):C85-92.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>8760033</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Miconazole</name>
        <accession>HMDB15242</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Alvarez J, Montero M, Garcia-Sancho J: High affinity inhibition of Ca(2+)-dependent K+ channels by cytochrome P-450 inhibitors. J Biol Chem. 1992 Jun 15;267(17):11789-93.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>1376313</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
