<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:02:05 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:02:05 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP07730</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13439</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>HIST2H2AB</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in DNA binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Core component of nucleosome. Nucleosomes wrap and compact DNA into chromatin, limiting DNA accessibility to the cellular machineries which require DNA as a template. Histones thereby play a central role in transcription regulation, DNA repair, DNA replication and chromosomal stability. DNA accessibility is regulated via a complex set of post-translational modifications of histones, also called histone code, and nucleosome remodeling</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>nucleic acid binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>dna binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>cellular process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>cellular component organization at cellular level</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>organelle organization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>chromosome organization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>chromatin organization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>nucleosome organization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>nucleosome assembly</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>organelle</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>membrane-bounded organelle</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>intracellular membrane-bounded organelle</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>nucleus</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>macromolecular complex</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>protein-dna complex</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>nucleosome</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Nucleus</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Chromosome</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>1q21</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;393 bp
ATGTCAGGACGCGGAAAGCAGGGAGGCAAGGCCCGCGCTAAGGCCAAGTCGCGCTCGTCC
CGCGCTGGTCTCCAGTTCCCGGTGGGGCGAGTGCACCGCTTGCTGCGCAAAGGCAACTAC
GCGGAGCGGGTCGGGGCAGGCGCCCCGGTGTACCTGGCGGCGGTCCTCGAGTACCTGACC
GCGGAAATTCTGGAGCTGGCGGGCAACGCGGCTCGGGACAACAAGAAGACGCGCATCATC
CCTCGCCATCTGCAACTAGCCGTGAGGAATGACGAAGAGCTCAACAAGTTACTCGGGGGT
GTCACCATTGCCCAGGGCGGCGTCTTGCCCAATATCCAGGCTGTCCTGTTGCCCAAGAAA
ACGGAGAGTCACAAGCCTGGCAAGAACAAGTAA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>130</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>13995.2</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>11.53</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Histone</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00125</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Histone H2A type 2-B
MSGRGKQGGKARAKAKSRSSRAGLQFPVGRVHRLLRKGNYAERVGAGAPVYLAAVLEYLT
AEILELAGNAARDNKKTRIIPRHLQLAVRNDEELNKLLGGVTIAQGGVLPNIQAVLLPKK
TESHKPGKNK</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>24496255</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>Q8IUE6</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>H2A2B_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1EQZ</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AY131972</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>HIST2H2AB</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>HIST2H2AB</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:20508</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Marzluff WF, Gongidi P, Woods KR, Jin J, Maltais LJ: The human and mouse replication-dependent histone genes.  Genomics. 2002 Nov;80(5):487-98.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12408966</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gregory SG, Barlow KF, McLay KE, Kaul R, Swarbreck D, Dunham A, Scott CE, Howe KL, Woodfine K, Spencer CC, Jones MC, Gillson C, Searle S, Zhou Y, Kokocinski F, McDonald L, Evans R, Phillips K, Atkinson A, Cooper R, Jones C, Hall RE, Andrews TD, Lloyd C, Ainscough R, Almeida JP, Ambrose KD, Anderson F, Andrew RW, Ashwell RI, Aubin K, Babbage AK, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Beasley H, Bethel G, Bird CP, Bray-Allen S, Brown JY, Brown AJ, Buckley D, Burton J, Bye J, Carder C, Chapman JC, Clark SY, Clarke G, Clee C, Cobley V, Collier RE, Corby N, Coville GJ, Davies J, Deadman R, Dunn M, Earthrowl M, Ellington AG, Errington H, Frankish A, Frankland J, French L, Garner P, Garnett J, Gay L, Ghori MR, Gibson R, Gilby LM, Gillett W, Glithero RJ, Grafham DV, Griffiths C, Griffiths-Jones S, Grocock R, Hammond S, Harrison ES, Hart E, Haugen E, Heath PD, Holmes S, Holt K, Howden PJ, Hunt AR, Hunt SE, Hunter G, Isherwood J, James R, Johnson C, Johnson D, Joy A, Kay M, Kershaw JK, Kibukawa M, Kimberley AM, King A, Knights AJ, Lad H, Laird G, Lawlor S, Leongamornlert DA, Lloyd DM, Loveland J, Lovell J, Lush MJ, Lyne R, Martin S, Mashreghi-Mohammadi M, Matthews L, Matthews NS, McLaren S, Milne S, Mistry S, Moore MJ, Nickerson T, O'Dell CN, Oliver K, Palmeiri A, Palmer SA, Parker A, Patel D, Pearce AV, Peck AI, Pelan S, Phelps K, Phillimore BJ, Plumb R, Rajan J, Raymond C, Rouse G, Saenphimmachak C, Sehra HK, Sheridan E, Shownkeen R, Sims S, Skuce CD, Smith M, Steward C, Subramanian S, Sycamore N, Tracey A, Tromans A, Van Helmond Z, Wall M, Wallis JM, White S, Whitehead SL, Wilkinson JE, Willey DL, Williams H, Wilming L, Wray PW, Wu Z, Coulson A, Vaudin M, Sulston JE, Durbin R, Hubbard T, Wooster R, Dunham I, Carter NP, McVean G, Ross MT, Harrow J, Olson MV, Beck S, Rogers J, Bentley DR, Banerjee R, Bryant SP, Burford DC, Burrill WD, Clegg SM, Dhami P, Dovey O, Faulkner LM, Gribble SM, Langford CF, Pandian RD, Porter KM, Prigmore E: The DNA sequence and biological annotation of human chromosome 1.  Nature. 2006 May 18;441(7091):315-21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16710414</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Aihara H, Nakagawa T, Yasui K, Ohta T, Hirose S, Dhomae N, Takio K, Kaneko M, Takeshima Y, Muramatsu M, Ito T: Nucleosomal histone kinase-1 phosphorylates H2A Thr 119 during mitosis in the early Drosophila embryo. Genes Dev. 2004 Apr 15;18(8):877-88. Epub 2004 Apr 12.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15078818</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Zhang Y, Griffin K, Mondal N, Parvin JD: Phosphorylation of histone H2A inhibits transcription on chromatin templates. J Biol Chem. 2004 May 21;279(21):21866-72. Epub 2004 Mar 9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15010469</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wang H, Wang L, Erdjument-Bromage H, Vidal M, Tempst P, Jones RS, Zhang Y: Role of histone H2A ubiquitination in Polycomb silencing.  Nature. 2004 Oct 14;431(7010):873-8. Epub 2004 Sep 22.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15386022</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hagiwara T, Hidaka Y, Yamada M: Deimination of histone H2A and H4 at arginine 3 in HL-60 granulocytes.  Biochemistry. 2005 Apr 19;44(15):5827-34.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15823041</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Cao R, Tsukada Y, Zhang Y: Role of Bmi-1 and Ring1A in H2A ubiquitylation and Hox gene silencing.  Mol Cell. 2005 Dec 22;20(6):845-54.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16359901</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bergink S, Salomons FA, Hoogstraten D, Groothuis TA, de Waard H, Wu J, Yuan L, Citterio E, Houtsmuller AB, Neefjes J, Hoeijmakers JH, Vermeulen W, Dantuma NP: DNA damage triggers nucleotide excision repair-dependent monoubiquitylation of histone H2A. Genes Dev. 2006 May 15;20(10):1343-52.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16702407</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Mailand N, Bekker-Jensen S, Faustrup H, Melander F, Bartek J, Lukas C, Lukas J: RNF8 ubiquitylates histones at DNA double-strand breaks and promotes assembly of repair proteins. Cell. 2007 Nov 30;131(5):887-900. Epub 2007 Nov 20.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18001824</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Huen MS, Grant R, Manke I, Minn K, Yu X, Yaffe MB, Chen J: RNF8 transduces the DNA-damage signal via histone ubiquitylation and checkpoint protein assembly. Cell. 2007 Nov 30;131(5):901-14. Epub 2007 Nov 20.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18001825</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Stewart GS, Panier S, Townsend K, Al-Hakim AK, Kolas NK, Miller ES, Nakada S, Ylanko J, Olivarius S, Mendez M, Oldreive C, Wildenhain J, Tagliaferro A, Pelletier L, Taubenheim N, Durandy A, Byrd PJ, Stankovic T, Taylor AM, Durocher D: The RIDDLE syndrome protein mediates a ubiquitin-dependent signaling cascade at sites of DNA damage. Cell. 2009 Feb 6;136(3):420-34.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19203578</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Doil C, Mailand N, Bekker-Jensen S, Menard P, Larsen DH, Pepperkok R, Ellenberg J, Panier S, Durocher D, Bartek J, Lukas J, Lukas C: RNF168 binds and amplifies ubiquitin conjugates on damaged chromosomes to allow accumulation of repair proteins. Cell. 2009 Feb 6;136(3):435-46.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19203579</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Sjoblom T, Jones S, Wood LD, Parsons DW, Lin J, Barber TD, Mandelker D, Leary RJ, Ptak J, Silliman N, Szabo S, Buckhaults P, Farrell C, Meeh P, Markowitz SD, Willis J, Dawson D, Willson JK, Gazdar AF, Hartigan J, Wu L, Liu C, Parmigiani G, Park BH, Bachman KE, Papadopoulos N, Vogelstein B, Kinzler KW, Velculescu VE: The consensus coding sequences of human breast and colorectal cancers.  Science. 2006 Oct 13;314(5797):268-74. Epub 2006 Sep 7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16959974</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
