<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:00:42 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:00:42 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP07591</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13299</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>C-type lectin superfamily member 5</synonym>
    <synonym>MDL-1</synonym>
    <synonym>Myeloid DAP12-associating lectin 1</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>CLEC5A</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>May be involved in proinflammatory activation of myeloid cells via TYROBP-mediated signaling in a calcium-dependent manner</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Membrane</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Single-pass type II membrane protein (Probable)</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:7</chromosome_location>
    <locus>7q33</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;567 bp
ATGAACTGGCACATGATCATCTCTGGGCTTATTGTGGTAGTGCTTAAAGTTGTTGGAATG
ACCTTATTTCTACTTTATTTCCCACAGATTTTTAACAAAAGTAACGATGGTTTCACCACC
ACCAGGAGCTATGGAACAGTCTCACAGATTTTTGGGAGCAGTTCCCCAAGTCCCAACGGC
TTCATTACCACAAGGAGCTATGGAACAGTCTGCCCCAAAGACTGGGAATTTTATCAAGCA
AGATGTTTTTTCTTATCCACTTCTGAATCATCTTGGAATGAAAGCAGGGACTTTTGCAAA
GGAAAAGGATCCACATTGGCAATTGTCAACACGCCAGAGAAACTGAAGTTTCTTCAGGAC
ATAACTGATGCTGAGAAGTATTTTATTGGCTTAATTTACCATCGTGAAGAGAAAAGGTGG
CGTTGGATCAACAACTCTGTGTTCAATGGCAATGTTACCAATCAGAATCAGAATTTCAAC
TGTGCGACCATTGGCCTAACAAAGACATTTGATGCTGCATCATGTGACATCAGCTACCGC
AGGATCTGTGAGAAGAATGCCAAATGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>188</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>21521.3</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>9.01</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Lectin_C</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00059</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>5-27</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;C-type lectin domain family 5 member A
MNWHMIISGLIVVVLKVVGMTLFLLYFPQIFNKSNDGFTTTRSYGTVSQIFGSSSPSPNG
FITTRSYGTVCPKDWEFYQARCFFLSTSESSWNESRDFCKGKGSTLAIVNTPEKLKFLQD
ITDAEKYFIGLIYHREEKRWRWINNSVFNGNVTNQNQNFNCATIGLTKTFDAASCDISYR
RICEKNAK</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>41472352</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>Q9NY25</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>CLC5A_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AC073647</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>CLEC5A</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>CLEC5A</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:2054</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bakker AB, Baker E, Sutherland GR, Phillips JH, Lanier LL: Myeloid DAP12-associating lectin (MDL)-1 is a cell surface receptor involved in the activation of myeloid cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1999 Aug 17;96(17):9792-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10449773</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hillier LW, Fulton RS, Fulton LA, Graves TA, Pepin KH, Wagner-McPherson C, Layman D, Maas J, Jaeger S, Walker R, Wylie K, Sekhon M, Becker MC, O'Laughlin MD, Schaller ME, Fewell GA, Delehaunty KD, Miner TL, Nash WE, Cordes M, Du H, Sun H, Edwards J, Bradshaw-Cordum H, Ali J, Andrews S, Isak A, Vanbrunt A, Nguyen C, Du F, Lamar B, Courtney L, Kalicki J, Ozersky P, Bielicki L, Scott K, Holmes A, Harkins R, Harris A, Strong CM, Hou S, Tomlinson C, Dauphin-Kohlberg S, Kozlowicz-Reilly A, Leonard S, Rohlfing T, Rock SM, Tin-Wollam AM, Abbott A, Minx P, Maupin R, Strowmatt C, Latreille P, Miller N, Johnson D, Murray J, Woessner JP, Wendl MC, Yang SP, Schultz BR, Wallis JW, Spieth J, Bieri TA, Nelson JO, Berkowicz N, Wohldmann PE, Cook LL, Hickenbotham MT, Eldred J, Williams D, Bedell JA, Mardis ER, Clifton SW, Chissoe SL, Marra MA, Raymond C, Haugen E, Gillett W, Zhou Y, James R, Phelps K, Iadanoto S, Bubb K, Simms E, Levy R, Clendenning J, Kaul R, Kent WJ, Furey TS, Baertsch RA, Brent MR, Keibler E, Flicek P, Bork P, Suyama M, Bailey JA, Portnoy ME, Torrents D, Chinwalla AT, Gish WR, Eddy SR, McPherson JD, Olson MV, Eichler EE, Green ED, Waterston RH, Wilson RK: The DNA sequence of human chromosome 7.  Nature. 2003 Jul 10;424(6945):157-64.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12853948</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
