<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 18:50:05 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-05-27 11:30:39 -0600</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP00412</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>5649</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>L-isoaspartyl protein carboxyl methyltransferase</synonym>
    <synonym>PIMT</synonym>
    <synonym>Protein L-isoaspartyl/D-aspartyl methyltransferase</synonym>
    <synonym>Protein-beta-aspartate methyltransferase</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>PCMT1</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in protein-L-isoaspartate (D-aspartate) O-methyltransferase activity</general_function>
  <specific_function>Catalyzes the methyl esterification of L-isoaspartyl and D-aspartyl residues in peptides and proteins that result from spontaneous decomposition of normal L-aspartyl and L-asparaginyl residues. It plays a role in the repair and/or degradation of damaged proteins. Acts on microtubule-associated protein 2, calreticulin, clathrin light chains a and b, Ubiquitin carboxyl-terminal hydrolase isozyme L1, phosphatidylethanolamine-binding protein 1, stathmin, beta-synuclein and alpha-synuclein (By similarity).
</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01185</accession>
      <name>S-Adenosylmethionine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00939</accession>
      <name>S-Adenosylhomocysteine</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>catalytic activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>transferase activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>transferase activity, transferring one-carbon groups</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>methyltransferase activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>s-adenosylmethionine-dependent methyltransferase activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>protein-l-isoaspartate (d-aspartate) o-methyltransferase activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>macromolecule metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>macromolecule modification</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>protein modification process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>Cellular component</category>
      <description>endoplasmic reticulum</description>
      <go_id>GO:0005783</go_id>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>Molecular function</category>
      <description>protein-L-isoaspartate (D-aspartate) O-methyltransferase activity</description>
      <go_id>GO:0004719</go_id>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>Biological process</category>
      <description>protein repair</description>
      <go_id>GO:0030091</go_id>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>Biological process</category>
      <description>S-adenosylhomocysteine metabolic process</description>
      <go_id>GO:0046498</go_id>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>Biological process</category>
      <description>S-adenosylmethionine metabolic process</description>
      <go_id>GO:0046500</go_id>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasm</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>6</chromosome_location>
    <locus>6q24-q25</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;684 bp
ATGGCCTGGAAATCCGGCGGCGCCAGCCACTCGGAGCTAATCCACAATCTCCGCAAAAAT
GGAATCATCAAGACAGATAAAGTATTTGAAGTGATGCTGGCTACAGACCGCTCCCACTAT
GCAAAATGTAACCCATACATGGATTCTCCACAATCAATAGGTTTCCAAGCAACAATCAGT
GCTCCACACATGCATGCATATGCGCTAGAACTTCTATTTGATCAGTTGCATGAAGGAGCT
AAAGCTCTTGATGTAGGATCTGGAAGTGGAATCCTTACTGCATGTTTTGCACGTATGGTT
GGATGTACTGGAAAAGTCATAGGAATTGATCACATTAAAGAGCTAGTAGATGACTCAGTA
AATAATGTCAGGAAGGACGATCCAACACTTCTGTCTTCAGGGAGAGTACAGCTTGTTGTG
GGGGATGGAAGAATGGGATATGCTGAAGAAGCCCCTTATGATGCCATTCATGTGGGAGCT
GCAGCCCCTGTTGTACCCCAGGCGCTAATAGATCAGTTAAAGCCCGGAGGAAGATTGATA
TTGCCTGTTGGTCCTGCAGGCGGAAACCAAATGTTGGAGCAGTATGACAAGCTACAAGAT
GGCAGCATCAAAATGAAGCCTCTGATGGGGGTGATATACGTGCCTTTAACAGATAAAGAA
AAGCAGTGGTCCAGGTGGAAGTGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>227</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>30357.695</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>6.725</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>PCMT</name>
        <pfam_id>PF01135</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Protein-L-isoaspartate(D-aspartate) O-methyltransferase
MAWKSGGASHSELIHNLRKNGIIKTDKVFEVMLATDRSHYAKCNPYMDSPQSIGFQATIS
APHMHAYALELLFDQLHEGAKALDVGSGSGILTACFARMVGCTGKVIGIDHIKELVDDSI
NNVRKDDPTLLSSGRVQLVVGDGRMGYAEEAPYDAIHVGAAAPVVPQALIDQLKPGGRLI
LPVGPAGGNQMLEQYDKLQDGSIKMKPLMGVIYVPLTDKEKQWSRWK</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>158260471</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P22061</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>PIMT_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1I1N</pdb_id>
    <pdb_id>1KR5</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AK289724</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>PCMT1</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>PCMT1</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:8728</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ingrosso D, Fowler AV, Bleibaum J, Clarke S: Sequence of the D-aspartyl/L-isoaspartyl protein methyltransferase from human erythrocytes. Common sequence motifs for protein, DNA, RNA, and small molecule S-adenosylmethionine-dependent methyltransferases. J Biol Chem. 1989 Nov 25;264(33):20131-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2684970</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>MacLaren DC, Kagan RM, Clarke S: Alternative splicing of the human isoaspartyl protein carboxyl methyltransferase RNA leads to the generation of a C-terminal -RDEL sequence in isozyme II. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1992 May 29;185(1):277-83.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1339271</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Takeda R, Mizobuchi M, Murao K, Sato M, Takahara J: Characterization of three cDNAs encoding two isozymes of an isoaspartyl protein carboxyl methyltransferase from human erythroid leukemia cells. J Biochem (Tokyo). 1995 Apr;117(4):683-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7592526</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ota T, Suzuki Y, Nishikawa T, Otsuki T, Sugiyama T, Irie R, Wakamatsu A, Hayashi K, Sato H, Nagai K, Kimura K, Makita H, Sekine M, Obayashi M, Nishi T, Shibahara T, Tanaka T, Ishii S, Yamamoto J, Saito K, Kawai Y, Isono Y, Nakamura Y, Nagahari K, Murakami K, Yasuda T, Iwayanagi T, Wagatsuma M, Shiratori A, Sudo H, Hosoiri T, Kaku Y, Kodaira H, Kondo H, Sugawara M, Takahashi M, Kanda K, Yokoi T, Furuya T, Kikkawa E, Omura Y, Abe K, Kamihara K, Katsuta N, Sato K, Tanikawa M, Yamazaki M, Ninomiya K, Ishibashi T, Yamashita H, Murakawa K, Fujimori K, Tanai H, Kimata M, Watanabe M, Hiraoka S, Chiba Y, Ishida S, Ono Y, Takiguchi S, Watanabe S, Yosida M, Hotuta T, Kusano J, Kanehori K, Takahashi-Fujii A, Hara H, Tanase TO, Nomura Y, Togiya S, Komai F, Hara R, Takeuchi K, Arita M, Imose N, Musashino K, Yuuki H, Oshima A, Sasaki N, Aotsuka S, Yoshikawa Y, Matsunawa H, Ichihara T, Shiohata N, Sano S, Moriya S, Momiyama H, Satoh N, Takami S, Terashima Y, Suzuki O, Nakagawa S, Senoh A, Mizoguchi H, Goto Y, Shimizu F, Wakebe H, Hishigaki H, Watanabe T, Sugiyama A, Takemoto M, Kawakami B, Yamazaki M, Watanabe K, Kumagai A, Itakura S, Fukuzumi Y, Fujimori Y, Komiyama M, Tashiro H, Tanigami A, Fujiwara T, Ono T, Yamada K, Fujii Y, Ozaki K, Hirao M, Ohmori Y, Kawabata A, Hikiji T, Kobatake N, Inagaki H, Ikema Y, Okamoto S, Okitani R, Kawakami T, Noguchi S, Itoh T, Shigeta K, Senba T, Matsumura K, Nakajima Y, Mizuno T, Morinaga M, Sasaki M, Togashi T, Oyama M, Hata H, Watanabe M, Komatsu T, Mizushima-Sugano J, Satoh T, Shirai Y, Takahashi Y, Nakagawa K, Okumura K, Nagase T, Nomura N, Kikuchi H, Masuho Y, Yamashita R, Nakai K, Yada T, Nakamura Y, Ohara O, Isogai T, Sugano S: Complete sequencing and characterization of 21,243 full-length human cDNAs. Nat Genet. 2004 Jan;36(1):40-5. Epub 2003 Dec 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14702039</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Mungall AJ, Palmer SA, Sims SK, Edwards CA, Ashurst JL, Wilming L, Jones MC, Horton R, Hunt SE, Scott CE, Gilbert JG, Clamp ME, Bethel G, Milne S, Ainscough R, Almeida JP, Ambrose KD, Andrews TD, Ashwell RI, Babbage AK, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Banerjee R, Barker DJ, Barlow KF, Bates K, Beare DM, Beasley H, Beasley O, Bird CP, Blakey S, Bray-Allen S, Brook J, Brown AJ, Brown JY, Burford DC, Burrill W, Burton J, Carder C, Carter NP, Chapman JC, Clark SY, Clark G, Clee CM, Clegg S, Cobley V, Collier RE, Collins JE, Colman LK, Corby NR, Coville GJ, Culley KM, Dhami P, Davies J, Dunn M, Earthrowl ME, Ellington AE, Evans KA, Faulkner L, Francis MD, Frankish A, Frankland J, French L, Garner P, Garnett J, Ghori MJ, Gilby LM, Gillson CJ, Glithero RJ, Grafham DV, Grant M, Gribble S, Griffiths C, Griffiths M, Hall R, Halls KS, Hammond S, Harley JL, Hart EA, Heath PD, Heathcott R, Holmes SJ, Howden PJ, Howe KL, Howell GR, Huckle E, Humphray SJ, Humphries MD, Hunt AR, Johnson CM, Joy AA, Kay M, Keenan SJ, Kimberley AM, King A, Laird GK, Langford C, Lawlor S, Leongamornlert DA, Leversha M, Lloyd CR, Lloyd DM, Loveland JE, Lovell J, Martin S, Mashreghi-Mohammadi M, Maslen GL, Matthews L, McCann OT, McLaren SJ, McLay K, McMurray A, Moore MJ, Mullikin JC, Niblett D, Nickerson T, Novik KL, Oliver K, Overton-Larty EK, Parker A, Patel R, Pearce AV, Peck AI, Phillimore B, Phillips S, Plumb RW, Porter KM, Ramsey Y, Ranby SA, Rice CM, Ross MT, Searle SM, Sehra HK, Sheridan E, Skuce CD, Smith S, Smith M, Spraggon L, Squares SL, Steward CA, Sycamore N, Tamlyn-Hall G, Tester J, Theaker AJ, Thomas DW, Thorpe A, Tracey A, Tromans A, Tubby B, Wall M, Wallis JM, West AP, White SS, Whitehead SL, Whittaker H, Wild A, Willey DJ, Wilmer TE, Wood JM, Wray PW, Wyatt JC, Young L, Younger RM, Bentley DR, Coulson A, Durbin R, Hubbard T, Sulston JE, Dunham I, Rogers J, Beck S: The DNA sequence and analysis of human chromosome 6.  Nature. 2003 Oct 23;425(6960):805-11.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14574404</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>DeVry CG, Tsai W, Clarke S: Structure of the human gene encoding the protein repair L-isoaspartyl (D-aspartyl) O-methyltransferase. Arch Biochem Biophys. 1996 Nov 15;335(2):321-32.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8914929</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gilbert JM, Fowler A, Bleibaum J, Clarke S: Purification of homologous protein carboxyl methyltransferase isozymes from human and bovine erythrocytes. Biochemistry. 1988 Jul 12;27(14):5227-33.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3167043</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Tsai W, Clarke S: Amino acid polymorphisms of the human L-isoaspartyl/D-aspartyl methyltransferase involved in protein repair. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1994 Aug 30;203(1):491-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8074695</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ingrosso D, Kagan RM, Clarke S: Distinct C-terminal sequences of isozymes I and II of the human erythrocyte L-isoaspartyl/D-aspartyl protein methyltransferase. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1991 Feb 28;175(1):351-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1998518</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>DeVry CG, Clarke S: Polymorphic forms of the protein L-isoaspartate (D-aspartate) O-methyltransferase involved in the repair of age-damaged proteins. J Hum Genet. 1999;44(5):275-88.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10496068</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ryttersgaard C, Griffith SC, Sawaya MR, MacLaren DC, Clarke S, Yeates TO: Crystal structure of human L-isoaspartyl methyltransferase.  J Biol Chem. 2002 Mar 22;277(12):10642-6. Epub 2002 Jan 15.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11792715</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Smith CD, Carson M, Friedman AM, Skinner MM, Delucas L, Chantalat L, Weise L, Shirasawa T, Chattopadhyay D: Crystal structure of human L-isoaspartyl-O-methyl-transferase with S-adenosyl homocysteine at 1.6-A resolution and modeling of an isoaspartyl-containing peptide at the active site. Protein Sci. 2002 Mar;11(3):625-35.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11847284</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
