<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 19:04:08 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 19:04:08 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP02286</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>7771</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Calgranulin-B</synonym>
    <synonym>Calprotectin L1H subunit</synonym>
    <synonym>Leukocyte L1 complex heavy chain</synonym>
    <synonym>MRP-14</synonym>
    <synonym>Migration inhibitory factor-related protein 14</synonym>
    <synonym>S100 calcium-binding protein A9</synonym>
    <synonym>p14</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>S100A9</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in calcium ion binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Calcium-binding protein. Has antimicrobial activity towards bacteria and fungi. Important for resistance to invasion by pathogenic bacteria. Up-regulates transcription of genes that are under the control of NF-kappa-B. Plays a role in the development of endotoxic shock in response to bacterial lipopolysaccharide (LPS). Promotes tubulin polymerization when unphosphorylated. Promotes phagocyte migration and infiltration of granulocytes at sites of wounding. Plays a role as a pro-inflammatory mediator in acute and chronic inflammation and up-regulates the release of IL8 and cell-surface expression of ICAM1. Extracellular calprotectin binds to target cells and promotes apoptosis. Antimicrobial and proapoptotic activity is inhibited by zinc ions</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>cation binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>metal ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>calcium ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Secreted</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasm</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasm</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>cytoskeleton</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Cell membrane</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Peripheral membrane protein</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>1q21</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;345 bp
ATGACTTGCAAAATGTCGCAGCTGGAACGCAACATAGAGACCATCATCAACACCTTCCAC
CAATACTCTGTGAAGCTGGGGCACCCAGACACCCTGAACCAGGGGGAATTCAAAGAGCTG
GTGCGAAAAGATCTGCAAAATTTTCTCAAGAAGGAGAATAAGAATGAAAAGGTCATAGAA
CACATCATGGAGGACCTGGACACAAATGCAGACAAGCAGCTGAGCTTCGAGGAGTTCATC
ATGCTGATGGCGAGGCTAACCTGGGCCTCCCACGAGAAGATGCACGAGGGTGACGAGGGC
CCTGGCCACCACCATAAGCCAGGCCTCGGGGAGGGCACCCCCTAA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>114</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>13242.0</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>6.08</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>S_100</name>
        <pfam_id>PF01023</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Protein S100-A9
MTCKMSQLERNIETIINTFHQYSVKLGHPDTLNQGEFKELVRKDLQNFLKKENKNEKVIE
HIMEDLDTNADKQLSFEEFIMLMARLTWASHEKMHEGDEGPGHHHKPGLGEGTP</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>34771</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P06702</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>S10A9_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1IRJ</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>X06233</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>S100A9</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>S100A9</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:10499</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Odink K, Cerletti N, Bruggen J, Clerc RG, Tarcsay L, Zwadlo G, Gerhards G, Schlegel R, Sorg C: Two calcium-binding proteins in infiltrate macrophages of rheumatoid arthritis. Nature. 1987 Nov 5-11;330(6143):80-2.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3313057</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Lagasse E, Clerc RG: Cloning and expression of two human genes encoding calcium-binding proteins that are regulated during myeloid differentiation. Mol Cell Biol. 1988 Jun;8(6):2402-10.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3405210</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Murao S, Collart FR, Huberman E: A protein containing the cystic fibrosis antigen is an inhibitor of protein kinases. J Biol Chem. 1989 May 15;264(14):8356-60.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2656677</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gregory SG, Barlow KF, McLay KE, Kaul R, Swarbreck D, Dunham A, Scott CE, Howe KL, Woodfine K, Spencer CC, Jones MC, Gillson C, Searle S, Zhou Y, Kokocinski F, McDonald L, Evans R, Phillips K, Atkinson A, Cooper R, Jones C, Hall RE, Andrews TD, Lloyd C, Ainscough R, Almeida JP, Ambrose KD, Anderson F, Andrew RW, Ashwell RI, Aubin K, Babbage AK, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Beasley H, Bethel G, Bird CP, Bray-Allen S, Brown JY, Brown AJ, Buckley D, Burton J, Bye J, Carder C, Chapman JC, Clark SY, Clarke G, Clee C, Cobley V, Collier RE, Corby N, Coville GJ, Davies J, Deadman R, Dunn M, Earthrowl M, Ellington AG, Errington H, Frankish A, Frankland J, French L, Garner P, Garnett J, Gay L, Ghori MR, Gibson R, Gilby LM, Gillett W, Glithero RJ, Grafham DV, Griffiths C, Griffiths-Jones S, Grocock R, Hammond S, Harrison ES, Hart E, Haugen E, Heath PD, Holmes S, Holt K, Howden PJ, Hunt AR, Hunt SE, Hunter G, Isherwood J, James R, Johnson C, Johnson D, Joy A, Kay M, Kershaw JK, Kibukawa M, Kimberley AM, King A, Knights AJ, Lad H, Laird G, Lawlor S, Leongamornlert DA, Lloyd DM, Loveland J, Lovell J, Lush MJ, Lyne R, Martin S, Mashreghi-Mohammadi M, Matthews L, Matthews NS, McLaren S, Milne S, Mistry S, Moore MJ, Nickerson T, O'Dell CN, Oliver K, Palmeiri A, Palmer SA, Parker A, Patel D, Pearce AV, Peck AI, Pelan S, Phelps K, Phillimore BJ, Plumb R, Rajan J, Raymond C, Rouse G, Saenphimmachak C, Sehra HK, Sheridan E, Shownkeen R, Sims S, Skuce CD, Smith M, Steward C, Subramanian S, Sycamore N, Tracey A, Tromans A, Van Helmond Z, Wall M, Wallis JM, White S, Whitehead SL, Wilkinson JE, Willey DL, Williams H, Wilming L, Wray PW, Wu Z, Coulson A, Vaudin M, Sulston JE, Durbin R, Hubbard T, Wooster R, Dunham I, Carter NP, McVean G, Ross MT, Harrow J, Olson MV, Beck S, Rogers J, Bentley DR, Banerjee R, Bryant SP, Burford DC, Burrill WD, Clegg SM, Dhami P, Dovey O, Faulkner LM, Gribble SM, Langford CF, Pandian RD, Porter KM, Prigmore E: The DNA sequence and biological annotation of human chromosome 1.  Nature. 2006 May 18;441(7091):315-21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16710414</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Edgeworth J, Freemont P, Hogg N: Ionomycin-regulated phosphorylation of the myeloid calcium-binding protein p14. Nature. 1989 Nov 9;342(6246):189-92.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2478889</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Tobe T, Murakami K, Tomita M, Nozawa R: Amino acid sequences of 60B8 antigens induced in HL-60 cells by 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D3. The antigens are identical with macrophage-related protein-14 and -8. Chem Pharm Bull (Tokyo). 1989 Jun;37(6):1576-80.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2776242</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rasmussen HH, van Damme J, Puype M, Gesser B, Celis JE, Vandekerckhove J: Microsequences of 145 proteins recorded in the two-dimensional gel protein database of normal human epidermal keratinocytes. Electrophoresis. 1992 Dec;13(12):960-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1286667</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Miyasaki KT, Bodeau AL, Murthy AR, Lehrer RI: In vitro antimicrobial activity of the human neutrophil cytosolic S-100 protein complex, calprotectin, against Capnocytophaga sputigena. J Dent Res. 1993 Feb;72(2):517-23.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8423249</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rammes A, Roth J, Goebeler M, Klempt M, Hartmann M, Sorg C: Myeloid-related protein (MRP) 8 and MRP14, calcium-binding proteins of the S100 family, are secreted by activated monocytes via a novel, tubulin-dependent pathway. J Biol Chem. 1997 Apr 4;272(14):9496-502.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9083090</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Streichert T, Ebrahimnejad A, Ganzer S, Flayeh R, Wagener C, Brummer J: The microbial receptor CEACAM3 is linked to the calprotectin complex in granulocytes. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2001 Nov 23;289(1):191-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11708798</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Vogl T, Ludwig S, Goebeler M, Strey A, Thorey IS, Reichelt R, Foell D, Gerke V, Manitz MP, Nacken W, Werner S, Sorg C, Roth J: MRP8 and MRP14 control microtubule reorganization during transendothelial migration of phagocytes. Blood. 2004 Dec 15;104(13):4260-8. Epub 2004 Aug 26.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15331440</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Viemann D, Strey A, Janning A, Jurk K, Klimmek K, Vogl T, Hirono K, Ichida F, Foell D, Kehrel B, Gerke V, Sorg C, Roth J: Myeloid-related proteins 8 and 14 induce a specific inflammatory response in human microvascular endothelial cells. Blood. 2005 Apr 1;105(7):2955-62. Epub 2004 Dec 14.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15598812</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Nakatani Y, Yamazaki M, Chazin WJ, Yui S: Regulation of S100A8/A9 (calprotectin) binding to tumor cells by zinc ion and its implication for apoptosis-inducing activity. Mediators Inflamm. 2005 Oct 24;2005(5):280-92.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16258195</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bode G, Luken A, Kerkhoff C, Roth J, Ludwig S, Nacken W: Interaction between S100A8/A9 and annexin A6 is involved in the calcium-induced cell surface exposition of S100A8/A9. J Biol Chem. 2008 Nov 14;283(46):31776-84. Epub 2008 Sep 11.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18786929</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Han G, Ye M, Zhou H, Jiang X, Feng S, Jiang X, Tian R, Wan D, Zou H, Gu J: Large-scale phosphoproteome analysis of human liver tissue by enrichment and fractionation of phosphopeptides with strong anion exchange chromatography. Proteomics. 2008 Apr;8(7):1346-61.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18318008</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Carrascal M, Ovelleiro D, Casas V, Gay M, Abian J: Phosphorylation analysis of primary human T lymphocytes using sequential IMAC and titanium oxide enrichment. J Proteome Res. 2008 Dec;7(12):5167-76.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19367720</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Sroussi HY, Kohler GA, Agabian N, Villines D, Palefsky JM: Substitution of methionine 63 or 83 in S100A9 and cysteine 42 in S100A8 abrogate the antifungal activities of S100A8/A9: potential role for oxidative regulation. FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol. 2009 Jan;55(1):55-61. Epub 2008 Dec 11.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19087201</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Champaiboon C, Sappington KJ, Guenther BD, Ross KF, Herzberg MC: Calprotectin S100A9 calcium-binding loops I and II are essential for keratinocyte resistance to bacterial invasion. J Biol Chem. 2009 Mar 13;284(11):7078-90. Epub 2009 Jan 3.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19122197</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Oppermann FS, Gnad F, Olsen JV, Hornberger R, Greff Z, Keri G, Mann M, Daub H: Large-scale proteomics analysis of the human kinome.  Mol Cell Proteomics. 2009 Jul;8(7):1751-64. Epub 2009 Apr 15.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19369195</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bjork P, Bjork A, Vogl T, Stenstrom M, Liberg D, Olsson A, Roth J, Ivars F, Leanderson T: Identification of human S100A9 as a novel target for treatment of autoimmune disease via binding to quinoline-3-carboxamides. PLoS Biol. 2009 Apr 28;7(4):e97.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19402754</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Itou H, Yao M, Fujita I, Watanabe N, Suzuki M, Nishihira J, Tanaka I: The crystal structure of human MRP14 (S100A9), a Ca(2+)-dependent regulator protein in inflammatory process. J Mol Biol. 2002 Feb 15;316(2):265-76.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11851337</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Korndorfer IP, Brueckner F, Skerra A: The crystal structure of the human (S100A8/S100A9)2 heterotetramer, calprotectin, illustrates how conformational changes of interacting alpha-helices can determine specific association of two EF-hand proteins. J Mol Biol. 2007 Jul 27;370(5):887-98. Epub 2007 May 3.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17553524</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
