<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 19:05:05 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 19:05:05 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP02415</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>7908</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Enzyme</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Eukaryotic initiation factor 5A isoform 1</synonym>
    <synonym>Rev-binding factor</synonym>
    <synonym>eIF-4D</synonym>
    <synonym>eIF-5A</synonym>
    <synonym>eIF-5A-1</synonym>
    <synonym>eIF-5A1</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>EIF5A</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in RNA binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>mRNA-binding protein involved in translation elongation. Has an important function at the level of mRNA turnover, probably acting downstream of decapping. Involved in actin dynamics and cell cycle progression, mRNA decay and probably in a pathway involved in stress response and maintenance of cell wall integrity. With syntenin SDCBP, functions as a regulator of TP53/p53 and TP53/p53-dependent apoptosis. Regulates also TNF- alpha-mediated apoptosis. Mediates effects of polyamines on neuronal process extension and survival. May play an important role in brain development and function, and in skeletal muscle stem cell differentiation. Also described as a cellular cofactor of human T-cell leukemia virus type I (HTLV-1) Rex protein and of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) Rev protein, essential for mRNA export of retroviral transcripts</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB11140</accession>
      <name>Hypusine</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ribonucleoprotein binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ribosome binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>translation factor activity, nucleic acid binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>translation elongation factor activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>nucleic acid binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>rna binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>macromolecule metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>macromolecule modification</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>protein modification process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>peptidyl-amino acid modification</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>peptidyl-lysine modification</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>peptidyl-lysine modification to hypusine</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>regulation of translational termination</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>positive regulation of translational termination</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>regulation of translational elongation</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>positive regulation of translational elongation</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>biological regulation</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>regulation of biological process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>regulation of metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>regulation of macromolecule metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>regulation of gene expression</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>posttranscriptional regulation of gene expression</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>regulation of translation</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>translational frameshifting</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasm</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Nucleus</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Endoplasmic reticulum membrane</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Peripheral membrane protein</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasmic side</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Nucleus</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>nuclear pore complex</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>17p13-p12</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;465 bp
ATGGCAGATGACTTGGACTTCGAGACAGGAGATGCAGGGGCCTCAGCCACCTTCCCAATG
CAGTGCTCAGCATTACGTAAGAATGGCTTTGTGGTGCTCAAAGGCCGGCCATGTAAGATC
GTCGAGATGTCTACTTCGAAGACTGGCAAGCACGGCCACGCCAAGGTCCATCTGGTTGGT
ATTGACATCTTTACTGGGAAGAAATATGAAGATATCTGCCCGTCAACTCATAATATGGAT
GTCCCCAACATCAAAAGGAATGACTTCCAGCTGATTGGCATCCAGGATGGGTACCTATCA
CTGCTCCAGGACAGCGGGGAGGTACGAGAGGACCTTCGTCTCCCTGAGGGAGACCTTGGC
AAGGAGATTGAGCAGAAGTACGACTGTGGAGAAGAGATCCTGATCACGGTGCTGTCTGCC
ATGACAGAGGAGGCAGCTGTTGCAATCAAGGCCATGGCAAAATAA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>154</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>16832.1</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>4.86</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>eIF-5a</name>
        <pfam_id>PF01287</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
      <pfam>
        <name>KOW</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00467</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Eukaryotic translation initiation factor 5A-1
MADDLDFETGDAGASATFPMQCSALRKNGFVVLKGRPCKIVEMSTSKTGKHGHAKVHLVG
IDIFTGKKYEDICPSTHNMDVPNIKRNDFQLIGIQDGYLSLLQDSGEVREDLRLPEGDLG
KEIEQKYDCGEEILITVLSAMTEEAAVAIKAMAK</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>158258667</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P63241</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>IF5A1_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AK292615</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>EIF5A</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>EIF5A</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:3300</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Smit-McBride Z, Dever TE, Hershey JW, Merrick WC: Sequence determination and cDNA cloning of eukaryotic initiation factor 4D, the hypusine-containing protein. J Biol Chem. 1989 Jan 25;264(3):1578-83.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2492279</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ruhl M, Himmelspach M, Bahr GM, Hammerschmid F, Jaksche H, Wolff B, Aschauer H, Farrington GK, Probst H, Bevec D, et al.: Eukaryotic initiation factor 5A is a cellular target of the human immunodeficiency virus type 1 Rev activation domain mediating trans-activation. J Cell Biol. 1993 Dec;123(6 Pt 1):1309-20.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8253832</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Koettnitz K, Kappel B, Baumruker T, Hauber J, Bevec D: The genomic structure encoding human initiation factor eIF-5A.  Gene. 1994 Jul 8;144(2):249-52.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7545941</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Koettnitz K, Wohl T, Kappel B, Lottspeich F, Hauber J, Bevec D: Identification of a new member of the human eIF-5A gene family.  Gene. 1995 Jul 4;159(2):283-4.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7622067</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ota T, Suzuki Y, Nishikawa T, Otsuki T, Sugiyama T, Irie R, Wakamatsu A, Hayashi K, Sato H, Nagai K, Kimura K, Makita H, Sekine M, Obayashi M, Nishi T, Shibahara T, Tanaka T, Ishii S, Yamamoto J, Saito K, Kawai Y, Isono Y, Nakamura Y, Nagahari K, Murakami K, Yasuda T, Iwayanagi T, Wagatsuma M, Shiratori A, Sudo H, Hosoiri T, Kaku Y, Kodaira H, Kondo H, Sugawara M, Takahashi M, Kanda K, Yokoi T, Furuya T, Kikkawa E, Omura Y, Abe K, Kamihara K, Katsuta N, Sato K, Tanikawa M, Yamazaki M, Ninomiya K, Ishibashi T, Yamashita H, Murakawa K, Fujimori K, Tanai H, Kimata M, Watanabe M, Hiraoka S, Chiba Y, Ishida S, Ono Y, Takiguchi S, Watanabe S, Yosida M, Hotuta T, Kusano J, Kanehori K, Takahashi-Fujii A, Hara H, Tanase TO, Nomura Y, Togiya S, Komai F, Hara R, Takeuchi K, Arita M, Imose N, Musashino K, Yuuki H, Oshima A, Sasaki N, Aotsuka S, Yoshikawa Y, Matsunawa H, Ichihara T, Shiohata N, Sano S, Moriya S, Momiyama H, Satoh N, Takami S, Terashima Y, Suzuki O, Nakagawa S, Senoh A, Mizoguchi H, Goto Y, Shimizu F, Wakebe H, Hishigaki H, Watanabe T, Sugiyama A, Takemoto M, Kawakami B, Yamazaki M, Watanabe K, Kumagai A, Itakura S, Fukuzumi Y, Fujimori Y, Komiyama M, Tashiro H, Tanigami A, Fujiwara T, Ono T, Yamada K, Fujii Y, Ozaki K, Hirao M, Ohmori Y, Kawabata A, Hikiji T, Kobatake N, Inagaki H, Ikema Y, Okamoto S, Okitani R, Kawakami T, Noguchi S, Itoh T, Shigeta K, Senba T, Matsumura K, Nakajima Y, Mizuno T, Morinaga M, Sasaki M, Togashi T, Oyama M, Hata H, Watanabe M, Komatsu T, Mizushima-Sugano J, Satoh T, Shirai Y, Takahashi Y, Nakagawa K, Okumura K, Nagase T, Nomura N, Kikuchi H, Masuho Y, Yamashita R, Nakai K, Yada T, Nakamura Y, Ohara O, Isogai T, Sugano S: Complete sequencing and characterization of 21,243 full-length human cDNAs. Nat Genet. 2004 Jan;36(1):40-5. Epub 2003 Dec 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14702039</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Lee YB, Joe YA, Wolff EC, Dimitriadis EK, Park MH: Complex formation between deoxyhypusine synthase and its protein substrate, the eukaryotic translation initiation factor 5A (eIF5A) precursor. Biochem J. 1999 May 15;340 ( Pt 1):273-81.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10229683</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Park MH, Liu TY, Neece SH, Swiggard WJ: Eukaryotic initiation factor 4D. Purification from human red blood cells and the sequence of amino acids around its single hypusine residue. J Biol Chem. 1986 Nov 5;261(31):14515-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3095320</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rasmussen HH, van Damme J, Puype M, Gesser B, Celis JE, Vandekerckhove J: Microsequences of 145 proteins recorded in the two-dimensional gel protein database of normal human epidermal keratinocytes. Electrophoresis. 1992 Dec;13(12):960-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1286667</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shi XP, Yin KC, Zimolo ZA, Stern AM, Waxman L: The subcellular distribution of eukaryotic translation initiation factor, eIF-5A, in cultured cells. Exp Cell Res. 1996 Jun 15;225(2):348-56.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8660923</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Lipowsky G, Bischoff FR, Schwarzmaier P, Kraft R, Kostka S, Hartmann E, Kutay U, Gorlich D: Exportin 4: a mediator of a novel nuclear export pathway in higher eukaryotes. EMBO J. 2000 Aug 15;19(16):4362-71.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10944119</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Xu A, Jao DL, Chen KY: Identification of mRNA that binds to eukaryotic initiation factor 5A by affinity co-purification and differential display. Biochem J. 2004 Dec 15;384(Pt 3):585-90.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15303967</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Cracchiolo BM, Heller DS, Clement PM, Wolff EC, Park MH, Hanauske-Abel HM: Eukaryotic initiation factor 5A-1 (eIF5A-1) as a diagnostic marker for aberrant proliferation in intraepithelial neoplasia of the vulva. Gynecol Oncol. 2004 Jul;94(1):217-22.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15262146</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Li AL, Li HY, Jin BF, Ye QN, Zhou T, Yu XD, Pan X, Man JH, He K, Yu M, Hu MR, Wang J, Yang SC, Shen BF, Zhang XM: A novel eIF5A complex functions as a regulator of p53 and p53-dependent apoptosis. J Biol Chem. 2004 Nov 19;279(47):49251-8. Epub 2004 Sep 14.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15371445</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Taylor CA, Senchyna M, Flanagan J, Joyce EM, Cliche DO, Boone AN, Culp-Stewart S, Thompson JE: Role of eIF5A in TNF-alpha-mediated apoptosis of lamina cribrosa cells.  Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2004 Oct;45(10):3568-76.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15452064</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Clement PM, Johansson HE, Wolff EC, Park MH: Differential expression of eIF5A-1 and eIF5A-2 in human cancer cells.  FEBS J. 2006 Mar;273(6):1102-14.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16519677</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Schrader R, Young C, Kozian D, Hoffmann R, Lottspeich F: Temperature-sensitive eIF5A mutant accumulates transcripts targeted to the nonsense-mediated decay pathway. J Biol Chem. 2006 Nov 17;281(46):35336-46. Epub 2006 Sep 20.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16987817</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kim SC, Sprung R, Chen Y, Xu Y, Ball H, Pei J, Cheng T, Kho Y, Xiao H, Xiao L, Grishin NV, White M, Yang XJ, Zhao Y: Substrate and functional diversity of lysine acetylation revealed by a proteomics survey. Mol Cell. 2006 Aug;23(4):607-18.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16916647</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Taylor CA, Sun Z, Cliche DO, Ming H, Eshaque B, Jin S, Hopkins MT, Thai B, Thompson JE: Eukaryotic translation initiation factor 5A induces apoptosis in colon cancer cells and associates with the nucleus in response to tumour necrosis factor alpha signalling. Exp Cell Res. 2007 Feb 1;313(3):437-49. Epub 2006 Oct 28.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17187778</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kang KR, Kim YS, Wolff EC, Park MH: Specificity of the deoxyhypusine hydroxylase-eukaryotic translation initiation factor (eIF5A) interaction: identification of amino acid residues of the enzyme required for binding of its substrate, deoxyhypusine-containing eIF5A. J Biol Chem. 2007 Mar 16;282(11):8300-8. Epub 2007 Jan 9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17213197</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Huang Y, Higginson DS, Hester L, Park MH, Snyder SH: Neuronal growth and survival mediated by eIF5A, a polyamine-modified translation initiation factor. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007 Mar 6;104(10):4194-9. Epub 2007 Feb 28.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17360499</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Cano VS, Jeon GA, Johansson HE, Henderson CA, Park JH, Valentini SR, Hershey JW, Park MH: Mutational analyses of human eIF5A-1--identification of amino acid residues critical for eIF5A activity and hypusine modification. FEBS J. 2008 Jan;275(1):44-58. Epub 2007 Dec 6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18067580</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gauci S, Helbig AO, Slijper M, Krijgsveld J, Heck AJ, Mohammed S: Lys-N and trypsin cover complementary parts of the phosphoproteome in a refined SCX-based approach. Anal Chem. 2009 Jun 1;81(11):4493-501.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19413330</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Lee SB, Park JH, Kaevel J, Sramkova M, Weigert R, Park MH: The effect of hypusine modification on the intracellular localization of eIF5A. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2009 Jun 12;383(4):497-502. Epub 2009 Apr 18.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19379712</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Facchiano AM, Stiuso P, Chiusano ML, Caraglia M, Giuberti G, Marra M, Abbruzzese A, Colonna G: Homology modelling of the human eukaryotic initiation factor 5A (eIF-5A).  Protein Eng. 2001 Nov;14(11):881-90.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11742107</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
