<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:03:26 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:03:26 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP07857</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13567</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Aging-associated gene 8 protein</synonym>
    <synonym>SIG-1R</synonym>
    <synonym>SR-BP</synonym>
    <synonym>SR31747-binding protein</synonym>
    <synonym>Sigma 1-type opioid receptor</synonym>
    <synonym>Sigma1-receptor</synonym>
    <synonym>Sigma1R</synonym>
    <synonym>hSigmaR1</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>SIGMAR1</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in C-8 sterol isomerase activity</general_function>
  <specific_function>Functions in lipid transport from the endoplasmic reticulum and is involved in a wide array of cellular functions probably through regulation of the biogenesis of lipid microdomains at the plasma membrane. Involved in the regulation of different receptors it plays a role in BDNF signaling and EGF signaling. Also regulates ion channels like the potassium channel and could modulate neurotransmitter release. Plays a role in calcium signaling through modulation together with ANK2 of the ITP3R-dependent calcium efflux at the endoplasmic reticulum. Plays a role in several other cell functions including proliferation, survival and death. Originally identified for its ability to bind various psychoactive drugs it is involved in learning processes, memory and mood alteration</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01920</accession>
      <name>Dextromethorphan</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB14553</accession>
      <name>Remoxipride</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB14790</accession>
      <name>Pentazocine</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>catalytic activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>isomerase activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>intramolecular oxidoreductase activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>intramolecular oxidoreductase activity, transposing c=c bonds</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>c-8 sterol isomerase activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>small molecule metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>alcohol metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>sterol metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>ergosterol metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>ergosterol biosynthetic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>organelle</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>membrane-bounded organelle</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>intracellular membrane-bounded organelle</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>endoplasmic reticulum</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Nucleus inner membrane</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Nucleus outer membrane</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Endoplasmic reticulum membrane</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Lipid droplet</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Cell junction</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Cell membrane</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Cell projection</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>growth cone</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:9</chromosome_location>
    <locus>9p13.3</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;672 bp
ATGCAGTGGGCCGTGGGCCGGCGGTGGGCGTGGGCCGCGCTGCTCCTGGCTGTCGCAGCG
GTGCTGACCCAGGTCGTCTGGCTCTGGCTGGGTACGCAGAGCTTCGTCTTCCAGCGCGAA
GAGATAGCGCAGTTGGCGCGGCAGTACGCTGGGCTGGACCACGAGCTGGCCTTCTCTCGT
CTGATCGTGGAGCTGCGGCGGCTGCACCCAGGCCACGTGCTGCCCGACGAGGAGCTGCAG
TGGGTGTTCGTGAATGCGGGTGGCTGGATGGGCGCCATGTGCCTTCTGCACGCCTCGCTG
TCCGAGTATGTGCTGCTCTTCGGCACCGCCTTGGGCTCCCGCGGCCACTCGGGGCGCTAC
TGGGCTGAGATCTCGGATACCATCATCTCTGGCACCTTCCACCAGTGGAGAGAGGGCACC
ACCAAAAGTGAGGTCTTCTACCCAGGGGAGACGGTAGTACACGGGCCTGGTGAGGCAACA
GCTGTGGAGTGGGGGCCAAACACATGGATGGTGGAGTACGGCCGGGGCGTCATCCCATCC
ACCCTGGCCTTCGCGCTGGCCGACACTGTCTTCAGCACCCAGGACTTCCTCACCCTCTTC
TATACTCTTCGCTCCTATGCTCGGGGCCTCCGGCTTGAGCTCACCACCTACCTCTTTGGC
CAGGACCCTTGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>223</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>25127.5</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>5.87</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>ERG2_Sigma1R</name>
        <pfam_id>PF04622</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>10-30</region>
      <region>81-101</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Sigma non-opioid intracellular receptor 1
MQWAVGRRWAWAALLLAVAAVLTQVVWLWLGTQSFVFQREEIAQLARQYAGLDHELAFSR
LIVELRRLHPGHVLPDEELQWVFVNAGGWMGAMCLLHASLSEYVLLFGTALGSRGHSGRY
WAEISDTIISGTFHQWREGTTKSEVFYPGETVVHGPGEATAVEWGPNTWMVEYGRGVIPS
TLAFALADTVFSTQDFLTLFYTLRSYARGLRLELTTYLFGQDP</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id/>
  <uniprot_id>Q99720</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>SGMR1_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>U75283</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>SIGMAR1</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>SIGMAR1</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:8157</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kekuda R, Prasad PD, Fei YJ, Leibach FH, Ganapathy V: Cloning and functional expression of the human type 1 sigma receptor (hSigmaR1). Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1996 Dec 13;229(2):553-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8954936</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Jbilo O, Vidal H, Paul R, De Nys N, Bensaid M, Silve S, Carayon P, Davi D, Galiegue S, Bourrie B, Guillemot JC, Ferrara P, Loison G, Maffrand JP, Le Fur G, Casellas P: Purification and characterization of the human SR 31747A-binding protein. A nuclear membrane protein related to yeast sterol isomerase. J Biol Chem. 1997 Oct 24;272(43):27107-15.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9341151</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Prasad PD, Li HW, Fei YJ, Ganapathy ME, Fujita T, Plumley LH, Yang-Feng TL, Leibach FH, Ganapathy V: Exon-intron structure, analysis of promoter region, and chromosomal localization of the human type 1 sigma receptor gene. J Neurochem. 1998 Feb;70(2):443-51.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9453537</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ota T, Suzuki Y, Nishikawa T, Otsuki T, Sugiyama T, Irie R, Wakamatsu A, Hayashi K, Sato H, Nagai K, Kimura K, Makita H, Sekine M, Obayashi M, Nishi T, Shibahara T, Tanaka T, Ishii S, Yamamoto J, Saito K, Kawai Y, Isono Y, Nakamura Y, Nagahari K, Murakami K, Yasuda T, Iwayanagi T, Wagatsuma M, Shiratori A, Sudo H, Hosoiri T, Kaku Y, Kodaira H, Kondo H, Sugawara M, Takahashi M, Kanda K, Yokoi T, Furuya T, Kikkawa E, Omura Y, Abe K, Kamihara K, Katsuta N, Sato K, Tanikawa M, Yamazaki M, Ninomiya K, Ishibashi T, Yamashita H, Murakawa K, Fujimori K, Tanai H, Kimata M, Watanabe M, Hiraoka S, Chiba Y, Ishida S, Ono Y, Takiguchi S, Watanabe S, Yosida M, Hotuta T, Kusano J, Kanehori K, Takahashi-Fujii A, Hara H, Tanase TO, Nomura Y, Togiya S, Komai F, Hara R, Takeuchi K, Arita M, Imose N, Musashino K, Yuuki H, Oshima A, Sasaki N, Aotsuka S, Yoshikawa Y, Matsunawa H, Ichihara T, Shiohata N, Sano S, Moriya S, Momiyama H, Satoh N, Takami S, Terashima Y, Suzuki O, Nakagawa S, Senoh A, Mizoguchi H, Goto Y, Shimizu F, Wakebe H, Hishigaki H, Watanabe T, Sugiyama A, Takemoto M, Kawakami B, Yamazaki M, Watanabe K, Kumagai A, Itakura S, Fukuzumi Y, Fujimori Y, Komiyama M, Tashiro H, Tanigami A, Fujiwara T, Ono T, Yamada K, Fujii Y, Ozaki K, Hirao M, Ohmori Y, Kawabata A, Hikiji T, Kobatake N, Inagaki H, Ikema Y, Okamoto S, Okitani R, Kawakami T, Noguchi S, Itoh T, Shigeta K, Senba T, Matsumura K, Nakajima Y, Mizuno T, Morinaga M, Sasaki M, Togashi T, Oyama M, Hata H, Watanabe M, Komatsu T, Mizushima-Sugano J, Satoh T, Shirai Y, Takahashi Y, Nakagawa K, Okumura K, Nagase T, Nomura N, Kikuchi H, Masuho Y, Yamashita R, Nakai K, Yada T, Nakamura Y, Ohara O, Isogai T, Sugano S: Complete sequencing and characterization of 21,243 full-length human cDNAs. Nat Genet. 2004 Jan;36(1):40-5. Epub 2003 Dec 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14702039</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Humphray SJ, Oliver K, Hunt AR, Plumb RW, Loveland JE, Howe KL, Andrews TD, Searle S, Hunt SE, Scott CE, Jones MC, Ainscough R, Almeida JP, Ambrose KD, Ashwell RI, Babbage AK, Babbage S, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Banerjee R, Barker DJ, Barlow KF, Bates K, Beasley H, Beasley O, Bird CP, Bray-Allen S, Brown AJ, Brown JY, Burford D, Burrill W, Burton J, Carder C, Carter NP, Chapman JC, Chen Y, Clarke G, Clark SY, Clee CM, Clegg S, Collier RE, Corby N, Crosier M, Cummings AT, Davies J, Dhami P, Dunn M, Dutta I, Dyer LW, Earthrowl ME, Faulkner L, Fleming CJ, Frankish A, Frankland JA, French L, Fricker DG, Garner P, Garnett J, Ghori J, Gilbert JG, Glison C, Grafham DV, Gribble S, Griffiths C, Griffiths-Jones S, Grocock R, Guy J, Hall RE, Hammond S, Harley JL, Harrison ES, Hart EA, Heath PD, Henderson CD, Hopkins BL, Howard PJ, Howden PJ, Huckle E, Johnson C, Johnson D, Joy AA, Kay M, Keenan S, Kershaw JK, Kimberley AM, King A, Knights A, Laird GK, Langford C, Lawlor S, Leongamornlert DA, Leversha M, Lloyd C, Lloyd DM, Lovell J, Martin S, Mashreghi-Mohammadi M, Matthews L, McLaren S, McLay KE, McMurray A, Milne S, Nickerson T, Nisbett J, Nordsiek G, Pearce AV, Peck AI, Porter KM, Pandian R, Pelan S, Phillimore B, Povey S, Ramsey Y, Rand V, Scharfe M, Sehra HK, Shownkeen R, Sims SK, Skuce CD, Smith M, Steward CA, Swarbreck D, Sycamore N, Tester J, Thorpe A, Tracey A, Tromans A, Thomas DW, Wall M, Wallis JM, West AP, Whitehead SL, Willey DL, Williams SA, Wilming L, Wray PW, Young L, Ashurst JL, Coulson A, Blocker H, Durbin R, Sulston JE, Hubbard T, Jackson MJ, Bentley DR, Beck S, Rogers J, Dunham I: DNA sequence and analysis of human chromosome 9.  Nature. 2004 May 27;429(6990):369-74.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15164053</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Dussossoy D, Carayon P, Belugou S, Feraut D, Bord A, Goubet C, Roque C, Vidal H, Combes T, Loison G, Casellas P: Colocalization of sterol isomerase and sigma(1) receptor at endoplasmic reticulum and nuclear envelope level. Eur J Biochem. 1999 Jul;263(2):377-86.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10406945</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ganapathy ME, Prasad PD, Huang W, Seth P, Leibach FH, Ganapathy V: Molecular and ligand-binding characterization of the sigma-receptor in the Jurkat human T lymphocyte cell line. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 1999 Apr;289(1):251-60.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10087012</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Seth P, Ganapathy ME, Conway SJ, Bridges CD, Smith SB, Casellas P, Ganapathy V: Expression pattern of the type 1 sigma receptor in the brain and identity of critical anionic amino acid residues in the ligand-binding domain of the receptor. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2001 Jul 25;1540(1):59-67.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11476895</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ola MS, Moore P, El-Sherbeny A, Roon P, Agarwal N, Sarthy VP, Casellas P, Ganapathy V, Smith SB: Expression pattern of sigma receptor 1 mRNA and protein in mammalian retina. Brain Res Mol Brain Res. 2001 Nov 1;95(1-2):86-95.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11687279</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wang L, Duncan G: Silencing of sigma-1 receptor induces cell death in human lens cells.  Exp Cell Res. 2006 May 1;312(8):1439-46. Epub 2006 Feb 9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16472803</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Satoh F, Miyatake R, Furukawa A, Suwaki H: Lack of association between sigma receptor gene variants and schizophrenia. Psychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2004 Aug;58(4):359-63.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15298647</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Remoxipride</name>
        <accession>HMDB14553</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Lang A, Soosaar A, Koks S, Volke V, Bourin M, Bradwejn J, Vasar E: Pharmacological comparison of antipsychotic drugs and sigma-antagonists in rodents. Pharmacol Toxicol. 1994 Sep-Oct;75(3-4):222-7.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>7800667</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Remoxipride</name>
        <accession>HMDB14553</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Okuyama S: [Atypical antipsychotic profiles of sigma receptor ligands].  Nihon Yakurigaku Zasshi. 1999 Jul;114(1):13-23.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>10562961</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pentazocine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14790</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Chien CC, Pasternak GW: (-)-Pentazocine analgesia in mice: interactions with a sigma receptor system.  Eur J Pharmacol. 1995 Dec 27;294(1):303-8.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>8788445</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pentazocine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14790</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Colabufo NA, Contino M, Inglese C, Niso M, Perrone R, Roperto S, Roperto F: In vitro and ex vivo characterization of sigma-1 and sigma-2 receptors: agonists and antagonists in biological assays. Cent Nerv Syst Agents Med Chem. 2009 Sep;9(3):161-71.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>20021350</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pentazocine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14790</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Dun Y, Thangaraju M, Prasad P, Ganapathy V, Smith SB: Prevention of excitotoxicity in primary retinal ganglion cells by (+)-pentazocine, a sigma receptor-1 specific ligand. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2007 Oct;48(10):4785-94.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17898305</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pentazocine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14790</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Mamolo MG, Zampieri D, Zanette C, Florio C, Collina S, Urbano M, Azzolina O, Vio L: Substituted benzylaminoalkylindoles with preference for the sigma2 binding site.  Eur J Med Chem. 2008 Oct;43(10):2073-81. Epub 2007 Sep 26.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>18069094</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pentazocine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14790</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Pal A, Hajipour AR, Fontanilla D, Ramachandran S, Chu UB, Mavlyutov T, Ruoho AE: Identification of regions of the sigma-1 receptor ligand binding site using a novel photoprobe. Mol Pharmacol. 2007 Oct;72(4):921-33. Epub 2007 Jul 10.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17622576</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
