<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:19:10 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:19:10 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP09081</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>14825</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>SCN2B</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in voltage-gated sodium channel activity</general_function>
  <specific_function>Crucial in the assembly, expression, and functional modulation of the heterotrimeric complex of the sodium channel. The subunit beta-2 causes an increase in the plasma membrane surface area and in its folding into microvilli. Interacts with TNR may play a crucial role in clustering and regulation of activity of sodium channels at nodes of Ranvier</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00588</accession>
      <name>Sodium</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15045</accession>
      <name>Zonisamide</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>cell part</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>membrane</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Membrane</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Single-pass type I membrane protein</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>11q23</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;648 bp
ATGCAAAGAGATGCCTGGTTACTTCGCCCTGCCTTCAGCCTCAACGGGCTCAGTCTCTTT
TTCTCTTTGGTGCCACCAGGACGGAGCATGGAGGTCACAGTACCTGCCACCCTCAACGTC
CTCAATGGCTCTGACGCCCGCCAGCCCTGCACCTTCAACTCCTGCTACACAGTGAACCAC
AAACAGTTCTCCCTGAACTGGAGTTACCAGGAGTGCAACAACTGCTCTGAGGAGATGTTC
CTCCAGTTCCGCATGAAGATCATTAACCTGAAGCTGGAGCGGTTTCAAGACCGCGTGGAG
TTCTCAGGGAACCCCAGCAAGTACGATGTGTCGGTGATGCTGAGAAACGTGCAGCCGGAG
GATGAGGGGATTTACAACTGCTACATCATGAACCCCCCTGACCGCCACCGTGGCCATGGC
AAGATCCATCTGCAGGTCCTCATGGAAGAGCCCCCTGAGCGGGACTCCACGGTGGCCGTG
ATTGTGGGTGCCTCCGTCGGGGGCTTCCTGGCTGTGGTCATCTTGGTGCTGACGGCGGTC
AAGTGTGTGAGGAGAAAAAAAGAGCAGAAGCTGAGCACAGATGACCTGAAGACCGAGGAG
GAGGGCAAGACGGACGGTGAAGGCAACCCGGATGATGGCGCCAAGTAG</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>215</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>24325.7</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>6.35</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>V-set</name>
        <pfam_id>PF07686</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>160-180</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>1-29</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Sodium channel subunit beta-2
MHRDAWLPRPAFSLTGLSLFFSLVPPGRSMEVTVPATLNVLNGSDARLPCTFNSCYTVNH
KQFSLNWTYQECNNCSEEMFLQFRMKIINLKLERFQDRVEFSGNPSKYDVSVMLRNVQPE
DEGIYNCYIMNPPDRHRGHGKIHLQVLMEEPPERDSTVAVIVGASVGGFLAVVILVLMVV
KCVRRKKEQKLSTDDLKTEEEGKTDGEGNPDDGAK</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>3309111</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>O60939</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>SCN2B_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AF007783</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>SCN2B</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>SCN2B</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:10589</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Eubanks J, Srinivasan J, Dinulos MB, Disteche CM, Catterall WA: Structure and chromosomal localization of the beta2 subunit of the human brain sodium channel. Neuroreport. 1997 Aug 18;8(12):2775-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9295116</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bolino A, Seri M, Caroli F, Eubanks J, Srinivasan J, Mandich P, Schenone A, Quattrone A, Romeo G, Catterall WA, Devoto M: Exclusion of the SCN2B gene as candidate for CMT4B.  Eur J Hum Genet. 1998 Nov-Dec;6(6):629-34.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9887383</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Clark HF, Gurney AL, Abaya E, Baker K, Baldwin D, Brush J, Chen J, Chow B, Chui C, Crowley C, Currell B, Deuel B, Dowd P, Eaton D, Foster J, Grimaldi C, Gu Q, Hass PE, Heldens S, Huang A, Kim HS, Klimowski L, Jin Y, Johnson S, Lee J, Lewis L, Liao D, Mark M, Robbie E, Sanchez C, Schoenfeld J, Seshagiri S, Simmons L, Singh J, Smith V, Stinson J, Vagts A, Vandlen R, Watanabe C, Wieand D, Woods K, Xie MH, Yansura D, Yi S, Yu G, Yuan J, Zhang M, Zhang Z, Goddard A, Wood WI, Godowski P, Gray A: The secreted protein discovery initiative (SPDI), a large-scale effort to identify novel human secreted and transmembrane proteins: a bioinformatics assessment. Genome Res. 2003 Oct;13(10):2265-70. Epub 2003 Sep 15.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12975309</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Zonisamide</name>
        <accession>HMDB15045</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Janszky J: [Role of zonisamid in treating epilepsy, Parkinson disorders and other neurological diseases]. Ideggyogy Sz. 2009 Nov 30;62(11-12):383-9.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>20025128</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Zonisamide</name>
        <accession>HMDB15045</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Kothare SV, Kaleyias J: Zonisamide: review of pharmacology, clinical efficacy, tolerability, and safety.  Expert Opin Drug Metab Toxicol. 2008 Apr;4(4):493-506.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>18433351</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Zonisamide</name>
        <accession>HMDB15045</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Schulze-Bonhage A: Zonisamide in the treatment of epilepsy.  Expert Opin Pharmacother. 2010 Jan;11(1):115-26.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>20001433</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Zonisamide</name>
        <accession>HMDB15045</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Sobieszek G, Borowicz KK, Kimber-Trojnar Z, Malek R, Piskorska B, Czuczwar SJ: Zonisamide: a new antiepileptic drug.  Pol J Pharmacol. 2003 Sep-Oct;55(5):683-9.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>14704463</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Zonisamide</name>
        <accession>HMDB15045</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Sonsalla PK, Wong LY, Winnik B, Buckley B: The antiepileptic drug zonisamide inhibits MAO-B and attenuates MPTP toxicity in mice: clinical relevance. Exp Neurol. 2010 Feb;221(2):329-34. Epub 2009 Dec 4.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>19948168</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Zonisamide</name>
        <accession>HMDB15045</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Leppik IE: Zonisamide: chemistry, mechanism of action, and pharmacokinetics.  Seizure. 2004 Dec;13 Suppl 1:S5-9; discussion S10.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>15511691</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Zonisamide</name>
        <accession>HMDB15045</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Zaccara G, Specchio LM: Long-term safety and effectiveness of zonisamide in the treatment of epilepsy: a review of the literature. Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat. 2009;5:249-59. Epub 2009 May 20.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>19557119</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
