<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 19:03:01 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 19:03:01 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP02150</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>7633</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Enzyme</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>HB-GAM</synonym>
    <synonym>HBBM</synonym>
    <synonym>HBGF-8</synonym>
    <synonym>HBNF-1</synonym>
    <synonym>Heparin-binding brain mitogen</synonym>
    <synonym>Heparin-binding growth factor 8</synonym>
    <synonym>Heparin-binding growth-associated molecule</synonym>
    <synonym>Heparin-binding neurite outgrowth-promoting factor 1</synonym>
    <synonym>OSF-1</synonym>
    <synonym>Osteoblast-specific factor 1</synonym>
    <synonym>PTN</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>PTN</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in growth factor activity</general_function>
  <specific_function>Heparin binding mitogenic protein. Has neurite extension activity</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01394</accession>
      <name>Heparin</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>protein binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>receptor binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>growth factor activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Secreted</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:7</chromosome_location>
    <locus>7q33</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;507 bp
ATGCAGGCTCAACAGTACCAGCAGCAGCGTCGAAAATTTGCAGCTGCCTTCTTGGCATTC
ATTTTCATACTGGCAGCTGTGGATACTGCTGAAGCAGGGAAGAAAGAGAAACCAGAAAAA
AAAGTGAAGAAGTCTGACTGTGGAGAATGGCAGTGGAGTGTGTGTGTGCCCACCAGTGGA
GACTGTGGGCTGGGCACACGGGAGGGCACTCGGACTGGAGCTGAGTGCAAGCAAACCATG
AAGACCCAGAGATGTAAGATCCCCTGCAACTGGAAGAAGCAATTTGGCGCGGAGTGCAAA
TACCAGTTCCAGGCCTGGGGAGAATGTGACCTGAACACAGCCCTGAAGACCAGAACTGGA
AGTCTGAAGCGAGCCCTGCACAATGCCGAATGCCAGAAGACTGTCACCATCTCCAAGCCC
TGTGGCAAACTGACCAAGCCCAAACCTCAAGCAGAATCTAAGAAGAAGAAAAAGGAAGGC
AAGAAACAGGAGAAGATGCTGGATTAA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>168</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>18941.9</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>10.3</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>PTN_MK_C</name>
        <pfam_id>PF01091</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
      <pfam>
        <name>PTN_MK_N</name>
        <pfam_id>PF05196</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>1-32</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Pleiotrophin
MQAQQYQQQRRKFAAAFLAFIFILAAVDTAEAGKKEKPEKKVKKSDCGEWQWSVCVPTSG
DCGLGTREGTRTGAECKQTMKTQRCKIPCNWKKQFGAECKYQFQAWGECDLNTALKTRTG
SLKRALHNAECQKTVTISKPCGKLTKPKPQAESKKKKKEGKKQEKMLD</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>2564040</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P21246</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>PTN_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AB004306</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>PTN</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>PTN</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:9630</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Tezuka K, Takeshita S, Hakeda Y, Kumegawa M, Kikuno R, Hashimoto-Gotoh T: Isolation of mouse and human cDNA clones encoding a protein expressed specifically in osteoblasts and brain tissues. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1990 Nov 30;173(1):246-51.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1701634</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Li YS, Milner PG, Chauhan AK, Watson MA, Hoffman RM, Kodner CM, Milbrandt J, Deuel TF: Cloning and expression of a developmentally regulated protein that induces mitogenic and neurite outgrowth activity. Science. 1990 Dec 21;250(4988):1690-4.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2270483</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kretschmer PJ, Fairhurst JL, Decker MM, Chan CP, Gluzman Y, Bohlen P, Kovesdi I: Cloning, characterization and developmental regulation of two members of a novel human gene family of neurite outgrowth-promoting proteins. Growth Factors. 1991;5(2):99-114.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1768439</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Milner PG, Shah D, Veile R, Donis-Keller H, Kumar BV: Cloning, nucleotide sequence, and chromosome localization of the human pleiotrophin gene. Biochemistry. 1992 Dec 8;31(48):12023-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1457401</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kretschmer PJ, Fairhurst JL, Hulmes JD, Popjes ML, Bohlen P, Kovesdi I: Genomic organization of the human HBNF gene and characterization of an HBNF variant protein as a splice mutant. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1993 Apr 30;192(2):420-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8484754</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Masuda H, Tsujimura A, Yoshioka M, Arai Y, Kuboki Y, Mukai T, Nakamura T, Tsuji H, Nakagawa M, Hashimoto-Gotoh T: Bone mass loss due to estrogen deficiency is compensated in transgenic mice overexpressing human osteoblast stimulating factor-1. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1997 Sep 18;238(2):528-33.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9299545</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ota T, Suzuki Y, Nishikawa T, Otsuki T, Sugiyama T, Irie R, Wakamatsu A, Hayashi K, Sato H, Nagai K, Kimura K, Makita H, Sekine M, Obayashi M, Nishi T, Shibahara T, Tanaka T, Ishii S, Yamamoto J, Saito K, Kawai Y, Isono Y, Nakamura Y, Nagahari K, Murakami K, Yasuda T, Iwayanagi T, Wagatsuma M, Shiratori A, Sudo H, Hosoiri T, Kaku Y, Kodaira H, Kondo H, Sugawara M, Takahashi M, Kanda K, Yokoi T, Furuya T, Kikkawa E, Omura Y, Abe K, Kamihara K, Katsuta N, Sato K, Tanikawa M, Yamazaki M, Ninomiya K, Ishibashi T, Yamashita H, Murakawa K, Fujimori K, Tanai H, Kimata M, Watanabe M, Hiraoka S, Chiba Y, Ishida S, Ono Y, Takiguchi S, Watanabe S, Yosida M, Hotuta T, Kusano J, Kanehori K, Takahashi-Fujii A, Hara H, Tanase TO, Nomura Y, Togiya S, Komai F, Hara R, Takeuchi K, Arita M, Imose N, Musashino K, Yuuki H, Oshima A, Sasaki N, Aotsuka S, Yoshikawa Y, Matsunawa H, Ichihara T, Shiohata N, Sano S, Moriya S, Momiyama H, Satoh N, Takami S, Terashima Y, Suzuki O, Nakagawa S, Senoh A, Mizoguchi H, Goto Y, Shimizu F, Wakebe H, Hishigaki H, Watanabe T, Sugiyama A, Takemoto M, Kawakami B, Yamazaki M, Watanabe K, Kumagai A, Itakura S, Fukuzumi Y, Fujimori Y, Komiyama M, Tashiro H, Tanigami A, Fujiwara T, Ono T, Yamada K, Fujii Y, Ozaki K, Hirao M, Ohmori Y, Kawabata A, Hikiji T, Kobatake N, Inagaki H, Ikema Y, Okamoto S, Okitani R, Kawakami T, Noguchi S, Itoh T, Shigeta K, Senba T, Matsumura K, Nakajima Y, Mizuno T, Morinaga M, Sasaki M, Togashi T, Oyama M, Hata H, Watanabe M, Komatsu T, Mizushima-Sugano J, Satoh T, Shirai Y, Takahashi Y, Nakagawa K, Okumura K, Nagase T, Nomura N, Kikuchi H, Masuho Y, Yamashita R, Nakai K, Yada T, Nakamura Y, Ohara O, Isogai T, Sugano S: Complete sequencing and characterization of 21,243 full-length human cDNAs. Nat Genet. 2004 Jan;36(1):40-5. Epub 2003 Dec 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14702039</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Scherer SW, Cheung J, MacDonald JR, Osborne LR, Nakabayashi K, Herbrick JA, Carson AR, Parker-Katiraee L, Skaug J, Khaja R, Zhang J, Hudek AK, Li M, Haddad M, Duggan GE, Fernandez BA, Kanematsu E, Gentles S, Christopoulos CC, Choufani S, Kwasnicka D, Zheng XH, Lai Z, Nusskern D, Zhang Q, Gu Z, Lu F, Zeesman S, Nowaczyk MJ, Teshima I, Chitayat D, Shuman C, Weksberg R, Zackai EH, Grebe TA, Cox SR, Kirkpatrick SJ, Rahman N, Friedman JM, Heng HH, Pelicci PG, Lo-Coco F, Belloni E, Shaffer LG, Pober B, Morton CC, Gusella JF, Bruns GA, Korf BR, Quade BJ, Ligon AH, Ferguson H, Higgins AW, Leach NT, Herrick SR, Lemyre E, Farra CG, Kim HG, Summers AM, Gripp KW, Roberts W, Szatmari P, Winsor EJ, Grzeschik KH, Teebi A, Minassian BA, Kere J, Armengol L, Pujana MA, Estivill X, Wilson MD, Koop BF, Tosi S, Moore GE, Boright AP, Zlotorynski E, Kerem B, Kroisel PM, Petek E, Oscier DG, Mould SJ, Dohner H, Dohner K, Rommens JM, Vincent JB, Venter JC, Li PW, Mural RJ, Adams MD, Tsui LC: Human chromosome 7: DNA sequence and biology.  Science. 2003 May 2;300(5620):767-72. Epub 2003 Apr 10.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12690205</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Huber D, Gautschi-Sova P, Bohlen P: Amino-terminal sequences of a novel heparin-binding protein from human, bovine, rat, and chick brain: high interspecies homology. Neurochem Res. 1990 Apr;15(4):435-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2388713</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wellstein A, Fang WJ, Khatri A, Lu Y, Swain SS, Dickson RB, Sasse J, Riegel AT, Lippman ME: A heparin-binding growth factor secreted from breast cancer cells homologous to a developmentally regulated cytokine. J Biol Chem. 1992 Feb 5;267(4):2582-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1733956</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Novotny WF, Maffi T, Mehta RL, Milner PG: Identification of novel heparin-releasable proteins, as well as the cytokines midkine and pleiotrophin, in human postheparin plasma. Arterioscler Thromb. 1993 Dec;13(12):1798-805.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8241100</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hulmes JD, Seddon AP, Decker MM, Bohlen P: Comparison of the disulfide bond arrangements of human recombinant and bovine brain heparin binding neurite-promoting factors. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1993 Apr 30;192(2):738-46.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8484780</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
