<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:03:02 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:03:02 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP07821</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13530</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>CMLC1</synonym>
    <synonym>Cardiac myosin light chain 1</synonym>
    <synonym>MLC1SB</synonym>
    <synonym>Myosin light chain 1, slow-twitch muscle B/ventricular isoform</synonym>
    <synonym>Ventricular/slow twitch myosin alkali light chain</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>MYL3</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in calcium ion binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Regulatory light chain of myosin. Does not bind calcium</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>cation binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>metal ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>calcium ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:3</chromosome_location>
    <locus>3p21.3-p21.2</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;588 bp
ATGGCCCCCAAAAAGCCAGAGCCCAAGAAGGATGATGCCAAGGCAGCCCCCAAGGCAGCT
CCAGCTCCCGCACCTCCCCCTGAGCCTGAGCGCCCTAAGGAGGTCGAGTTTGATGCTTCC
AAGATCAAGATTGAGTTCACACCTGAGCAGATTGAAGAGTTCAAGGAAGCCTTCATGCTG
TTCGACCGCACACCCAAGTGTGAGATGAAGATCACCTACGGGCAGTGTGGGGATGTCCTG
CGGGCGCTGGGCCAGAACCCCACACAGGCAGAAGTGCTCCGTGTCCTGGGGAAGCCAAGA
CAGGAAGAGCTCAATACCAAGATGATGGACTTTGAAACTTTCCTGCCTATGCTCCAGCAC
ATTTCCAAGAACAAGGACACAGGCACCTATGAGGACTTCGTGGAGGGGCTGCGGGTCTTC
GACAAGGAGGGCAATGGCACTGTCATGGGTGCTGAGCTTCGCCACGTGCTGGCCACGCTG
GGTGAGAGGCTGACAGAAGACGAAGTGGAGAGGTTGATGGCTGGGCAAGAGGACTCCAAT
GGCTGCATCAACTATGAAGCATTTGTGAAGCACATCATGTCCAGCTAA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>195</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>21931.9</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>4.75</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Myosin light chain 3
MAPKKPEPKKDDAKAAPKAAPAPAPPPEPERPKEVEFDASKIKIEFTPEQIEEFKEAFML
FDRTPKCEMKITYGQCGDVLRALGQNPTQAEVLRVLGKPRQEELNTKMMDFETFLPMLQH
ISKNKDTGTYEDFVEGLRVFDKEGNGTVMGAELRHVLATLGERLTEDEVEKLMAGQEDSN
GCINYEAFVKHIMSS</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>9651188</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P08590</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>MYL3_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AF174483</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>MYL3</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>MYL3</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:7584</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kurabayashi M, Komuro I, Tsuchimochi H, Takaku F, Yazaki Y: Molecular cloning and characterization of human atrial and ventricular myosin alkali light chain cDNA clones. J Biol Chem. 1988 Sep 25;263(27):13930-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3417683</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hoffmann E, Shi QW, Floroff M, Mickle DA, Wu TW, Olley PM, Jackowski G: Molecular cloning and complete nucleotide sequence of a human ventricular myosin light chain 1. Nucleic Acids Res. 1988 Mar 25;16(5):2353.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3357795</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Fodor WL, Darras B, Seharaseyon J, Falkenthal S, Francke U, Vanin EF: Human ventricular/slow twitch myosin alkali light chain gene characterization, sequence, and chromosomal location. J Biol Chem. 1989 Feb 5;264(4):2143-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2789520</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ota T, Suzuki Y, Nishikawa T, Otsuki T, Sugiyama T, Irie R, Wakamatsu A, Hayashi K, Sato H, Nagai K, Kimura K, Makita H, Sekine M, Obayashi M, Nishi T, Shibahara T, Tanaka T, Ishii S, Yamamoto J, Saito K, Kawai Y, Isono Y, Nakamura Y, Nagahari K, Murakami K, Yasuda T, Iwayanagi T, Wagatsuma M, Shiratori A, Sudo H, Hosoiri T, Kaku Y, Kodaira H, Kondo H, Sugawara M, Takahashi M, Kanda K, Yokoi T, Furuya T, Kikkawa E, Omura Y, Abe K, Kamihara K, Katsuta N, Sato K, Tanikawa M, Yamazaki M, Ninomiya K, Ishibashi T, Yamashita H, Murakawa K, Fujimori K, Tanai H, Kimata M, Watanabe M, Hiraoka S, Chiba Y, Ishida S, Ono Y, Takiguchi S, Watanabe S, Yosida M, Hotuta T, Kusano J, Kanehori K, Takahashi-Fujii A, Hara H, Tanase TO, Nomura Y, Togiya S, Komai F, Hara R, Takeuchi K, Arita M, Imose N, Musashino K, Yuuki H, Oshima A, Sasaki N, Aotsuka S, Yoshikawa Y, Matsunawa H, Ichihara T, Shiohata N, Sano S, Moriya S, Momiyama H, Satoh N, Takami S, Terashima Y, Suzuki O, Nakagawa S, Senoh A, Mizoguchi H, Goto Y, Shimizu F, Wakebe H, Hishigaki H, Watanabe T, Sugiyama A, Takemoto M, Kawakami B, Yamazaki M, Watanabe K, Kumagai A, Itakura S, Fukuzumi Y, Fujimori Y, Komiyama M, Tashiro H, Tanigami A, Fujiwara T, Ono T, Yamada K, Fujii Y, Ozaki K, Hirao M, Ohmori Y, Kawabata A, Hikiji T, Kobatake N, Inagaki H, Ikema Y, Okamoto S, Okitani R, Kawakami T, Noguchi S, Itoh T, Shigeta K, Senba T, Matsumura K, Nakajima Y, Mizuno T, Morinaga M, Sasaki M, Togashi T, Oyama M, Hata H, Watanabe M, Komatsu T, Mizushima-Sugano J, Satoh T, Shirai Y, Takahashi Y, Nakagawa K, Okumura K, Nagase T, Nomura N, Kikuchi H, Masuho Y, Yamashita R, Nakai K, Yada T, Nakamura Y, Ohara O, Isogai T, Sugano S: Complete sequencing and characterization of 21,243 full-length human cDNAs. Nat Genet. 2004 Jan;36(1):40-5. Epub 2003 Dec 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14702039</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kovalyov LI, Shishkin SS, Efimochkin AS, Kovalyova MA, Ershova ES, Egorov TA, Musalyamov AK: The major protein expression profile and two-dimensional protein database of human heart. Electrophoresis. 1995 Jul;16(7):1160-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7498159</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Henry GD, Trayer IP, Brewer S, Levine BA: The widespread distribution of alpha-N-trimethylalanine as the N-terminal amino acid of light chains from vertebrate striated muscle myosins. Eur J Biochem. 1985 Apr 1;148(1):75-82.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3979397</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Poetter K, Jiang H, Hassanzadeh S, Master SR, Chang A, Dalakas MC, Rayment I, Sellers JR, Fananapazir L, Epstein ND: Mutations in either the essential or regulatory light chains of myosin are associated with a rare myopathy in human heart and skeletal muscle. Nat Genet. 1996 May;13(1):63-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8673105</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Olson TM, Karst ML, Whitby FG, Driscoll DJ: Myosin light chain mutation causes autosomal recessive cardiomyopathy with mid-cavitary hypertrophy and restrictive physiology. Circulation. 2002 May 21;105(20):2337-40.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12021217</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Richard P, Charron P, Carrier L, Ledeuil C, Cheav T, Pichereau C, Benaiche A, Isnard R, Dubourg O, Burban M, Gueffet JP, Millaire A, Desnos M, Schwartz K, Hainque B, Komajda M: Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy: distribution of disease genes, spectrum of mutations, and implications for a molecular diagnosis strategy. Circulation. 2003 May 6;107(17):2227-32. Epub 2003 Apr 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12707239</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
