<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 18:58:09 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 18:58:09 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP01625</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>6948</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Beta-globin</synonym>
    <synonym>Hemoglobin beta chain</synonym>
    <synonym>LVV-hemorphin-7</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>HBB</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in iron ion binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>LVV-hemorphin-7 potentiates the activity of bradykinin, causing a decrease in blood pressure</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB03178</accession>
      <name>Heme</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB03378</accession>
      <name>Nitric oxide</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01377</accession>
      <name>Oxygen</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>heme binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>oxygen binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>cation binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>metal ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>transition metal ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>iron ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>establishment of localization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>gas transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>oxygen transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>macromolecular complex</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>protein complex</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>hemoglobin complex</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>11p15.5</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;444 bp
ATGGTGCATCTGACTCCTGAGGAGAAGTCTGCCGTTACTGCCCTGTGGGGCAAGGTGAAC
GTGGATGAAGTTGGTGGTGAGGCCCTGGGCAGGCTGCTGGTGGTCTACCCTTGGACCCAG
AGGTTCTTTGAGTCCTTTGGGGATCTGTCCACTCCTGATGCTGTTATGGGCAACCCTAAG
GTGAAGGCTCATGGCAAGAAAGTGCTCGGTGCCTTTAGTGATGGCCTGGCTCACCTGGAC
AACCTCAAGGGCACCTTTGCCACACTGAGTGAGCTGCACTGTGACAAGCTGCACGTGGAT
CCTGAGAACTTCAGGCTCCTGGGCAACGTGCTGGTCTGTGTGCTGGCCCATCACTTTGGC
AAAGAATTCACCCCACCAGTGCAGGCTGCCTATCAGAAAGTGGTGGCTGGTGTGGCTAAT
GCCCTGGCCCACAAGTATCACTAA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>147</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>15998.3</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>7.32</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Globin</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00042</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Hemoglobin subunit beta
MVHLTPEEKSAVTALWGKVNVDEVGGEALGRLLVVYPWTQRFFESFGDLSTPDAVMGNPK
VKAHGKKVLGAFSDGLAHLDNLKGTFATLSELHCDKLHVDPENFRLLGNVLVCVLAHHFG
KEFTPPVQAAYQKVVAGVANALAHKYH</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>2253432</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P68871</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>HBB_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1DXT</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AF007546</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>HBB</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>HBB</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:4827</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Marotta CA, Forget BG, Cohen-Solal M, Weissman SM: Nucleotide sequence analysis of coding and noncoding regions of human beta-globin mRNA. Prog Nucleic Acid Res Mol Biol. 1976;19:165-75.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1019344</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Lawn RM, Efstratiadis A, O'Connell C, Maniatis T: The nucleotide sequence of the human beta-globin gene.  Cell. 1980 Oct;21(3):647-51.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6254664</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wood ET, Stover DA, Slatkin M, Nachman MW, Hammer MF: The beta -globin recombinational hotspot reduces the effects of strong selection around HbC, a recently arisen mutation providing resistance to malaria. Am J Hum Genet. 2005 Oct;77(4):637-42. Epub 2005 Aug 29.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16175509</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ota T, Suzuki Y, Nishikawa T, Otsuki T, Sugiyama T, Irie R, Wakamatsu A, Hayashi K, Sato H, Nagai K, Kimura K, Makita H, Sekine M, Obayashi M, Nishi T, Shibahara T, Tanaka T, Ishii S, Yamamoto J, Saito K, Kawai Y, Isono Y, Nakamura Y, Nagahari K, Murakami K, Yasuda T, Iwayanagi T, Wagatsuma M, Shiratori A, Sudo H, Hosoiri T, Kaku Y, Kodaira H, Kondo H, Sugawara M, Takahashi M, Kanda K, Yokoi T, Furuya T, Kikkawa E, Omura Y, Abe K, Kamihara K, Katsuta N, Sato K, Tanikawa M, Yamazaki M, Ninomiya K, Ishibashi T, Yamashita H, Murakawa K, Fujimori K, Tanai H, Kimata M, Watanabe M, Hiraoka S, Chiba Y, Ishida S, Ono Y, Takiguchi S, Watanabe S, Yosida M, Hotuta T, Kusano J, Kanehori K, Takahashi-Fujii A, Hara H, Tanase TO, Nomura Y, Togiya S, Komai F, Hara R, Takeuchi K, Arita M, Imose N, Musashino K, Yuuki H, Oshima A, Sasaki N, Aotsuka S, Yoshikawa Y, Matsunawa H, Ichihara T, Shiohata N, Sano S, Moriya S, Momiyama H, Satoh N, Takami S, Terashima Y, Suzuki O, Nakagawa S, Senoh A, Mizoguchi H, Goto Y, Shimizu F, Wakebe H, Hishigaki H, Watanabe T, Sugiyama A, Takemoto M, Kawakami B, Yamazaki M, Watanabe K, Kumagai A, Itakura S, Fukuzumi Y, Fujimori Y, Komiyama M, Tashiro H, Tanigami A, Fujiwara T, Ono T, Yamada K, Fujii Y, Ozaki K, Hirao M, Ohmori Y, Kawabata A, Hikiji T, Kobatake N, Inagaki H, Ikema Y, Okamoto S, Okitani R, Kawakami T, Noguchi S, Itoh T, Shigeta K, Senba T, Matsumura K, Nakajima Y, Mizuno T, Morinaga M, Sasaki M, Togashi T, Oyama M, Hata H, Watanabe M, Komatsu T, Mizushima-Sugano J, Satoh T, Shirai Y, Takahashi Y, Nakagawa K, Okumura K, Nagase T, Nomura N, Kikuchi H, Masuho Y, Yamashita R, Nakai K, Yada T, Nakamura Y, Ohara O, Isogai T, Sugano S: Complete sequencing and characterization of 21,243 full-length human cDNAs. Nat Genet. 2004 Jan;36(1):40-5. Epub 2003 Dec 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14702039</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>BRAUNITZER G, GEHRING-MUELLER R, HILSCHMANN N, HILSE K, HOBOM G, RUDLOFF V, WITTMANN-LIEBOLD B: [The structure of normal adult human hemoglobins.]  Hoppe Seylers Z Physiol Chem. 1961 Sep 20;325:283-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>13872627</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Glamsta EL, Meyerson B, Silberring J, Terenius L, Nyberg F: Isolation of a hemoglobin-derived opioid peptide from cerebrospinal fluid of patients with cerebrovascular bleedings. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1992 Apr 30;184(2):1060-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1575724</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Suzuki H, Wada C, Kamata K, Takahashi E, Sato N, Kunitomo T: Globin chain synthesis in hemolytic anemia reticulocytes. A case of hemoglobin Burke. Biochem Mol Biol Int. 1993 Jul;30(3):425-31.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8401300</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Lang KM, Spritz RA: Cloning specific complete polyadenylylated 3'-terminal cDNA segments.  Gene. 1985;33(2):191-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2581851</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Arnone A: X-ray diffraction study of binding of 2,3-diphosphoglycerate to human deoxyhaemoglobin. Nature. 1972 May 19;237(5351):146-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>4555506</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shamsuddin M, Mason RG, Ritchey JM, Honig GR, Klotz IM: Sites of acetylation of sickle cell hemoglobin by aspirin.  Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1974 Dec;71(12):4693-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>4531009</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bunn HF, Gabbay KH, Gallop PM: The glycosylation of hemoglobin: relevance to diabetes mellitus.  Science. 1978 Apr 7;200(4337):21-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>635569</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shapiro R, McManus MJ, Zalut C, Bunn HF: Sites of nonenzymatic glycosylation of human hemoglobin A.  J Biol Chem. 1980 Apr 10;255(7):3120-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7358733</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Yoshioka N, Atassi MZ: Haemoglobin binding with haptoglobin. Localization of the haptoglobin-binding sites on the beta-chain of human haemoglobin by synthetic overlapping peptides encompassing the entire chain. Biochem J. 1986 Mar 1;234(2):453-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3718478</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Brennan SO, Shaw J, Allen J, George PM: Beta 141 Leu is not deleted in the unstable haemoglobin Atlanta-Coventry but is replaced by a novel amino acid of mass 129 daltons. Br J Haematol. 1992 May;81(1):99-103.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1520632</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Jia L, Bonaventura C, Bonaventura J, Stamler JS: S-nitrosohaemoglobin: a dynamic activity of blood involved in vascular control. Nature. 1996 Mar 21;380(6571):221-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8637569</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Chan NL, Rogers PH, Arnone A: Crystal structure of the S-nitroso form of liganded human hemoglobin.  Biochemistry. 1998 Nov 24;37(47):16459-64.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9843411</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Durner J, Gow AJ, Stamler JS, Glazebrook J: Ancient origins of nitric oxide signaling in biological systems.  Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1999 Dec 7;96(25):14206-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10588683</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kim SC, Sprung R, Chen Y, Xu Y, Ball H, Pei J, Cheng T, Kho Y, Xiao H, Xiao L, Grishin NV, White M, Yang XJ, Zhao Y: Substrate and functional diversity of lysine acetylation revealed by a proteomics survey. Mol Cell. 2006 Aug;23(4):607-18.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16916647</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ianzer D, Konno K, Xavier CH, Stocklin R, Santos RA, de Camargo AC, Pimenta DC: Hemorphin and hemorphin-like peptides isolated from dog pancreas and sheep brain are able to potentiate bradykinin activity in vivo. Peptides. 2006 Nov;27(11):2957-66. Epub 2006 Aug 9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16904236</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rikova K, Guo A, Zeng Q, Possemato A, Yu J, Haack H, Nardone J, Lee K, Reeves C, Li Y, Hu Y, Tan Z, Stokes M, Sullivan L, Mitchell J, Wetzel R, Macneill J, Ren JM, Yuan J, Bakalarski CE, Villen J, Kornhauser JM, Smith B, Li D, Zhou X, Gygi SP, Gu TL, Polakiewicz RD, Rush J, Comb MJ: Global survey of phosphotyrosine signaling identifies oncogenic kinases in lung cancer. Cell. 2007 Dec 14;131(6):1190-203.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18083107</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Finch JT, Perutz MF, Bertles JF, Dobler J: Structure of sickled erythrocytes and of sickle-cell hemoglobin fibers.  Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1973 Mar;70(3):718-22.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>4123689</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wishner BC, Ward KB, Lattman EE, Love WE: Crystal structure of sickle-cell deoxyhemoglobin at 5 A resolution.  J Mol Biol. 1975 Oct 15;98(1):179-94.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1195378</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Fermi G: Three-dimensional fourier synthesis of human deoxyhaemoglobin at 2-5 A resolution: refinement of the atomic model. J Mol Biol. 1975 Sep 15;97(2):237-56.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1177322</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Baldwin JM: The structure of human carbonmonoxy haemoglobin at 2.7 A resolution.  J Mol Biol. 1980 Jan 15;136(2):103-28.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7373648</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Fermi G, Perutz MF, Shaanan B, Fourme R: The crystal structure of human deoxyhaemoglobin at 1.74 A resolution.  J Mol Biol. 1984 May 15;175(2):159-74.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6726807</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kavanaugh JS, Rogers PH, Case DA, Arnone A: High-resolution X-ray study of deoxyhemoglobin Rothschild 37 beta Trp----Arg: a mutation that creates an intersubunit chloride-binding site. Biochemistry. 1992 Apr 28;31(16):4111-21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1567857</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Fermi G, Perutz MF, Williamson D, Stein P, Shih DT: Structure-function relationships in the low-affinity mutant haemoglobin Aalborg (Gly74 (E18)beta----Arg). J Mol Biol. 1992 Aug 5;226(3):883-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1507231</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Richard V, Dodson GG, Mauguen Y: Human deoxyhaemoglobin-2,3-diphosphoglycerate complex low-salt structure at 2.5 A resolution. J Mol Biol. 1993 Sep 20;233(2):270-4.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8377203</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Paoli M, Liddington R, Tame J, Wilkinson A, Dodson G: Crystal structure of T state haemoglobin with oxygen bound at all four haems. J Mol Biol. 1996 Mar 8;256(4):775-92.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8642597</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kavanaugh JS, Weydert JA, Rogers PH, Arnone A: High-resolution crystal structures of human hemoglobin with mutations at tryptophan 37beta: structural basis for a high-affinity T-state,. Biochemistry. 1998 Mar 31;37(13):4358-73.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9521756</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Harrington DJ, Adachi K, Royer WE Jr: Crystal structure of deoxy-human hemoglobin beta6 Glu --&amp;gt; Trp. Implications for the structure and formation of the sickle cell fiber. J Biol Chem. 1998 Dec 4;273(49):32690-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9830011</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Dewan JC, Feeling-Taylor A, Puius YA, Patskovska L, Patskovsky Y, Nagel RL, Almo SC, Hirsch RE: Structure of mutant human carbonmonoxyhemoglobin C (betaE6K) at 2.0 A resolution. Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr. 2002 Dec;58(Pt 12):2038-42. Epub 2002       Nov 23.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12454462</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Brimhall B, Jones RT, Schneider RG, Hosty TS, Tomlin G, Atkins R: Two new hemoglobins. Hemoglobin Alabama (beta39(C5)Gln leads to Lys) and hemoglobin Montgomery (alpha 48(CD 6) Leu leads to Arg). Biochim Biophys Acta. 1975 Jan 30;379(1):28-32.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1115799</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Thillet J, Cohen-Solal M, Seligmann M, Rosa J: Functional and physicochemical studies of hemoglobin St. Louis beta 28 (B10) Leu replaced by Gln: a variant with ferric beta heme iron. J Clin Invest. 1976 Nov;58(5):1098-1106.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>186485</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Thein SL, Hesketh C, Taylor P, Temperley IJ, Hutchinson RM, Old JM, Wood WG, Clegg JB, Weatherall DJ: Molecular basis for dominantly inherited inclusion body beta-thalassemia.  Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1990 May;87(10):3924-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1971109</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Molchanova TP, Postnikov YuV, Pobedimskaya DD, Smetanina NS, Moschan AA, Kazanetz EG, Tokarev YuN, Huisman TH: Hb Alesha or alpha 2 beta (2)67(E11)Val--&amp;gt;Met: a new unstable hemoglobin variant identified through sequencing of amplified DNA. Hemoglobin. 1993 Jun;17(3):217-25.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8330974</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Adams JG 3rd, Przywara KP, Heller P, Shamsuddin M: Hemoglobin J Altgeld Gardens. A hemoglobin variant with a substitution of the proximal histidine of the beta-chain. Hemoglobin. 1978;2(5):403-15.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>721609</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Arcasoy A, Casey R, Lehmann H, Cavdar AO, Berki A: A new haemoglobin J from Turkey--Hb Ankara (beta10 (A7) Ala-Asp).  FEBS Lett. 1974 Jun 1;42(2):121-3.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>4850241</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Huisman TH, Wilson JB, Kutlar A, Yang KG, Chen SS, Webber BB, Altay C, Martinez AV: Hb J-Antakya or alpha 2 beta (2)65(E9)Lys----Met in a Turkish family and Hb complutense or alpha 2 beta (2)127(H5)Gln----Glu in a Spanish family; correction of a previously published identification. Biochim Biophys Acta. 1986 Jun 5;871(2):229-31.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3707969</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Williamson D, Wells RM, Anderson R, Matthews J: A new unstable and low oxygen affinity hemoglobin variant: Hb J-Auckland [beta 25(B7)Gly----Asp]. Hemoglobin. 1987;11(3):221-30.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3654265</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Lafferty J, Ali M, Matthew K, Eng B, Patterson M, Waye JS: Identification of a new high oxygen affinity hemoglobin variant: Hb Aurora [beta 139(H17) Asn--&amp;gt;Tyr] Hemoglobin. 1995;19(6):335-41.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8718692</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Baudin-Chich V, Wajcman H, Gombaud-Saintonge G, Arous N, Riou J, Briere J, Galacteros F: Hemoglobin Brest [beta 127 (H5)Gln----Lys] a new unstable human hemoglobin variant located at the alpha 1 beta 1 interface with specific electrophoretic behavior. Hemoglobin. 1988;12(2):179-88.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3384710</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Brennan SO, Wells RM, Smith H, Carrell RW: Hemoglobin Brisbane: beta68 Leu replaced by His. A new high oxygen affinity variant. Hemoglobin. 1981;5(4):325-35.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6166590</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Como PF, Kennett D, Wilkinson T, Kronenberg H: A new hemoglobin with high oxygen affinity--hemoglobin bunbury: alpha 2 beta 2 [94 (FG1) Asp replaced by Asn] Hemoglobin. 1983;7(5):413-21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6629823</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Garel MC, Hassan W, Coquelet MT, Goossens M, Rosa J, Arous N: Hemoglobin J Cairo: beta 65 (E9) Lys leads to Gln, A new hemoglobin variant discovered in an Egyptian family. Biochim Biophys Acta. 1976 Jan 20;420(1):97-104.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1247583</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wilkinson T, Chua CG, Carrell RW, Robin H, Exner T, Lee KM, Kronenberg H: Haemoglobin Camperdown beta104(G6) arginine leads to serine.  Biochim Biophys Acta. 1975 May 30;393(1):195-200.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1138922</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ahern E, Ahern V, Hilton T, Serjeant GR, Serjeant BE, Seakins M, Lang A, Middleton A, Lehmann H: Haemoglobin caribbean beta91 (F7) Leu replaced by Arg: a mildly haemoglobin with a low oxygen affinity. FEBS Lett. 1976 Oct 15;69(1):99-102.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>992050</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rahbar S, Asmerom Y, Blume KG: A silent hemoglobin variant detected by HPLC: hemoglobin City of Hope beta 69 (E13) Gly----Ser. Hemoglobin. 1984;8(4):333-42.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6434492</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Tamagnini GP, Ribeiro ML, Valente V, Ramachandran M, Wilson JB, Baysal E, Gu LH, Huisman TH: Hb Coimbra or alpha 2 beta (2)99(G1)Asp----Glu, a newly discovered highoxygen affinity variant. Hemoglobin. 1991;15(6):487-96.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1814856</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rodriguez Romero WE, Castillo M, Chaves MA, Saenz GF, Gu LH, Wilson JB, Baysal E, Smetanina NS, Leonova JY, Huisman TH: Hb Costa Rica or alpha 2 beta 2 77(EF1)His --&amp;gt; Arg: the first example of a somatic cell mutation in a globin gene. Hum Genet. 1996 Jun;97(6):829-33.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8641705</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Lacan P, Kister J, Francina A, Souillet G, Galacteros F, Delaunay J, Wajcman H: Hemoglobin Debrousse (beta 96[FG3]Leu--&amp;gt;Pro): a new unstable hemoglobin with twofold increased oxygen affinity. Am J Hematol. 1996 Apr;51(4):276-81.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8602627</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bardakdjian-Michau J, Fucharoen S, Delanoe-Garin J, Kister J, Lacombe C, Winichagoon P, Blouquit Y, Riou J, Wasi P, Galacteros F: Hemoglobin Dhonburi alpha 2 beta 2 126 (H4) Val----Gly: a new unstable beta variant producing a beta-thalassemia intermedia phenotype in association with beta zero-thalassemia. Am J Hematol. 1990 Oct;35(2):96-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2399911</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wajcman H, Blouquit Y, Vasseur C, Le Querrec A, Laniece M, Melevendi C, Rasore A, Galacteros F: Two new human hemoglobin variants caused by unusual mutational events: Hb Zaire contains a five residue repetition within the alpha-chain and Hb Duino has two residues substituted in the beta-chain. Hum Genet. 1992 Aug;89(6):676-80.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1511986</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Murru S, Poddie D, Sciarratta GV, Agosti S, Baffico M, Melevendi C, Pirastu M, Cao A: A novel beta-globin structural mutant, Hb Brescia (beta 114 Leu-Pro), causing a severe beta-thalassemia intermedia phenotype. Hum Mutat. 1992;1(2):124-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1301199</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>de Castro CM, Devlin B, Fleenor DE, Lee ME, Kaufman RE: A novel beta-globin mutation, beta Durham-NC [beta 114 Leu--&amp;gt;Pro], produces a dominant thalassemia-like phenotype. Blood. 1994 Feb 15;83(4):1109-16.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8111050</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kiger L, Kister J, Groff P, Kalmes G, Prome D, Galacteros F, Wajcman H: Hb J-Europa [beta 62(E6)Ala--&amp;gt;Asp]: normal oxygen binding properties in a new variant involving a residue located distal to the heme. Hemoglobin. 1996 May;20(2):135-40.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8811317</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Como PF, Hocking DR, Swinton GW, Trent RJ, Holland RA, Tibben EA, Wilkinson T, Kronenberg H: Hb Geelong [beta 139(H17)Asn----Asp]  Hemoglobin. 1991;15(1-2):85-95.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1917539</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Baklouti F, Giraud Y, Francina A, Richard G, Perier C, Geyssant A, Jaubert J, Brizard C, Delaunay J: Hemoglobin Grange-Blanche [beta 27(B9) Ala----Val], a new variant with normal expression and increased affinity for oxygen. FEBS Lett. 1987 Oct 19;223(1):59-62.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3666141</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Liu JS, Molchanova TP, Gu LH, Wilson JB, Hopmeier P, Schnedl W, Balaun E, Krejs GJ, Huisman TH: Hb Graz or alpha 2 beta 2(2)(NA2)His--&amp;gt;Leu; a new beta chain variant observed in four families from southern Austria. Hemoglobin. 1992;16(6):493-501.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1487420</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ikkala E, Koskela J, Pikkarainen P, Rahiala EL, El-Hazmi MA, Nagai K, Lang A, Lehmann H: Hb Helsinki: a variant with a high oxygen affinity and a substitution at a 2,3-DPG binding site (beta82[EF6] Lys replaced by Met). Acta Haematol. 1976;56(5):257-75.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>826083</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ohba Y, Miyaji T, Murakami M, Kadowaki S, Fujita T, Oimomi M, Hatanaka H, Ishikawa K, Baba S, Hitaka K, et al.: Hb Himeji or beta 140 (H18) Ala----Asp. A slightly unstable hemoglobin with increased beta N-terminal glycation. Hemoglobin. 1986;10(2):109-25.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3754244</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Moo-Penn WF, Johnson MH, Jue DL, Lonser R: Hb Hinsdale [beta 139 (H17)Asn----Lys]: a variant in the central cavity showing reduced affinity for oxygen and 2,3-diphosphoglycerate. Hemoglobin. 1989;13(5):455-64.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2513289</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Frischknecht H, Ventruto M, Hess D, Hunziker P, Rosatelli MC, Cao A, Breitenstein U, Fehr J, Tuchschmid P: HB Hinwil or beta 38(C4)Thr--&amp;gt;Asn: a new beta chain variant detected in a Swiss family. Hemoglobin. 1996 Feb;20(1):31-40.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8745430</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Owen MC, Ockelford PA, Wells RM: Hb Howick [beta 37(C3)Trp--&amp;gt;Gly]: a new high oxygen affinity variant of the alpha 1 beta 2 contact. Hemoglobin. 1993 Dec;17(6):513-21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8144352</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Adams JG, Steinberg MH, Boxer LA, Baehner RL, Forget BG, Tsistrakis GA: The structure of hemoglobin Indianapolis [beta112(G14) arginine]. An unstable variant detectable only by isotopic labeling. J Biol Chem. 1979 May 10;254(9):3479-82.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>429365</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Harano T, Harano K, Kushida Y, Ueda S, Yoshii A, Nishinarita M: Hb Isehara (or Hb Redondo) [beta 92 (F8) His----Asn]: an unstable variant with a proximal histidine substitution at the heme contact. Hemoglobin. 1991;15(4):279-90.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1787097</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Aksoy M, Erdem S, Efremov GD, Wilson JB, Huisman TH, Schroeder WA, Shelton JR, Shelton JB, Ulitin ON, Muftuoglu A: Hemoglobin Istanbul: substitution of glutamine for histidine in a proximal histidine (F8(92) ). J Clin Invest. 1972 Sep;51(9):2380-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>4639022</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gaudry CL Jr, Pitel PA, Jue DL, Hine TK, Johnson MH, Moo-Penn WF: Hb Jacksonville [alpha 2 beta 2(54)(D5)Val----Asp]: a new unstable variant found in a patient with hemolytic anemia. Hemoglobin. 1990;14(6):653-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2101840</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Lu YQ, Fan JL, Liu JF, Hu HL, Peng XH, Huang CH, Huang PY, Chen SS, Jai PC, Yang KG, et al.: Hemoglobin Jianghua [beta 120(GH3) LYS leads to ILE]: a new fast-moving variant found in China. Hemoglobin. 1983;7(4):321-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6618888</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Landin B: Hb Karlskoga or alpha 2 beta (2)21(B3) Asp--&amp;gt;His: a new slow-moving variant found in Sweden. Hemoglobin. 1993 Jun;17(3):201-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8330972</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Arous N, Galacteros F, Fessas P, Loukopoulos D, Blouquit Y, Komis G, Sellaye M, Boussiou M, Rosa J: Structural study of hemoglobin Knossos, beta 27 (B9) Ala leads to Ser. A new abnormal hemoglobin present as a silent beta-thalassemia. FEBS Lett. 1982 Oct 18;147(2):247-50.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7173395</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Harano T, Harano K, Kushida Y, Imai K, Nishinakamura R, Matsunaga T: Hb Kodaira [beta 146(HC3)His----Gln]: a new beta chain variant with an amino acid substitution at the C-terminus. Hemoglobin. 1992;16(1-2):85-91.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1634367</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Harano T, Harano K, Ueda S, Imai N, Kitazumi T: A new electrophoretically-silent hemoglobin variant: hemoglobin Kofu or alpha 2 beta 2 84 (EF8) Thr----Ile. Hemoglobin. 1986;10(4):417-20.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3744871</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Divoky V, Svobodova M, Indrak K, Chrobak L, Molchanova TP, Huisman TH: Hb Hradec Kralove (Hb HK) or alpha 2 beta 2 115(G17)Ala--&amp;gt;Asp, a severely unstable hemoglobin variant resulting in a dominant beta-thalassemia trait in a Czech family. Hemoglobin. 1993 Aug;17(4):319-28.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7693620</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Merault G, Keclard L, Garin J, Poyart C, Blouquit Y, Arous N, Galacteros F, Feingold J, Rosa J: Hemoglobin La Desirade alpha A2 beta 2 129 (H7) Ala----Val: a new unstable hemoglobin. Hemoglobin. 1986;10(6):593-605.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3557994</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wajcman H, Kister J, Vasseur C, Blouquit Y, Trastour JC, Cottenceau D, Galacteros F: Structure of the EF corner favors deamidation of asparaginyl residues in hemoglobin: the example of Hb La Roche-sur-Yon [beta 81 (EF5) Leu----His] Biochim Biophys Acta. 1992 Feb 14;1138(2):127-32.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1540659</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Malcorra-Azpiazu JJ, Balda-Aguirre MI, Diaz-Chico JC, Hu H, Wilson JB, Webber BB, Kutlar F, Kutlar A, Huisman TH: Hb Las Palmas or alpha 2 beta 2(49)(CD8)Ser----Phe, a mildly unstable hemoglobin variant. Hemoglobin. 1988;12(2):163-70.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3384708</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Berlin G, Wranne B, Jeppsson JO: Hb Linkoping (beta 36 Pro----Thr): a new high oxygen affinity hemoglobin variant found in two families of Finnish origin. Eur J Haematol. 1987 Nov;39(5):452-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3691763</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Marinucci M, Boissel JP, Massa A, Wajcman H, Tentori L, Labie D: Hemoglobin Maputo: a new beta-chain variant (alpha 2 beta 2 47 (CD6) Asp replaced by Tyr) in combination with hemoglobin S, identified by high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC). Hemoglobin. 1983;7(5):423-33.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6629824</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Sciarratta GV, Ivaldi G: Hb Matera [beta 55(D6)Met----Lys]: a new unstable hemoglobin variant in an Italian family. Hemoglobin. 1990;14(1):79-85.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2384314</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Nakatsuji T, Miwa S, Ohba Y, Hattori Y, Miyaji T, Miyata H, Shinohara T, Hori T, Takayama J: Hemoglobin Miyashiro (beta 23[B5] val substituting for gly) an electrophoretically silent variant discovered by the isopropanol test. Hemoglobin. 1981;5(7-8):653-66.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7338468</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ohba Y, Miyaji T, Matsuoka M, Sugiyama K, Suzuki T, Sugiura T: Hemoglobin Mizuho or beta 68 (E 12) leucine leads to proline, a new unstable variant associated with severe hemolytic anemia. Hemoglobin. 1977;1(5):467-77.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>893142</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ramachandran M, Gu LH, Wilson JB, Kitundu MN, Adekile AD, Liu JC, McKie KM, Huisman TH: A new variant, HB Muscat [alpha 2 beta (2)32(B14)Leu----Val] observed in association with HB S in an Arabian family. Hemoglobin. 1992;16(4):259-66.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1517102</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Lena-Russo D, Orsini A, Vovan L, Bardakdjian-Michau J, Lacombe C, Blouquit Y, Craescu CT, Galacteros F: Hb N-Timone [alpha 2 beta 2(8)(A5)Lys----Glu]: a new fast-moving variant with normal stability and oxygen affinity. Hemoglobin. 1989;13(7-8):743-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2634671</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ohba Y, Imanaka M, Matsuoka M, Hattori Y, Miyaji T, Funaki C, Shibata K, Shimokata H, Kuzuya F, Miwa S: A new unstable, high oxygen affinity hemoglobin: Hb Nagoya or beta 97 (FG4) His----Pro. Hemoglobin. 1985;9(1):11-24.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3838976</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Welch SG, Bateman C: Hb D-Neath or beta 121 (GH4) Glu--&amp;gt;Ala: a new member of the Hb D family.  Hemoglobin. 1993 Jun;17(3):255-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8330979</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rahbar S, Louis J, Lee T, Asmerom Y: Hemoglobin North Chicago (beta 36 [C2] proline----serine): a new high affinity hemoglobin. Hemoglobin. 1985;9(6):559-76.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3937824</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Arends T, Lehmann H, Plowman D, Stathopoulou R: Haemoglobin North Shore-Caracas beta 134 (H12) valine replaced by glutamic acid. FEBS Lett. 1977 Aug 15;80(2):261-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>891976</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Indrak K, Wiedermann BF, Batek F, Wilson JB, Webber BB, Kutlar A, Huisman TH: Hb Olomouc or alpha 2 beta 2(86)(F2)Ala----Asp, a new high oxygen affinity variant. Hemoglobin. 1987;11(2):151-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3623975</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Brennan SO, Williamson D, Whisson ME, Carrell RW: Hemoglobin Palmerston North beta 23 (B5) Val replaced by Phe. A new variant identified in a patient with polycythemia. Hemoglobin. 1982;6(6):569-75.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7161106</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Baklouti F, Giraud Y, Francina A, Richard G, Favre-Gilly J, Delaunay J: Hemoglobin Pierre-Benite [beta 90(F6)Glu----Asp], a new high affinity variant found in a French family. Hemoglobin. 1988;12(2):171-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3384709</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Moo-Penn WF, Wolff JA, Simon G, Vacek M, Jue DL, Johnson MH: Hemoglobin Presbyterian: beta108 (G10) asparagine leads to lysine, A hemoglobin variant with low oxygen affinity. FEBS Lett. 1978 Aug 1;92(1):53-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>668922</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wajcman H, Girodon E, Prome D, North ML, Plassa F, Duwig I, Kister J, Bergerat JP, Oberling F, Lampert E, et al.: Germline mosaicism for an alanine to valine substitution at residue beta 140 in hemoglobin Puttelange, a new variant with high oxygen affinity. Hum Genet. 1995 Dec;96(6):711-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8522332</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Jen PC, Chen LC, Chen PF, Wong Y, Chen LF, Guo YY, Chang FQ, Chow YC, Chiu Y: Hemoglobin Quin-Hai, beta 78 (EF2) Leu replaced by Arg, a new abnormal hemoglobin found in Guangdong, China. Hemoglobin. 1983;7(5):407-12.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6629822</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bisse E, Zorn N, Eigel A, Lizama M, Huaman-Guillen P, Marz W, Van Dorsselaer A, Wieland H: Hemoglobin Rambam (beta69[E13]Gly--&amp;gt;Asp), a pitfall in the assessment of diabetic control: characterization by electrospray mass spectrometry and HPLC. Clin Chem. 1998 Oct;44(10):2172-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9761252</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gilbert AT, Fleming PJ, Sumner DR, Hughes WG, Ip F, Kwan YL, Holland RA: Hemoglobin Randwick or beta 15 (A12)Trp----Gly: a new unstable beta-chain hemoglobin variant. Hemoglobin. 1988;12(2):149-61.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3384707</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Moo-Penn WF, Johnson MH, McGuffey JE, Jue DL, Therrell BL Jr: Hemoglobin Rio Grande [beta 8 (A5) Lys leads to Thr] a new variant found in a Mexican-American family. Hemoglobin. 1983;7(1):91-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6857757</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Adams JG 3rd, Winter WP, Tausk K, Heller P: Hemoglobin Rush (beta 101 (g3) glutamine): a new unstable hemoglobin causing mild hemolytic anemia. Blood. 1974 Feb;43(2):261-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>4129558</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ohba Y, Hasegawa Y, Amino H, Miwa S, Nakatsuji T, Hattori Y, Miyaji T: Hemoglobin saitama or beta 117 (G19) His leads to Pro, a new variant causing hemolytic disease. Hemoglobin. 1983;7(1):47-56.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6687721</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>GERALD PS, EFRON ML: Chemical studies of several varieties of Hb M.  Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1961 Nov 15;47:1758-67.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>13897827</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Moo-Penn WF, Johnson MH, McGuffey JE, Jue DL: Hemoglobin Shelby [beta 131(H9) Gln----Lys] a correction to the structure of hemoglobin Deaconess and hemoglobin Leslie. Hemoglobin. 1984;8(6):583-93.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6526653</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ricco G, Pich PG, Mazza U, Rossi G, Ajmar F, Arese P, Gallo E: Hb J Sicilia: beta 65 (E9) Lys-Asn, a beta homologue of Hb Zambia.  FEBS Lett. 1974 Feb 15;39(2):200-4.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>4852224</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Como PF, Wylie BR, Trent RJ, Bruce D, Volpato F, Wilkinson T, Kronenberg H, Holland RA, Tibben EA: A new unstable and low oxygen affinity hemoglobin variant: Hb Stanmore [beta 111(G13)Val----Ala] Hemoglobin. 1991;15(1-2):53-65.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1917537</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Arous N, Braconnier F, Thillet J, Blouquit Y, Galacteros F, Chevrier M, Bordahandy C, Rosa J: Hemoglobin Saint Mande beta 102 (G4) asn replaced by tyr: a new low oxygen affinity variant. FEBS Lett. 1981 Apr 6;126(1):114-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7238856</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gilbert AT, Fleming PJ, Sumner DR, Hughes WG, Holland RA, Tibben EA: Hemoglobin Windsor or beta 11 (A8)Val----Asp: a new unstable beta-chain hemoglobin variant producing a hemolytic anemia. Hemoglobin. 1989;13(5):437-53.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2599880</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Harano T, Harano K, Kushida Y, Ueda S: A new abnormal variant, Hb Yahata or beta 112(G14)Cys----Tyr, found in a Japanese: structural confirmation by DNA sequencing of the beta-globin gene. Hemoglobin. 1991;15(1-2):109-13.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1917530</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Nakatsuji T, Miwa S, Ohba Y, Hattori Y, Miyaji T, Hino S, Matsumoto N: A new unstable hemoglobin, Hb Yokohama beta 31 (B13)Leu substituting for Pro, causing hemolytic anemia. Hemoglobin. 1981;5(7-8):667-78.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7338469</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rahbar S, Feagler RJ, Beutler E: Hemoglobin Hammersmith (beta 42 (CD1) Phe replaced by Ser) associated with severe hemolytic anemia. Hemoglobin. 1981;5(1):97-105.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6259091</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Blouquit Y, Bardakdjian J, Lena-Russo D, Arous N, Perrimond H, Orsini A, Rosa J, Galacteros F: Hb Bruxelles: alpha 2A beta (2)41 or 42(C7 or CD1)Phe deleted.  Hemoglobin. 1989;13(5):465-74.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2599881</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Plaseska D, Wilson JB, Gu LH, Kutlar F, Huisman TH, Zeng YT, Shen M: Hb Zengcheng or alpha 2 beta(2)114(G16)Leu----Met.  Hemoglobin. 1990;14(5):555-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2079435</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Fay KC, Brennan SO, Costello JM, Potter HC, Williamson DA, Trent RJ, Ockelford PA, Boswell DR: Haemoglobin Manukau beta 67[E11] Val--&amp;gt;Gly: transfusion-dependent haemolytic anaemia ameliorated by coexisting alpha thalassaemia. Br J Haematol. 1993 Oct;85(2):352-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8280608</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rees DC, Rochette J, Schofield C, Green B, Morris M, Parker NE, Sasaki H, Tanaka A, Ohba Y, Clegg JB: A novel silent posttranslational mechanism converts methionine to aspartate in hemoglobin Bristol (beta 67[E11] Val-Met-&amp;gt;Asp). Blood. 1996 Jul 1;88(1):341-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8704193</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Deutsch S, Darbellay R, Offord R, Frutiger A, Kister J, Wajcman H, Beris P: Hb Iraq-Halabja beta10 (A7) Ala--&amp;gt;Val (GCC--&amp;gt;GTC): a new beta-chain silent variant in a family with multiple Hb disorders. Am J Hematol. 1999 Jul;61(3):187-93.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10398311</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Carbone V, Salzano AM, Pagano L, Buffardi S, De Rosa C, Pucci P: Identification of Hb Villejuif [beta123(H1)Thr--&amp;gt;Ile] in Southern Italy.  Hemoglobin. 2001 Feb;25(1):67-78.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11300351</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>North ML, Duwig I, Riou J, Prome D, Yapo AP, Kister J, Bardakdjian-Michau J, Cazenave JP, Wajcman H: Hb Tsukumi [beta117(G19)His--&amp;gt;Tyr] found in a Moroccan woman.  Hemoglobin. 2001 Feb;25(1):107-10.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11300344</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Brennan SO, Potter HC, Kubala LM, Carnoutsos SA, Ferguson MM: Hb Canterbury [beta112(G14)Cys--&amp;gt;Phe]: a new, mildly unstable variant.  Hemoglobin. 2002 Feb;26(1):67-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11939514</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Sawangareetrakul P, Svasti S, Yodsowon B, Winichagoon P, Srisomsap C, Svasti J, Fucharoen S: Double heterozygosity for Hb Pyrgos [beta83(EF7)Gly--&amp;gt;Asp] and Hb E [beta26(B8)Glu--&amp;gt;Lys] found in association with alpha-thalassemia. Hemoglobin. 2002 May;26(2):191-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12144064</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Villegas A, Ropero P, Nogales A, Gonzalez FA, Mateo M, Mazo E, Rodrigo E, Arias M: Hb Santander [beta34(B16)Val --&amp;gt; Asp (GTC --&amp;gt; GAC)]: a new unstable variant found as a de novo mutation in a Spanish patient. Hemoglobin. 2003 Feb;27(1):31-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12603091</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wajcman H, Bardakdjian-Michau J, Riou J, Prehu C, Kister J, Baudin-Creuza V, Prome D, Richelme-David S, Harousseau JL, Galacteros F: Two new hemoglobin variants with increased oxygen affinity: Hb Nantes [beta34(B16)Val--&amp;gt;Leu] and Hb Vexin [beta116(G18)His--&amp;gt;Leu]. Hemoglobin. 2003 Aug;27(3):191-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12908805</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Flatz G, Sanguansermsri T, Sengchanh S, Horst D, Horst J: The 'hot-spot' of Hb E [beta26(B8)Glu--&amp;gt;Lys] in Southeast Asia: beta-globin anomalies in the Lao Theung population of southern Laos. Hemoglobin. 2004 Aug;28(3):197-204.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15481886</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
