<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:11:17 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:11:17 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP08483</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>14195</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Ran-binding protein MOG1</synonym>
    <synonym>RanGNRF</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>RANGRF</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in guanyl-nucleotide exchange factor activity</general_function>
  <specific_function>May regulate the intracellular trafficking of RAN. In cardiac cells seems to regulate the cell surface localization of SCN5A</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01273</accession>
      <name>Guanosine triphosphate</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Nucleus</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasm</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>17p13.1</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;561 bp
ATGGAGCCCACGAGAGACTGCCCGCTGTTCGGGGGCGCCTTTTCCGCCATCCTCCCCATG
GGGGCCATTGACGTAAGCGACCTCCGACCGGTCCCGGACAATCAAGAAGTTTTCTGCCAT
CCCGTGACGGACCAGAGCCTGATAGTGGAACTTCTCGAGCTGCAGGCCCACGTACGGGGC
GAAGCGGCTGCGCGGTACCACTTTGAGGATGTTGGTGGCGTGCAGGGGGCTAGGGCTGTC
CATGTGGAGTCTGTTCAGCCTCTCAGTTTGGAGAACCTGGCCCTGAGGGGCCGCTGTCAA
GAAGCCTGGGTCCTCTCTGGCAAGCAGCAGATAGCTAAGGAAAACCAGCAGGTAGCAAAG
GACGTGACACTTCATCAGGCCTTGCTGAGGCTGCCCCAGTACCAGACTGATCTCTTGCTT
ACCTTCAATCAGCCCCCCCCTGACAACAGGTCATCTCTTGGCCCCGAAAATCTGTCACCT
GCACCCTGGAGCCTGGGTGACTTTGAACAGCTGGTGACCAGTCTGACCCTTCACGATCCT
AACATCTTTGGTCCCCAGTAA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>186</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>20447.9</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>4.57</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Mog1</name>
        <pfam_id>PF04603</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Ran guanine nucleotide release factor
MEPTRDCPLFGGAFSAILPMGAIDVSDLRPVPDNQEVFCHPVTDQSLIVELLELQAHVRG
EAAARYHFEDVGGVQGARAVHVESVQPLSLENLALRGRCQEAWVLSGKQQIAKENQQVAK
DVTLHQALLRLPQYQTDLLLTFNQPPPDNRSSLGPENLSPAPWSLGDFEQLVTSLTLHDP
NIFGPQ</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>41462397</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>Q9HD47</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>MOG1_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>NM_016492.4</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>RANGRF</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>RANGRF</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:17679</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Marfatia KA, Harreman MT, Fanara P, Vertino PM, Corbett AH: Identification and characterization of the human MOG1 gene.  Gene. 2001 Mar 21;266(1-2):45-56.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11290418</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Zhang QH, Ye M, Wu XY, Ren SX, Zhao M, Zhao CJ, Fu G, Shen Y, Fan HY, Lu G, Zhong M, Xu XR, Han ZG, Zhang JW, Tao J, Huang QH, Zhou J, Hu GX, Gu J, Chen SJ, Chen Z: Cloning and functional analysis of cDNAs with open reading frames for 300 previously undefined genes expressed in CD34+ hematopoietic stem/progenitor cells. Genome Res. 2000 Oct;10(10):1546-60.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11042152</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ota T, Suzuki Y, Nishikawa T, Otsuki T, Sugiyama T, Irie R, Wakamatsu A, Hayashi K, Sato H, Nagai K, Kimura K, Makita H, Sekine M, Obayashi M, Nishi T, Shibahara T, Tanaka T, Ishii S, Yamamoto J, Saito K, Kawai Y, Isono Y, Nakamura Y, Nagahari K, Murakami K, Yasuda T, Iwayanagi T, Wagatsuma M, Shiratori A, Sudo H, Hosoiri T, Kaku Y, Kodaira H, Kondo H, Sugawara M, Takahashi M, Kanda K, Yokoi T, Furuya T, Kikkawa E, Omura Y, Abe K, Kamihara K, Katsuta N, Sato K, Tanikawa M, Yamazaki M, Ninomiya K, Ishibashi T, Yamashita H, Murakawa K, Fujimori K, Tanai H, Kimata M, Watanabe M, Hiraoka S, Chiba Y, Ishida S, Ono Y, Takiguchi S, Watanabe S, Yosida M, Hotuta T, Kusano J, Kanehori K, Takahashi-Fujii A, Hara H, Tanase TO, Nomura Y, Togiya S, Komai F, Hara R, Takeuchi K, Arita M, Imose N, Musashino K, Yuuki H, Oshima A, Sasaki N, Aotsuka S, Yoshikawa Y, Matsunawa H, Ichihara T, Shiohata N, Sano S, Moriya S, Momiyama H, Satoh N, Takami S, Terashima Y, Suzuki O, Nakagawa S, Senoh A, Mizoguchi H, Goto Y, Shimizu F, Wakebe H, Hishigaki H, Watanabe T, Sugiyama A, Takemoto M, Kawakami B, Yamazaki M, Watanabe K, Kumagai A, Itakura S, Fukuzumi Y, Fujimori Y, Komiyama M, Tashiro H, Tanigami A, Fujiwara T, Ono T, Yamada K, Fujii Y, Ozaki K, Hirao M, Ohmori Y, Kawabata A, Hikiji T, Kobatake N, Inagaki H, Ikema Y, Okamoto S, Okitani R, Kawakami T, Noguchi S, Itoh T, Shigeta K, Senba T, Matsumura K, Nakajima Y, Mizuno T, Morinaga M, Sasaki M, Togashi T, Oyama M, Hata H, Watanabe M, Komatsu T, Mizushima-Sugano J, Satoh T, Shirai Y, Takahashi Y, Nakagawa K, Okumura K, Nagase T, Nomura N, Kikuchi H, Masuho Y, Yamashita R, Nakai K, Yada T, Nakamura Y, Ohara O, Isogai T, Sugano S: Complete sequencing and characterization of 21,243 full-length human cDNAs. Nat Genet. 2004 Jan;36(1):40-5. Epub 2003 Dec 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14702039</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bechtel S, Rosenfelder H, Duda A, Schmidt CP, Ernst U, Wellenreuther R, Mehrle A, Schuster C, Bahr A, Blocker H, Heubner D, Hoerlein A, Michel G, Wedler H, Kohrer K, Ottenwalder B, Poustka A, Wiemann S, Schupp I: The full-ORF clone resource of the German cDNA Consortium.  BMC Genomics. 2007 Oct 31;8:399.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17974005</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wu L, Yong SL, Fan C, Ni Y, Yoo S, Zhang T, Zhang X, Obejero-Paz CA, Rho HJ, Ke T, Szafranski P, Jones SW, Chen Q, Wang QK: Identification of a new co-factor, MOG1, required for the full function of cardiac sodium channel Nav 1.5. J Biol Chem. 2008 Mar 14;283(11):6968-78. Epub 2008 Jan 9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18184654</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
