<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 19:03:22 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 19:03:22 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP02186</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>7671</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Casoxin-D</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>CSN1S1</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in transporter activity</general_function>
  <specific_function>Casoxin D acts as opioid antagonist and has vasorelaxing activity mediated by bradykinin B1 receptors</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>transporter activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>establishment of localization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>extracellular region</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Secreted</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:4</chromosome_location>
    <locus>4q21.1</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;558 bp
ATGAGGCTTCTCATTCTCACCTGTCTTGTGGCTGTTGCTCTTGCCAGGCCTAAACTTCCT
CTTAGATACCCAGAACGCCTTCAGAATCCATCAGAGAGCAGTGAGCCTATACCATTAGAA
TCAAGAGAGGAATACATGAATGGTATGAACAGGCAGAGAAACATTCTGAGAGAAAAACAG
ACTGATGAAATCAAGGATACTAGGAATGAGTCTACTCAGAACTGTGTTGTGGCAGAGCCT
GAGAAGATGGAATCCAGCATCAGTTCATCGAGTGAGGAAATGTCTCTCAGTAAGTGTGCG
GAACAGTTTTGTAGACTGAACGAATACAACCAACTTCAGCTGCAAGCTGCCCATGCCCAG
GAGCAAATTCGCAGAATGAATGAAAACAGCCATGTCCAAGTGCCTTTCCAGCAGCTCAAC
CAACTTGCTGCCTACCCCTATGCTGTTTGGTACTATCCACAAATCATGCAGTATGTTCCT
TTCCCACCGTTTTCCGACATCTCCAATCCCACTGCTCATGAAAATTATGAAAAAAATAAC
GTCATGCTACAGTGGTGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>185</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>21671.3</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>5.08</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>1-15</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Alpha-S1-casein
MRLLILTCLVAVALARPKLPLRYPERLQNPSESSEPIPLESREEYMNGMNRQRNILREKQ
TDEIKDTRNESTQNCVVAEPEKMESSISSSSEEMSLSKCAEQFCRLNEYNQLQLQAAHAQ
EQIRRMNENSHVQVPFQQLNQLAAYPYAVWYYPQIMQYVPFPPFSDISNPTAHENYEKNN
VMLQW</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>854086</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P47710</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>CASA1_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>X78416</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>CSN1S1</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>CSN1S1</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:2445</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Johnsen LB, Rasmussen LK, Petersen TE, Berglund L: Characterization of three types of human alpha s1-casein mRNA transcripts.  Biochem J. 1995 Jul 1;309 ( Pt 1):237-42.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7619062</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Cavaletto M, Cantisani A, Giuffrida G, Napolitano L, Conti A: Human alpha S1-casein like protein: purification and N-terminal sequence determination. Biol Chem Hoppe Seyler. 1994 Feb;375(2):149-51.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8192860</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rasmussen LK, Due HA, Petersen TE: Human alpha s1-casein: purification and characterization.  Comp Biochem Physiol B Biochem Mol Biol. 1995 May;111(1):75-81.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7749638</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kjeldsen F, Savitski MM, Nielsen ML, Shi L, Zubarev RA: On studying protein phosphorylation patterns using bottom-up LC-MS/MS: the case of human alpha-casein. Analyst. 2007 Aug;132(8):768-76. Epub 2007 Jun 13.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17646876</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Poth AG, Deeth HC, Alewood PF, Holland JW: Analysis of the human casein phosphoproteome by 2-D electrophoresis and MALDI-TOF/TOF MS reveals new phosphoforms. J Proteome Res. 2008 Nov;7(11):5017-27. Epub 2008 Oct 11.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18847231</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Sorensen ES, Moller L, Vinther M, Petersen TE, Rasmussen LK: The phosphorylation pattern of human alphas1-casein is markedly different from the ruminant species. Eur J Biochem. 2003 Sep;270(17):3651-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12919330</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Fujiwara Y, Miwa M, Nogami M, Okumura K, Nobori T, Suzuki T, Ueda M: Genomic organization and chromosomal localization of the human casein gene family. Hum Genet. 1997 Mar;99(3):368-73.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9050925</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
