<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:38:38 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:38:38 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP10842</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>17132</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>MinK-related peptide 1</synonym>
    <synonym>Minimum potassium ion channel-related peptide 1</synonym>
    <synonym>Potassium channel subunit beta MiRP1</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>KCNE2</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in voltage-gated potassium channel activity</general_function>
  <specific_function>Ancillary protein that assembles as a beta subunit with a voltage-gated potassium channel complex of pore-forming alpha subunits. Modulates the gating kinetics and enhances stability of the channel complex. Associated with KCNH2/HERG is proposed to form the rapidly activating component of the delayed rectifying potassium current in heart (IKr). May associate with KCNQ2 and/or KCNQ3 and modulate the native M-type current. May associate with KCNQ1/KVLTQ1 and elicit a voltage-independent current. May associate with HCN1 and HCN2 and increase potassium current</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00586</accession>
      <name>Potassium</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>transporter activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>transmembrane transporter activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>substrate-specific transmembrane transporter activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ion transmembrane transporter activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ion channel activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>cation channel activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>potassium channel activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>voltage-gated potassium channel activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>cation transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>monovalent inorganic cation transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>potassium ion transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>establishment of localization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>ion transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>cell part</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>membrane</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Membrane</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Single-pass type I membrane protein</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:2</chromosome_location>
    <locus>21q22.12</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;372 bp
ATGTCTACTTTATCCAATTTCACACAGACGCTGGAAGACGTCTTCCGAAGGATTTTTATT
ACTTATATGGACAATTGGCGCCAGAACACAACAGCTGAGCAAGAGGCCCTCCAAGCCAAA
GTTGATGCTGAGAACTTCTACTATGTCATCCTGTACCTCATGGTGATGATTGGAATGTTC
TCTTTCATCATCGTGGCCATCCTGGTGAGCACTGTGAAATCCAAGAGACGGGAACACTCC
AATGACCCCTACCACCAGTACATTGTAGAGGACTGGCAGGAAAAGTACAAGAGCCAAATC
TTGAATCTAGAAGAATCGAAGGCCACCATCCATGAGAACATTGGTGCGGCTGGGTTCAAA
ATGTCCCCCTGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>123</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>14471.4</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>5.65</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>ISK_Channel</name>
        <pfam_id>PF02060</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>49-69</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Potassium voltage-gated channel subfamily E member 2
MSTLSNFTQTLEDVFRRIFITYMDNWRQNTTAEQEALQAKVDAENFYYVILYLMVMIGMF
SFIIVAILVSTVKSKRREHSNDPYHQYIVEDWQEKYKSQILNLEESKATIHENIGAAGFK
MSP</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>4704423</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>Q9Y6J6</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>KCNE2_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AF071002</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>KCNE2</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>KCNE2</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:6242</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Abbott GW, Sesti F, Splawski I, Buck ME, Lehmann MH, Timothy KW, Keating MT, Goldstein SA: MiRP1 forms IKr potassium channels with HERG and is associated with cardiac arrhythmia. Cell. 1999 Apr 16;97(2):175-87.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10219239</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Tinel N, Diochot S, Lauritzen I, Barhanin J, Lazdunski M, Borsotto M: M-type KCNQ2-KCNQ3 potassium channels are modulated by the KCNE2 subunit.  FEBS Lett. 2000 Sep 1;480(2-3):137-41.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11034315</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Tinel N, Diochot S, Borsotto M, Lazdunski M, Barhanin J: KCNE2 confers background current characteristics to the cardiac KCNQ1 potassium channel. EMBO J. 2000 Dec 1;19(23):6326-30.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11101505</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Abbott GW, Goldstein SA: Disease-associated mutations in KCNE potassium channel subunits (MiRPs) reveal promiscuous disruption of multiple currents and conservation of mechanism. FASEB J. 2002 Mar;16(3):390-400.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11874988</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Oppermann FS, Gnad F, Olsen JV, Hornberger R, Greff Z, Keri G, Mann M, Daub H: Large-scale proteomics analysis of the human kinome.  Mol Cell Proteomics. 2009 Jul;8(7):1751-64. Epub 2009 Apr 15.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19369195</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Isbrandt D, Friederich P, Solth A, Haverkamp W, Ebneth A, Borggrefe M, Funke H, Sauter K, Breithardt G, Pongs O, Schulze-Bahr E: Identification and functional characterization of a novel KCNE2 (MiRP1) mutation that alters HERG channel kinetics. J Mol Med. 2002 Aug;80(8):524-32. Epub 2002 Jun 28.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12185453</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Yang Y, Xia M, Jin Q, Bendahhou S, Shi J, Chen Y, Liang B, Lin J, Liu Y, Liu B, Zhou Q, Zhang D, Wang R, Ma N, Su X, Niu K, Pei Y, Xu W, Chen Z, Wan H, Cui J, Barhanin J, Chen Y: Identification of a KCNE2 gain-of-function mutation in patients with familial atrial fibrillation. Am J Hum Genet. 2004 Nov;75(5):899-905. Epub 2004 Sep 13.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15368194</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Millat G, Chevalier P, Restier-Miron L, Da Costa A, Bouvagnet P, Kugener B, Fayol L, Gonzalez Armengod C, Oddou B, Chanavat V, Froidefond E, Perraudin R, Rousson R, Rodriguez-Lafrasse C: Spectrum of pathogenic mutations and associated polymorphisms in a cohort of 44 unrelated patients with long QT syndrome. Clin Genet. 2006 Sep;70(3):214-27.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16922724</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
