<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:05:44 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:05:44 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP08050</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13761</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Fortilin</synonym>
    <synonym>HRF</synonym>
    <synonym>Histamine-releasing factor</synonym>
    <synonym>TCTP</synonym>
    <synonym>p23</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>TPT1</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in calcium ion binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Involved in calcium binding and microtubule stabilization</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasm</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>13q14</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;519 bp
ATGATTATCTACCGGGACCTCATCAGCCACGATGAGATGTTCTCCGACATCTACAAGATC
CGGGAGATCGCGGACGGGTTGTGCCTGGAGGTGGAGGGGAAGATGGTCAGTAGGACAGAA
GGTAACATTGATGACTCGCTCATTGGTGGAAATGCCTCCGCTGAAGGCCCCGAGGGCGAA
GGTACCGAAAGCACAGTAATCACTGGTGTCGATATTGTCATGAACCATCACCTGCAGGAA
ACAAGTTTCACAAAAGAAGCCTACAAGAAGTACATCAAAGATTACATGAAATCAATCAAA
GGGAAACTTGAAGAACAGAGACCAGAAAGAGTAAAACCTTTTATGACAGGGGCTGCAGAA
CAAATCAAGCACATCCTTGCTAATTTCAAAAACTACCAGTTCTTTATTGGTGAAAACATG
AATCCAGATGGCATGGTTGCTCTATTGGACTACCGTGAGGATGGTGTGACCCCATATATG
ATTTTCTTTAAGGATGGTTTAGAAATGGAAAAATGTTAA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>172</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>19595.2</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>4.57</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>TCTP</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00838</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Translationally-controlled tumor protein
MIIYRDLISHDEMFSDIYKIREIADGLCLEVEGKMVSRTEGNIDDSLIGGNASAEGPEGE
GTESTVITGVDIVMNHHLQETSFTKEAYKKYIKDYMKSIKGKLEEQRPERVKPFMTGAAE
QIKHILANFKNYQFFIGENMNPDGMVALLDYREDGVTPYMIFFKDGLEMEKC</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>7573519</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P13693</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>TCTP_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1Y41</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AJ400717</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>TPT1</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>TPT1</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:12022</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gross B, Gaestel M, Bohm H, Bielka H: cDNA sequence coding for a translationally controlled human tumor protein.  Nucleic Acids Res. 1989 Oct 25;17(20):8367.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2813067</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ota T, Suzuki Y, Nishikawa T, Otsuki T, Sugiyama T, Irie R, Wakamatsu A, Hayashi K, Sato H, Nagai K, Kimura K, Makita H, Sekine M, Obayashi M, Nishi T, Shibahara T, Tanaka T, Ishii S, Yamamoto J, Saito K, Kawai Y, Isono Y, Nakamura Y, Nagahari K, Murakami K, Yasuda T, Iwayanagi T, Wagatsuma M, Shiratori A, Sudo H, Hosoiri T, Kaku Y, Kodaira H, Kondo H, Sugawara M, Takahashi M, Kanda K, Yokoi T, Furuya T, Kikkawa E, Omura Y, Abe K, Kamihara K, Katsuta N, Sato K, Tanikawa M, Yamazaki M, Ninomiya K, Ishibashi T, Yamashita H, Murakawa K, Fujimori K, Tanai H, Kimata M, Watanabe M, Hiraoka S, Chiba Y, Ishida S, Ono Y, Takiguchi S, Watanabe S, Yosida M, Hotuta T, Kusano J, Kanehori K, Takahashi-Fujii A, Hara H, Tanase TO, Nomura Y, Togiya S, Komai F, Hara R, Takeuchi K, Arita M, Imose N, Musashino K, Yuuki H, Oshima A, Sasaki N, Aotsuka S, Yoshikawa Y, Matsunawa H, Ichihara T, Shiohata N, Sano S, Moriya S, Momiyama H, Satoh N, Takami S, Terashima Y, Suzuki O, Nakagawa S, Senoh A, Mizoguchi H, Goto Y, Shimizu F, Wakebe H, Hishigaki H, Watanabe T, Sugiyama A, Takemoto M, Kawakami B, Yamazaki M, Watanabe K, Kumagai A, Itakura S, Fukuzumi Y, Fujimori Y, Komiyama M, Tashiro H, Tanigami A, Fujiwara T, Ono T, Yamada K, Fujii Y, Ozaki K, Hirao M, Ohmori Y, Kawabata A, Hikiji T, Kobatake N, Inagaki H, Ikema Y, Okamoto S, Okitani R, Kawakami T, Noguchi S, Itoh T, Shigeta K, Senba T, Matsumura K, Nakajima Y, Mizuno T, Morinaga M, Sasaki M, Togashi T, Oyama M, Hata H, Watanabe M, Komatsu T, Mizushima-Sugano J, Satoh T, Shirai Y, Takahashi Y, Nakagawa K, Okumura K, Nagase T, Nomura N, Kikuchi H, Masuho Y, Yamashita R, Nakai K, Yada T, Nakamura Y, Ohara O, Isogai T, Sugano S: Complete sequencing and characterization of 21,243 full-length human cDNAs. Nat Genet. 2004 Jan;36(1):40-5. Epub 2003 Dec 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14702039</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Dunham A, Matthews LH, Burton J, Ashurst JL, Howe KL, Ashcroft KJ, Beare DM, Burford DC, Hunt SE, Griffiths-Jones S, Jones MC, Keenan SJ, Oliver K, Scott CE, Ainscough R, Almeida JP, Ambrose KD, Andrews DT, Ashwell RI, Babbage AK, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Bannerjee R, Barlow KF, Bates K, Beasley H, Bird CP, Bray-Allen S, Brown AJ, Brown JY, Burrill W, Carder C, Carter NP, Chapman JC, Clamp ME, Clark SY, Clarke G, Clee CM, Clegg SC, Cobley V, Collins JE, Corby N, Coville GJ, Deloukas P, Dhami P, Dunham I, Dunn M, Earthrowl ME, Ellington AG, Faulkner L, Frankish AG, Frankland J, French L, Garner P, Garnett J, Gilbert JG, Gilson CJ, Ghori J, Grafham DV, Gribble SM, Griffiths C, Hall RE, Hammond S, Harley JL, Hart EA, Heath PD, Howden PJ, Huckle EJ, Hunt PJ, Hunt AR, Johnson C, Johnson D, Kay M, Kimberley AM, King A, Laird GK, Langford CJ, Lawlor S, Leongamornlert DA, Lloyd DM, Lloyd C, Loveland JE, Lovell J, Martin S, Mashreghi-Mohammadi M, McLaren SJ, McMurray A, Milne S, Moore MJ, Nickerson T, Palmer SA, Pearce AV, Peck AI, Pelan S, Phillimore B, Porter KM, Rice CM, Searle S, Sehra HK, Shownkeen R, Skuce CD, Smith M, Steward CA, Sycamore N, Tester J, Thomas DW, Tracey A, Tromans A, Tubby B, Wall M, Wallis JM, West AP, Whitehead SL, Willey DL, Wilming L, Wray PW, Wright MW, Young L, Coulson A, Durbin R, Hubbard T, Sulston JE, Beck S, Bentley DR, Rogers J, Ross MT: The DNA sequence and analysis of human chromosome 13.  Nature. 2004 Apr 1;428(6982):522-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15057823</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hochstrasser DF, Frutiger S, Paquet N, Bairoch A, Ravier F, Pasquali C, Sanchez JC, Tissot JD, Bjellqvist B, Vargas R, et al.: Human liver protein map: a reference database established by microsequencing and gel comparison. Electrophoresis. 1992 Dec;13(12):992-1001.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1286669</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rasmussen HH, van Damme J, Puype M, Gesser B, Celis JE, Vandekerckhove J: Microsequences of 145 proteins recorded in the two-dimensional gel protein database of normal human epidermal keratinocytes. Electrophoresis. 1992 Dec;13(12):960-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1286667</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rasmussen RK, Ji H, Eddes JS, Moritz RL, Reid GE, Simpson RJ, Dorow DS: Two-dimensional electrophoretic analysis of human breast carcinoma proteins: mapping of proteins that bind to the SH3 domain of mixed lineage kinase MLK2. Electrophoresis. 1997 Mar-Apr;18(3-4):588-98.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9150946</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>MacDonald SM, Rafnar T, Langdon J, Lichtenstein LM: Molecular identification of an IgE-dependent histamine-releasing factor.  Science. 1995 Aug 4;269(5224):688-90.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7542803</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Sanchez JC, Schaller D, Ravier F, Golaz O, Jaccoud S, Belet M, Wilkins MR, James R, Deshusses J, Hochstrasser D: Translationally controlled tumor protein: a protein identified in several nontumoral cells including erythrocytes. Electrophoresis. 1997 Jan;18(1):150-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9059837</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Yarm FR: Plk phosphorylation regulates the microtubule-stabilizing protein TCTP.  Mol Cell Biol. 2002 Sep;22(17):6209-21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12167714</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Amzallag N, Passer BJ, Allanic D, Segura E, Thery C, Goud B, Amson R, Telerman A: TSAP6 facilitates the secretion of translationally controlled tumor protein/histamine-releasing factor via a nonclassical pathway. J Biol Chem. 2004 Oct 29;279(44):46104-12. Epub 2004 Aug 19.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15319436</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Arcuri F, Papa S, Carducci A, Romagnoli R, Liberatori S, Riparbelli MG, Sanchez JC, Tosi P, del Vecchio MT: Translationally controlled tumor protein (TCTP) in the human prostate and prostate cancer cells: expression, distribution, and calcium binding activity. Prostate. 2004 Jul 1;60(2):130-40.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15162379</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Arcuri F, Papa S, Meini A, Carducci A, Romagnoli R, Bianchi L, Riparbelli MG, Sanchez JC, Palmi M, Tosi P, Cintorino M: The translationally controlled tumor protein is a novel calcium binding protein of the human placenta and regulates calcium handling in trophoblast cells. Biol Reprod. 2005 Oct;73(4):745-51. Epub 2005 Jun 15.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15958728</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Leong WF, Chow VT: Transcriptomic and proteomic analyses of rhabdomyosarcoma cells reveal differential cellular gene expression in response to enterovirus 71 infection. Cell Microbiol. 2006 Apr;8(4):565-80.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16548883</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Molina H, Horn DM, Tang N, Mathivanan S, Pandey A: Global proteomic profiling of phosphopeptides using electron transfer dissociation tandem mass spectrometry. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007 Feb 13;104(7):2199-204. Epub 2007 Feb 7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17287340</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Dephoure N, Zhou C, Villen J, Beausoleil SA, Bakalarski CE, Elledge SJ, Gygi SP: A quantitative atlas of mitotic phosphorylation.  Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2008 Aug 5;105(31):10762-7. Epub 2008 Jul 31.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18669648</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Choudhary C, Kumar C, Gnad F, Nielsen ML, Rehman M, Walther TC, Olsen JV, Mann M: Lysine acetylation targets protein complexes and co-regulates major cellular functions. Science. 2009 Aug 14;325(5942):834-40. Epub 2009 Jul 16.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19608861</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
