<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:07:08 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:07:08 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP08164</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13875</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Neuropeptide NPSF</synonym>
    <synonym>Neuropeptide NPVF</synonym>
    <synonym>Neuropeptide RFRP-1</synonym>
    <synonym>Neuropeptide RFRP-2</synonym>
    <synonym>Neuropeptide RFRP-3</synonym>
    <synonym>Neuropeptide VF</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>NPVF</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in G-protein coupled receptor activity</general_function>
  <specific_function>Neuropeptides NPSF and NPVF efficiently inhibit forskolin-induced production of cAMP, but RFRP-2 shows no inhibitory activity. Neuropeptide NPSF induces secretion of prolactin in rats. Neuropeptide NPVF blocks morphine-induced analgesia</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00058</accession>
      <name>Cyclic AMP</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Secreted</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:7</chromosome_location>
    <locus>7p21-p15</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;591 bp
ATGGAAATTATTTCATCAAAACTATTCATTTTATTGACTTTAGCCACTTCAAGCTTGTTA
ACATCAAACATTTTTTGTGCAGATGAATTAGTGATGTCCAATCTTCACAGCAAAGAAAAT
TATGACAAATATTCTGAGCCTAGAGGATACCCAAAAGGGGAAAGAAGCCTCAATTTTGAG
GAATTAAAAGATTGGGGACCAAAAAATGTTATTAAGATGAGTACACCTGCAGTCAATAAA
ATGCCACACTCCTTCGCCAACTTGCCATTGAGATTTGGGAGGAACGTTCAAGAAGAAAGA
AGTGCTGGAGCAACAGCCAACCTGCCTCTGAGATCTGGAAGAAATATGGAGGTGAGCCTC
GTGAGACGTGTTCCTAACCTGCCCCAAAGGTTTGGGAGAACAACAACAGCCAAAAGTGTC
TGCAGGATGCTGAGTGATTTGTGTCAAGGATCCATGCATTCACCATGTGCCAATGACTTA
TTTTACTCCATGACCTGCCAGCACCAAGAAATCCAGAATCCCGATCAAAAACAGTCAAGG
AGACTGCTATTCAAGAAAATAGATGATGCAGAATTGAAACAAGAAAAATAA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>196</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>22326.4</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>9.52</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>1-26</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;FMRFamide-related peptides
MEIISSKLFILLTLATSSLLTSNIFCADELVMSNLHSKENYDKYSEPRGYPKGERSLNFE
ELKDWGPKNVIKMSTPAVNKMPHSFANLPLRFGRNVQEERSAGATANLPLRSGRNMEVSL
VRRVPNLPQRFGRTTTAKSVCRMLSDLCQGSMHSPCANDLFYSMTCQHQEIQNPDQKQSR
RLLFKKIDDAELKQEK</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>11125708</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>Q9HCQ7</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>RFRP_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AB040290</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>NPVF</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>NPVF</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:13782</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hinuma S, Shintani Y, Fukusumi S, Iijima N, Matsumoto Y, Hosoya M, Fujii R, Watanabe T, Kikuchi K, Terao Y, Yano T, Yamamoto T, Kawamata Y, Habata Y, Asada M, Kitada C, Kurokawa T, Onda H, Nishimura O, Tanaka M, Ibata Y, Fujino M: New neuropeptides containing carboxy-terminal RFamide and their receptor in mammals. Nat Cell Biol. 2000 Oct;2(10):703-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11025660</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Schulz HL, Stoehr H, White K, van Driel MA, Hoyng CB, Cremers F, Weber BH: Genomic structure and assessment of the retinally expressed RFamide-related peptide gene in dominant cystoid macular dystrophy. Mol Vis. 2002 Mar 19;8:67-71.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11951088</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Liu Q, Guan XM, Martin WJ, McDonald TP, Clements MK, Jiang Q, Zeng Z, Jacobson M, Williams DL Jr, Yu H, Bomford D, Figueroa D, Mallee J, Wang R, Evans J, Gould R, Austin CP: Identification and characterization of novel mammalian neuropeptide FF-like peptides that attenuate morphine-induced antinociception. J Biol Chem. 2001 Oct 5;276(40):36961-9. Epub 2001 Jul 31.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11481330</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Scherer SW, Cheung J, MacDonald JR, Osborne LR, Nakabayashi K, Herbrick JA, Carson AR, Parker-Katiraee L, Skaug J, Khaja R, Zhang J, Hudek AK, Li M, Haddad M, Duggan GE, Fernandez BA, Kanematsu E, Gentles S, Christopoulos CC, Choufani S, Kwasnicka D, Zheng XH, Lai Z, Nusskern D, Zhang Q, Gu Z, Lu F, Zeesman S, Nowaczyk MJ, Teshima I, Chitayat D, Shuman C, Weksberg R, Zackai EH, Grebe TA, Cox SR, Kirkpatrick SJ, Rahman N, Friedman JM, Heng HH, Pelicci PG, Lo-Coco F, Belloni E, Shaffer LG, Pober B, Morton CC, Gusella JF, Bruns GA, Korf BR, Quade BJ, Ligon AH, Ferguson H, Higgins AW, Leach NT, Herrick SR, Lemyre E, Farra CG, Kim HG, Summers AM, Gripp KW, Roberts W, Szatmari P, Winsor EJ, Grzeschik KH, Teebi A, Minassian BA, Kere J, Armengol L, Pujana MA, Estivill X, Wilson MD, Koop BF, Tosi S, Moore GE, Boright AP, Zlotorynski E, Kerem B, Kroisel PM, Petek E, Oscier DG, Mould SJ, Dohner H, Dohner K, Rommens JM, Vincent JB, Venter JC, Li PW, Mural RJ, Adams MD, Tsui LC: Human chromosome 7: DNA sequence and biology.  Science. 2003 May 2;300(5620):767-72. Epub 2003 Apr 10.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12690205</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hillier LW, Fulton RS, Fulton LA, Graves TA, Pepin KH, Wagner-McPherson C, Layman D, Maas J, Jaeger S, Walker R, Wylie K, Sekhon M, Becker MC, O'Laughlin MD, Schaller ME, Fewell GA, Delehaunty KD, Miner TL, Nash WE, Cordes M, Du H, Sun H, Edwards J, Bradshaw-Cordum H, Ali J, Andrews S, Isak A, Vanbrunt A, Nguyen C, Du F, Lamar B, Courtney L, Kalicki J, Ozersky P, Bielicki L, Scott K, Holmes A, Harkins R, Harris A, Strong CM, Hou S, Tomlinson C, Dauphin-Kohlberg S, Kozlowicz-Reilly A, Leonard S, Rohlfing T, Rock SM, Tin-Wollam AM, Abbott A, Minx P, Maupin R, Strowmatt C, Latreille P, Miller N, Johnson D, Murray J, Woessner JP, Wendl MC, Yang SP, Schultz BR, Wallis JW, Spieth J, Bieri TA, Nelson JO, Berkowicz N, Wohldmann PE, Cook LL, Hickenbotham MT, Eldred J, Williams D, Bedell JA, Mardis ER, Clifton SW, Chissoe SL, Marra MA, Raymond C, Haugen E, Gillett W, Zhou Y, James R, Phelps K, Iadanoto S, Bubb K, Simms E, Levy R, Clendenning J, Kaul R, Kent WJ, Furey TS, Baertsch RA, Brent MR, Keibler E, Flicek P, Bork P, Suyama M, Bailey JA, Portnoy ME, Torrents D, Chinwalla AT, Gish WR, Eddy SR, McPherson JD, Olson MV, Eichler EE, Green ED, Waterston RH, Wilson RK: The DNA sequence of human chromosome 7.  Nature. 2003 Jul 10;424(6945):157-64.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12853948</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
