<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 19:02:12 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 19:02:12 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP02070</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>7551</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Enzyme</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Cachectin</synonym>
    <synonym>TNF-a</synonym>
    <synonym>TNF-alpha</synonym>
    <synonym>Tumor necrosis factor ligand superfamily member 2</synonym>
    <synonym>Tumor necrosis factor, membrane form</synonym>
    <synonym>Tumor necrosis factor, soluble form</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>TNF</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in tumor necrosis factor receptor binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Cytokine that binds to TNFRSF1A/TNFR1 and TNFRSF1B/TNFBR. It is mainly secreted by macrophages and can induce cell death of certain tumor cell lines. It is potent pyrogen causing fever by direct action or by stimulation of interleukin-1 secretion and is implicated in the induction of cachexia, Under certain conditions it can stimulate cell proliferation and induce cell differentiation</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00039</accession>
      <name>Butyric acid</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01514</accession>
      <name>Glucosamine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB05007</accession>
      <name>Simvastatin</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB05006</accession>
      <name>Atorvastatin</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB14746</accession>
      <name>Chloroquine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB13870</accession>
      <name>cis,trans-5'-Hydroxythalidomide</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15477</accession>
      <name>Clenbuterol</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15481</accession>
      <name>Pranlukast</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15496</accession>
      <name>Amrinone</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00863</accession>
      <name>Isopropyl alcohol</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB31643</accession>
      <name>Ethyl pyruvate</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>protein binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>receptor binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>cytokine receptor binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>tumor necrosis factor receptor superfamily binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>tumor necrosis factor receptor binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>immune system process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>immune response</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>cell part</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>membrane</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Tumor necrosis factor</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>soluble form:Secreted</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:6</chromosome_location>
    <locus>6p21.3</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;702 bp
ATGAGCACTGAAAGCATGATCCGGGACGTGGAGCTGGCCGAGGAGGCGCTCCCCAAGAAG
ACAGGGGGGCCCCAGGGCTCCAGGCGGTGCTTGTTCCTCAGCCTCTTCTCCTTCCTGATC
GTGGCAGGCGCCACCACGCTCTTCTGCCTGCTGCACTTTGGAGTGATCGGCCCCCAGAGG
GAAGAGTTCCCCAGGGACCTCTCTCTAATCAGCCCTCTGGCCCAGGCAGTCAGATCATCT
TCTCGAACCCCGAGTGACAAGCCTGTAGCCCATGTTGTAGCAAACCCTCAAGCTGAGGGG
CAGCTCCAGTGGCTGAACCGCCGGGCCAATGCCCTCCTGGCCAATGGCGTGGAGCTGAGA
GATAACCAGCTGGTGGTGCCATCAGAGGGCCTGTACCTCATCTACTCCCAGGTCCTCTTC
AAGGGCCAAGGCTGCCCCTCCACCCATGTGCTCCTCACCCACACCATCAGCCGCATCGCC
GTCTCCTACCAGACCAAGGTCAACCTCCTCTCTGCCATCAAGAGCCCCTGCCAGAGGGAG
ACCCCAGAGGGGGCTGAGGCCAAGCCCTGGTATGAGCCCATCTATCTGGGAGGGGTCTTC
CAGCTGGAGAAGGGTGACCGACTCAGCGCTGAGATCAATCGGCCCGACTATCTCGACTTT
GCCGAGTCTGGGCAGGTCTACTTTGGGATCATTGCCCTGTGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>233</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>25644.1</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>6.92</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>TNF</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00229</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>36-56</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Tumor necrosis factor
MSTESMIRDVELAEEALPKKTGGPQGSRRCLFLSLFSFLIVAGATTLFCLLHFGVIGPQR
EEFPRDLSLISPLAQAVRSSSRTPSDKPVAHVVANPQAEGQLQWLNRRANALLANGVELR
DNQLVVPSEGLYLIYSQVLFKGQGCPSTHVLLTHTISRIAVSYQTKVNLLSAIKSPCQRE
TPEGAEAKPWYEPIYLGGVFQLEKGDRLSAEINRPDYLDFAESGQVYFGIIAL</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>37220</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P01375</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>TNFA_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1A8M</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>X01394</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>TNF</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>TNF</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:11892</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Nedospasov SA, Shakhov AN, Turetskaya RL, Mett VA, Azizov MM, Georgiev GP, Korobko VG, Dobrynin VN, Filippov SA, Bystrov NS, et al.: Tandem arrangement of genes coding for tumor necrosis factor (TNF-alpha) and lymphotoxin (TNF-beta) in the human genome. Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol. 1986;51 Pt 1:611-24.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3555974</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Pennica D, Nedwin GE, Hayflick JS, Seeburg PH, Derynck R, Palladino MA, Kohr WJ, Aggarwal BB, Goeddel DV: Human tumour necrosis factor: precursor structure, expression and homology to lymphotoxin. Nature. 1984 Dec 20-1985 Jan 2;312(5996):724-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6392892</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shirai T, Yamaguchi H, Ito H, Todd CW, Wallace RB: Cloning and expression in Escherichia coli of the gene for human tumour necrosis factor. Nature. 1985 Feb 28-Mar 6;313(6005):803-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3883195</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Nedwin GE, Naylor SL, Sakaguchi AY, Smith D, Jarrett-Nedwin J, Pennica D, Goeddel DV, Gray PW: Human lymphotoxin and tumor necrosis factor genes: structure, homology and chromosomal localization. Nucleic Acids Res. 1985 Sep 11;13(17):6361-73.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2995927</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wang AM, Creasey AA, Ladner MB, Lin LS, Strickler J, Van Arsdell JN, Yamamoto R, Mark DF: Molecular cloning of the complementary DNA for human tumor necrosis factor. Science. 1985 Apr 12;228(4696):149-54.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3856324</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Marmenout A, Fransen L, Tavernier J, Van der Heyden J, Tizard R, Kawashima E, Shaw A, Johnson MJ, Semon D, Muller R, et al.: Molecular cloning and expression of human tumor necrosis factor and comparison with mouse tumor necrosis factor. Eur J Biochem. 1985 Nov 4;152(3):515-22.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3932069</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Iris FJ, Bougueleret L, Prieur S, Caterina D, Primas G, Perrot V, Jurka J, Rodriguez-Tome P, Claverie JM, Dausset J, et al.: Dense Alu clustering and a potential new member of the NF kappa B family within a 90 kilobase HLA class III segment. Nat Genet. 1993 Feb;3(2):137-45.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8499947</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Neville MJ, Campbell RD: A new member of the Ig superfamily and a V-ATPase G subunit are among the predicted products of novel genes close to the TNF locus in the human MHC. J Immunol. 1999 Apr 15;162(8):4745-54.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10202016</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Xie T, Rowen L, Aguado B, Ahearn ME, Madan A, Qin S, Campbell RD, Hood L: Analysis of the gene-dense major histocompatibility complex class III region and its comparison to mouse. Genome Res. 2003 Dec;13(12):2621-36.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14656967</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Takakura-Yamamoto R, Yamamoto S, Fukuda S, Kurimoto M: O-glycosylated species of natural human tumor-necrosis factor-alpha.  Eur J Biochem. 1996 Jan 15;235(1-2):431-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8631363</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Pocsik E, Duda E, Wallach D: Phosphorylation of the 26 kDa TNF precursor in monocytic cells and in transfected HeLa cells. J Inflamm. 1995;45(3):152-60.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8597870</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Watts AD, Hunt NH, Wanigasekara Y, Bloomfield G, Wallach D, Roufogalis BD, Chaudhri G: A casein kinase I motif present in the cytoplasmic domain of members of the tumour necrosis factor ligand family is implicated in 'reverse signalling'. EMBO J. 1999 Apr 15;18(8):2119-26.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10205166</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Van Ostade X, Tavernier J, Prange T, Fiers W: Localization of the active site of human tumour necrosis factor (hTNF) by mutational analysis. EMBO J. 1991 Apr;10(4):827-36.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2009860</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Stevenson FT, Bursten SL, Locksley RM, Lovett DH: Myristyl acylation of the tumor necrosis factor alpha precursor on specific lysine residues. J Exp Med. 1992 Oct 1;176(4):1053-62.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1402651</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Moss ML, Jin SL, Milla ME, Bickett DM, Burkhart W, Carter HL, Chen WJ, Clay WC, Didsbury JR, Hassler D, Hoffman CR, Kost TA, Lambert MH, Leesnitzer MA, McCauley P, McGeehan G, Mitchell J, Moyer M, Pahel G, Rocque W, Overton LK, Schoenen F, Seaton T, Su JL, Becherer JD, et al.: Cloning of a disintegrin metalloproteinase that processes precursor tumour-necrosis factor-alpha. Nature. 1997 Feb 20;385(6618):733-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9034191</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Jones EY, Stuart DI, Walker NP: Structure of tumour necrosis factor.  Nature. 1989 Mar 16;338(6212):225-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2922050</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Jones EY, Stuart DI, Walker NP: The structure of tumour necrosis factor--implications for biological function. J Cell Sci Suppl. 1990;13:11-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1964681</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Eck MJ, Sprang SR: The structure of tumor necrosis factor-alpha at 2.6 A resolution. Implications for receptor binding. J Biol Chem. 1989 Oct 15;264(29):17595-605.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2551905</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Reed C, Fu ZQ, Wu J, Xue YN, Harrison RW, Chen MJ, Weber IT: Crystal structure of TNF-alpha mutant R31D with greater affinity for receptor R1 compared with R2. Protein Eng. 1997 Oct;10(10):1101-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9488135</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Cha SS, Kim JS, Cho HS, Shin NK, Jeong W, Shin HC, Kim YJ, Hahn JH, Oh BH: High resolution crystal structure of a human tumor necrosis factor-alpha mutant with low systemic toxicity. J Biol Chem. 1998 Jan 23;273(4):2153-60.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9442056</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Balding J, Kane D, Livingstone W, Mynett-Johnson L, Bresnihan B, Smith O, FitzGerald O: Cytokine gene polymorphisms: association with psoriatic arthritis susceptibility and severity. Arthritis Rheum. 2003 May;48(5):1408-13.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12746914</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kim YJ, Lee HS, Yoon JH, Kim CY, Park MH, Kim LH, Park BL, Shin HD: Association of TNF-alpha promoter polymorphisms with the clearance of hepatitis B virus infection. Hum Mol Genet. 2003 Oct 1;12(19):2541-6. Epub 2003 Aug 5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12915457</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Butyric acid</name>
        <accession>HMDB00039</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Fukae J, Amasaki Y, Yamashita Y, Bohgaki T, Yasuda S, Jodo S, Atsumi T, Koike T: Butyrate suppresses tumor necrosis factor alpha production by regulating specific messenger RNA degradation mediated through a cis-acting AU-rich element. Arthritis Rheum. 2005 Sep;52(9):2697-707.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>16142751</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Chloroquine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14746</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Jang CH, Choi JH, Byun MS, Jue DM: Chloroquine inhibits production of TNF-alpha, IL-1beta and IL-6 from lipopolysaccharide-stimulated human monocytes/macrophages by different modes. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2006 Jun;45(6):703-10. Epub 2006 Jan 17.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>16418198</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Chloroquine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14746</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Rachmilewitz D, Karmeli F, Shteingart S, Lee J, Takabayashi K, Raz E: Immunostimulatory oligonucleotides inhibit colonic proinflammatory cytokine production in ulcerative colitis. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2006 May;12(5):339-45.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>16670522</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Chloroquine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14746</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Wozniacka A, Lesiak A, Narbutt J, McCauliffe DP, Sysa-Jedrzejowska A: Chloroquine treatment influences proinflammatory cytokine levels in systemic lupus erythematosus patients. Lupus. 2006;15(5):268-75.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>16761500</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Chloroquine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14746</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Lim EJ, Lee SH, Lee JG, Chin BR, Bae YS, Kim JR, Lee CH, Baek SH: Activation of toll-like receptor-9 induces matrix metalloproteinase-9 expression through Akt and tumor necrosis factor-alpha signaling. FEBS Lett. 2006 Aug 7;580(18):4533-8. Epub 2006 Jul 17.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>16870179</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Chloroquine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14746</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Dias-Melicio LA, Calvi SA, Bordon AP, Golim MA, Peracoli MT, Soares AM: Chloroquine is therapeutic in murine experimental model of paracoccidioidomycosis. FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol. 2007 Jun;50(1):133-43. Epub 2007 Apr 23.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17456179</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>cis,trans-5'-Hydroxythalidomide</name>
        <accession>HMDB13870</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Richardson P, Hideshima T, Anderson K: Thalidomide in multiple myeloma.  Biomed Pharmacother. 2002 May;56(3):115-28.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>12046682</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>cis,trans-5'-Hydroxythalidomide</name>
        <accession>HMDB13870</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Fu LM, Fu-Liu CS: Thalidomide and tuberculosis.  Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2002 Jul;6(7):569-72.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>12102294</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>cis,trans-5'-Hydroxythalidomide</name>
        <accession>HMDB13870</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Enomoto N, Takei Y, Hirose M, Ikejima K, Miwa H, Kitamura T, Sato N: Thalidomide prevents alcoholic liver injury in rats through suppression of Kupffer cell sensitization and TNF-alpha production. Gastroenterology. 2002 Jul;123(1):291-300.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>12105857</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>cis,trans-5'-Hydroxythalidomide</name>
        <accession>HMDB13870</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Rajkumar SV: Thalidomide in the treatment of multiple myeloma.  Expert Rev Anticancer Ther. 2001 Jun;1(1):20-8.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>12113124</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>cis,trans-5'-Hydroxythalidomide</name>
        <accession>HMDB13870</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Vescovo G, Ravara B, Angelini A, Sandri M, Carraro U, Ceconi C, Dalla Libera L: Effect of thalidomide on the skeletal muscle in experimental heart failure.  Eur J Heart Fail. 2002 Aug;4(4):455-60.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>12167383</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>cis,trans-5'-Hydroxythalidomide</name>
        <accession>HMDB13870</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Chen X, Ji ZL, Chen YZ: TTD: Therapeutic Target Database.  Nucleic Acids Res. 2002 Jan 1;30(1):412-5.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>11752352</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Clenbuterol</name>
        <accession>HMDB15477</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Izeboud CA, Mocking JA, Monshouwer M, van Miert AS, Witkamp RF: Participation of beta-adrenergic receptors on macrophages in modulation of LPS-induced cytokine release. J Recept Signal Transduct Res. 1999 Jan-Jul;19(1-4):191-202.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>10071758</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Clenbuterol</name>
        <accession>HMDB15477</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Yoshimura T: [Modulation of cytokine production from human mononuclear cells by several agents]. Yakugaku Zasshi. 2000 Dec;120(12):1277-90.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>11193379</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Clenbuterol</name>
        <accession>HMDB15477</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Izeboud CA, Hoebe KH, Grootendorst AF, Nijmeijer SM, van Miert AS, Witkamp RR, Rodenburg RJ: Endotoxin-induced liver damage in rats is minimized by beta 2-adrenoceptor stimulation. Inflamm Res. 2004 Mar;53(3):93-9. Epub 2004 Feb 16.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>15021963</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Clenbuterol</name>
        <accession>HMDB15477</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Laan TT, Bull S, Pirie RS, Fink-Gremmels J: Evaluation of cytokine production by equine alveolar macrophages exposed to lipopolysaccharide, Aspergillus fumigatus, and a suspension of hay dust. Am J Vet Res. 2005 Sep;66(9):1584-9.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>16261833</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Clenbuterol</name>
        <accession>HMDB15477</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>van den Hoven R, Duvigneau JC, Hartl RT, Gemeiner M: Clenbuterol affects the expression of messenger RNA for interleukin 10 in peripheral leukocytes from horses challenged intrabronchially with lipopolysaccharides. Vet Res Commun. 2006 Nov;30(8):921-8.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17139543</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pranlukast</name>
        <accession>HMDB15481</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Tomari S, Matsuse H, Machida I, Kondo Y, Kawano T, Obase Y, Fukushima C, Shimoda T, Kohno S: Pranlukast, a cysteinyl leukotriene receptor 1 antagonist, attenuates allergen-specific tumour necrosis factor alpha production and nuclear factor kappa B nuclear translocation in peripheral blood monocytes from atopic asthmatics. Clin Exp Allergy. 2003 Jun;33(6):795-801.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>12801315</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pranlukast</name>
        <accession>HMDB15481</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Ichiyama T, Hasegawa S, Umeda M, Terai K, Matsubara T, Furukawa S: Pranlukast inhibits NF-kappa B activation in human monocytes/macrophages and T cells. Clin Exp Allergy. 2003 Jun;33(6):802-7.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>12801316</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pranlukast</name>
        <accession>HMDB15481</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Ichiyama T, Kajimoto M, Hasegawa M, Hashimoto K, Matsubara T, Furukawa S: Cysteinyl leukotrienes enhance tumour necrosis factor-alpha-induced matrix metalloproteinase-9 in human monocytes/macrophages. Clin Exp Allergy. 2007 Apr;37(4):608-14.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17430359</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Amrinone</name>
        <accession>HMDB15496</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Kumar A, Kosuri R, Kandula P, Dimou C, Allen J, Parrillo JE: Effects of epinephrine and amrinone on contractility and cyclic adenosine monophosphate generation of tumor necrosis factor alpha-exposed cardiac myocytes. Crit Care Med. 1999 Feb;27(2):286-92.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>10075051</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Amrinone</name>
        <accession>HMDB15496</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Bergman MR, Kao RH, McCune SA, Holycross BJ: Myocardial tumor necrosis factor-alpha secretion in hypertensive and heart failure-prone rats. Am J Physiol. 1999 Aug;277(2 Pt 2):H543-50.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>10444479</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Amrinone</name>
        <accession>HMDB15496</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Haddad JJ, Land SC, Tarnow-Mordi WO, Zembala M, Kowalczyk D, Lauterbach R: Immunopharmacological potential of selective phosphodiesterase inhibition. I. Differential regulation of lipopolysaccharide-mediated proinflammatory cytokine (interleukin-6 and tumor necrosis factor-alpha) biosynthesis in alveolar epithelial cells. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 2002 Feb;300(2):559-66.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>11805217</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Amrinone</name>
        <accession>HMDB15496</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Marx D, Tassabehji M, Heer S, Huttenbrink KB, Szelenyi I: Modulation of TNF and GM-CSF release from dispersed human nasal polyp cells and human whole blood by inhibitors of different PDE isoenzymes and glucocorticoids. Pulm Pharmacol Ther. 2002;15(1):7-15.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>11969359</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Amrinone</name>
        <accession>HMDB15496</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Giroir BP, Beutler B: Effect of amrinone on tumor necrosis factor production in endotoxic shock.  Circ Shock. 1992 Mar;36(3):200-7.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>1611705</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Isopropyl alcohol</name>
        <accession>HMDB00863</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Berman HM, Westbrook J, Feng Z, Gilliland G, Bhat TN, Weissig H, Shindyalov IN, Bourne PE: The Protein Data Bank.  Nucleic Acids Res. 2000 Jan 1;28(1):235-42.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>10592235</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
