<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:01:35 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:01:35 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP07685</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13394</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>12 kDa FK506-binding protein</synonym>
    <synonym>12 kDa FKBP</synonym>
    <synonym>FK506-binding protein 1A</synonym>
    <synonym>FKBP-12</synonym>
    <synonym>FKBP-1A</synonym>
    <synonym>Immunophilin FKBP12</synonym>
    <synonym>PPIase FKBP1A</synonym>
    <synonym>Rotamase</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>FKBP1A</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in protein folding</general_function>
  <specific_function>May play a role in modulation of ryanodine receptor isoform-1 (RYR-1), a component of the calcium release channel of skeletal muscle sarcoplasmic reticulum. There are four molecules of FKBP12 per skeletal muscle RYR. PPIases accelerate the folding of proteins. It catalyzes the cis-trans isomerization of proline imidic peptide bonds in oligopeptides</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB14481</accession>
      <name>Pimecrolimus</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15002</accession>
      <name>Tacrolimus</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15015</accession>
      <name>Sirolimus</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>macromolecule metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>protein metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>cellular protein metabolic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>protein folding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasm</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:2</chromosome_location>
    <locus>20p13</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;327 bp
ATGGGAGTGCAGGTGGAAACCATCTCCCCAGGAGACGGGCGCACCTTCCCCAAGCGCGGC
CAGACCTGCGTGGTGCACTACACCGGGATGCTTGAAGATGGAAAGAAATTTGATTCCTCC
CGGGACAGAAACAAGCCCTTTAAGTTTATGCTAGGCAAGCAGGAGGTGATCCGAGGCTGG
GAAGAAGGGGTTGCCCAGATGAGTGTGGGTCAGAGAGCCAAACTGACTATATCTCCAGAT
TATGCCTATGGTGCCACTGGGCACCCAGGCATCATCCCACCACATGCCACTCTCGTCTTC
GATGTGGAGCTTCTAAAACTGGAATGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>108</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>11950.7</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>8.48</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>FKBP_C</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00254</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Peptidyl-prolyl cis-trans isomerase FKBP1A
MGVQVETISPGDGRTFPKRGQTCVVHYTGMLEDGKKFDSSRDRNKPFKFMLGKQEVIRGW
EEGVAQMSVGQRAKLTISPDYAYGATGHPGIIPPHATLVFDVELLKLE</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id/>
  <uniprot_id>P62942</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>FKB1A_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1J4I</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>M34539</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>FKBP1A</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>FKBP1A</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:3711</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Maki N, Sekiguchi F, Nishimaki J, Miwa K, Hayano T, Takahashi N, Suzuki M: Complementary DNA encoding the human T-cell FK506-binding protein, a peptidylprolyl cis-trans isomerase distinct from cyclophilin. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1990 Jul;87(14):5440-3.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1695378</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Standaert RF, Galat A, Verdine GL, Schreiber SL: Molecular cloning and overexpression of the human FK506-binding protein FKBP. Nature. 1990 Aug 16;346(6285):671-4.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1696686</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>DiLella AG, Craig RJ: Exon organization of the human FKBP-12 gene: correlation with structural and functional protein domains. Biochemistry. 1991 Sep 3;30(35):8512-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1716149</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Peattie DA, Hsiao K, Benasutti M, Lippke JA: Three distinct messenger RNAs can encode the human immunosuppressant-binding protein FKBP12. Gene. 1994 Dec 15;150(2):251-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7529739</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Deloukas P, Matthews LH, Ashurst J, Burton J, Gilbert JG, Jones M, Stavrides G, Almeida JP, Babbage AK, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Barlow KF, Bates KN, Beard LM, Beare DM, Beasley OP, Bird CP, Blakey SE, Bridgeman AM, Brown AJ, Buck D, Burrill W, Butler AP, Carder C, Carter NP, Chapman JC, Clamp M, Clark G, Clark LN, Clark SY, Clee CM, Clegg S, Cobley VE, Collier RE, Connor R, Corby NR, Coulson A, Coville GJ, Deadman R, Dhami P, Dunn M, Ellington AG, Frankland JA, Fraser A, French L, Garner P, Grafham DV, Griffiths C, Griffiths MN, Gwilliam R, Hall RE, Hammond S, Harley JL, Heath PD, Ho S, Holden JL, Howden PJ, Huckle E, Hunt AR, Hunt SE, Jekosch K, Johnson CM, Johnson D, Kay MP, Kimberley AM, King A, Knights A, Laird GK, Lawlor S, Lehvaslaiho MH, Leversha M, Lloyd C, Lloyd DM, Lovell JD, Marsh VL, Martin SL, McConnachie LJ, McLay K, McMurray AA, Milne S, Mistry D, Moore MJ, Mullikin JC, Nickerson T, Oliver K, Parker A, Patel R, Pearce TA, Peck AI, Phillimore BJ, Prathalingam SR, Plumb RW, Ramsay H, Rice CM, Ross MT, Scott CE, Sehra HK, Shownkeen R, Sims S, Skuce CD, Smith ML, Soderlund C, Steward CA, Sulston JE, Swann M, Sycamore N, Taylor R, Tee L, Thomas DW, Thorpe A, Tracey A, Tromans AC, Vaudin M, Wall M, Wallis JM, Whitehead SL, Whittaker P, Willey DL, Williams L, Williams SA, Wilming L, Wray PW, Hubbard T, Durbin RM, Bentley DR, Beck S, Rogers J: The DNA sequence and comparative analysis of human chromosome 20.  Nature. 2001 Dec 20-27;414(6866):865-71.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11780052</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Siekierka JJ, Wiederrecht G, Greulich H, Boulton D, Hung SH, Cryan J, Hodges PJ, Sigal NH: The cytosolic-binding protein for the immunosuppressant FK-506 is both a ubiquitous and highly conserved peptidyl-prolyl cis-trans isomerase. J Biol Chem. 1990 Dec 5;265(34):21011-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1701173</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Harding MW, Galat A, Uehling DE, Schreiber SL: A receptor for the immunosuppressant FK506 is a cis-trans peptidyl-prolyl isomerase. Nature. 1989 Oct 26;341(6244):758-60.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2477715</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gevaert K, Goethals M, Martens L, Van Damme J, Staes A, Thomas GR, Vandekerckhove J: Exploring proteomes and analyzing protein processing by mass spectrometric identification of sorted N-terminal peptides. Nat Biotechnol. 2003 May;21(5):566-9. Epub 2003 Mar 31.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12665801</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Mayya V, Lundgren DH, Hwang SI, Rezaul K, Wu L, Eng JK, Rodionov V, Han DK: Quantitative phosphoproteomic analysis of T cell receptor signaling reveals system-wide modulation of protein-protein interactions. Sci Signal. 2009 Aug 18;2(84):ra46.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19690332</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Choudhary C, Kumar C, Gnad F, Nielsen ML, Rehman M, Walther TC, Olsen JV, Mann M: Lysine acetylation targets protein complexes and co-regulates major cellular functions. Science. 2009 Aug 14;325(5942):834-40. Epub 2009 Jul 16.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19608861</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rosen MK, Michnick SW, Karplus M, Schreiber SL: Proton and nitrogen sequential assignments and secondary structure determination of the human FK506 and rapamycin binding protein. Biochemistry. 1991 May 14;30(19):4774-89.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1709363</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Michnick SW, Rosen MK, Wandless TJ, Karplus M, Schreiber SL: Solution structure of FKBP, a rotamase enzyme and receptor for FK506 and rapamycin. Science. 1991 May 10;252(5007):836-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1709301</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Lepre CA, Thomson JA, Moore JM: Solution structure of FK506 bound to FKBP-12.  FEBS Lett. 1992 May 4;302(1):89-96.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1375171</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Xu RX, Nettesheim D, Olejniczak ET, Meadows R, Gemmecker G, Fesik SW: 1H, 13C, and 15N assignments and secondary structure of the FK506 binding protein when bound to ascomycin. Biopolymers. 1993 Apr;33(4):535-50.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7682113</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Van Duyne GD, Standaert RF, Karplus PA, Schreiber SL, Clardy J: Atomic structure of FKBP-FK506, an immunophilin-immunosuppressant complex.  Science. 1991 May 10;252(5007):839-42.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1709302</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Van Duyne GD, Standaert RF, Karplus PA, Schreiber SL, Clardy J: Atomic structures of the human immunophilin FKBP-12 complexes with FK506 and rapamycin. J Mol Biol. 1993 Jan 5;229(1):105-24.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7678431</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Burkhard P, Taylor P, Walkinshaw MD: X-ray structures of small ligand-FKBP complexes provide an estimate for hydrophobic interaction energies. J Mol Biol. 2000 Jan 28;295(4):953-62.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10656803</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pimecrolimus</name>
        <accession>HMDB14481</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Reitamo S, Remitz A, Kyllonen H, Saarikko J: Topical noncorticosteroid immunomodulation in the treatment of atopic dermatitis.  Am J Clin Dermatol. 2002;3(6):381-8.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>12113647</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Tacrolimus</name>
        <accession>HMDB15002</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Labrande C, Velly L, Canolle B, Guillet B, Masmejean F, Nieoullon A, Pisano P: Neuroprotective effects of tacrolimus (FK506) in a model of ischemic cortical cell cultures: role of glutamate uptake and FK506 binding protein 12 kDa. Neuroscience. 2006;137(1):231-9. Epub 2005 Nov 10.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>16289353</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Tacrolimus</name>
        <accession>HMDB15002</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Masri M, Rizk S, Barbari A, Stephan A, Kamel G, Rost M: An assay for the determination of sirolimus levels in the lymphocyte of transplant patients. Transplant Proc. 2007 May;39(4):1204-6.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17524933</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Sirolimus</name>
        <accession>HMDB15015</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Chen X, Ji ZL, Chen YZ: TTD: Therapeutic Target Database.  Nucleic Acids Res. 2002 Jan 1;30(1):412-5.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>11752352</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Sirolimus</name>
        <accession>HMDB15015</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Sehgal SN: Sirolimus: its discovery, biological properties, and mechanism of action.  Transplant Proc. 2003 May;35(3 Suppl):7S-14S.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>12742462</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
