<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:00:02 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:00:02 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP07530</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13238</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>CCP</synonym>
    <synonym>Calcitonin</synonym>
    <synonym>Calcitonin carboxyl-terminal peptide</synonym>
    <synonym>Katacalcin</synonym>
    <synonym>PDN-21</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>CALCA</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in hormone activity</general_function>
  <specific_function>Katacalcin is a potent plasma calcium-lowering peptide</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>protein binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>receptor binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>hormone activity</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>extracellular region</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Secreted</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>11p15.2</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;426 bp
ATGGGCTTCCAAAAGTTCTCCCCCTTCCTGGCTCTCAGCATCTTGGTCCTGTTGCAGGCA
GGCAGCCTCCATGCAGCACCATTCAGGTCTGCCCTGGAGAGCAGCCCAGCAGACCCGGCC
ACGCTCAGTGAGGACGAAGCGCGCCTCCTGCTGGCTGCACTGGTGCAGGACTATGTGCAG
ATGAAGGCCAGTGAGCTGGAGCAGGAGCAAGAGAGAGAGGGCTCCAGCCTGGACAGCCCC
AGATCTAAGCGGTGCGGTAATCTGAGTACTTGCATGCTGGGCACATACACGCAGGACTTC
AACAAGTTTCACACGTTCCCCCAAACTGCAATTGGGGTTGGAGCACCTGGAAAGAAAAGG
GATATGTCCAGCGACTTGGAGAGAGACCATCGCCCTCATGTTAGCATGCCCCAGAATGCC
AACTAA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>141</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>15467.3</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>6.1</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Calc_CGRP_IAPP</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00214</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>1-25</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Calcitonin
MGFQKFSPFLALSILVLLQAGSLHAAPFRSALESSPADPATLSEDEARLLLAALVQDYVQ
MKASELEQEQEREGSSLDSPRSKRCGNLSTCMLGTYTQDFNKFHTFPQTAIGVGAPGKKR
DMSSDLERDHRPHVSMPQNAN</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>76880484</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P01258</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>CALC_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>NM_001033952.2</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>CALCA</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>CALCA</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:1437</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Le Moullec JM, Jullienne A, Chenais J, Lasmoles F, Guliana JM, Milhaud G, Moukhtar MS: The complete sequence of human preprocalcitonin.  FEBS Lett. 1984 Feb 13;167(1):93-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6546550</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Jonas V, Lin CR, Kawashima E, Semon D, Swanson LW, Mermod JJ, Evans RM, Rosenfeld MG: Alternative RNA processing events in human calcitonin/calcitonin gene-related peptide gene expression. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1985 Apr;82(7):1994-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3872459</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Craig RK, Riley JH, Edbrooke MR, Broad PM, Foord SM, Al-Kazwini SJ, Holman JJ, Marshall I: Expression and function of the human calcitonin/alpha-CGRP gene in health and disease. Biochem Soc Symp. 1986;52:91-105.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3034287</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Riley JH, Edbrooke MR, Craig RK: Ectopic synthesis of high-Mr calcitonin by the BEN lung carcinoma cell line reflects aberrant proteolytic processing. FEBS Lett. 1986 Mar 17;198(1):71-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3485540</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Minvielle S, Giscard-Dartevelle S, Cohen R, Taboulet J, Labye F, Jullienne A, Rivaille P, Milhaud G, Moukhtar MS, Lasmoles F: A novel calcitonin carboxyl-terminal peptide produced in medullary thyroid carcinoma by alternative RNA processing of the calcitonin/calcitonin gene-related peptide gene. J Biol Chem. 1991 Dec 25;266(36):24627-31.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1761559</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Taylor TD, Noguchi H, Totoki Y, Toyoda A, Kuroki Y, Dewar K, Lloyd C, Itoh T, Takeda T, Kim DW, She X, Barlow KF, Bloom T, Bruford E, Chang JL, Cuomo CA, Eichler E, FitzGerald MG, Jaffe DB, LaButti K, Nicol R, Park HS, Seaman C, Sougnez C, Yang X, Zimmer AR, Zody MC, Birren BW, Nusbaum C, Fujiyama A, Hattori M, Rogers J, Lander ES, Sakaki Y: Human chromosome 11 DNA sequence and analysis including novel gene identification. Nature. 2006 Mar 23;440(7083):497-500.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16554811</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Nelkin BD, Rosenfeld KI, de Bustros A, Leong SS, Roos BA, Baylin SB: Structure and expression of a gene encoding human calcitonin and calcitonin gene related peptide. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1984 Sep 17;123(2):648-55.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6148938</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Edbrooke MR, Parker D, McVey JH, Riley JH, Sorenson GD, Pettengill OS, Craig RK: Expression of the human calcitonin/CGRP gene in lung and thyroid carcinoma. EMBO J. 1985 Mar;4(3):715-24.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2408883</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Neher R, Riniker B, Rittel W, Zuber H: [Human calcitonin. Structure of calcitonin M and D]  Helv Chim Acta. 1968;51(8):1900-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>5760861</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Motta A, Temussi PA, Wunsch E, Bovermann G: A 1H NMR study of human calcitonin in solution.  Biochemistry. 1991 Mar 5;30(9):2364-71.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2001366</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hillyard CJ, Myers C, Abeyasekera G, Stevvensvenson JC, Craig RK, MacIntyre I: Katacalcin: a new plasma calcium-lowering hormone.  Lancet. 1983 Apr 16;1(8329):846-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6132180</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hillman RT, Green RE, Brenner SE: An unappreciated role for RNA surveillance.  Genome Biol. 2004;5(2):R8. Epub 2004 Feb 2.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14759258</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
