<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:04:56 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:04:56 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP07983</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13694</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Calvasculin</synonym>
    <synonym>Metastasin</synonym>
    <synonym>Placental calcium-binding protein</synonym>
    <synonym>Protein Mts1</synonym>
    <synonym>S100 calcium-binding protein A4</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>S100A4</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in calcium ion binding</general_function>
  <specific_function/>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB14969</accession>
      <name>Trifluoperazine</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>cation binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>metal ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>calcium ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>1q21</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;306 bp
ATGGCGTGCCCTCTGGAGAAGGCCCTGGATGTGATGGTGTCCACCTTCCACAAGTACTCG
GGCAAAGAGGGTGACAAGTTCAAGCTCAACAAGTCAGAACTAAAGGAGCTGCTGACCCGG
GAGCTGCCCAGCTTCTTGGGGAAAAGGACAGATGAAGCTGCTTTCCAGAAGCTGATGAGC
AACTTGGACAGCAACAGGGACAACGAGGTGGACTTCCAAGAGTACTGTGTCTTCCTGTCC
TGCATCGCCATGATGTGTAACGAATTCTTTGAAGGCTTCCCAGATAAGCAGCCCAGGAAG
AAATGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>101</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>11728.4</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>5.92</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>S_100</name>
        <pfam_id>PF01023</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Protein S100-A4
MACPLEKALDVMVSTFHKYSGKEGDKFKLNKSELKELLTRELPSFLGKRTDEAAFQKLMS
NLDSNRDNEVDFQEYCVFLSCIAMMCNEFFEGFPDKQPRKK</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>158257598</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P26447</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>S10A4_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1M31</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AK292083</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>S100A4</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>S100A4</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:10494</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Engelkamp D, Schafer BW, Erne P, Heizmann CW: S100 alpha, CAPL, and CACY: molecular cloning and expression analysis of three calcium-binding proteins from human heart. Biochemistry. 1992 Oct 27;31(42):10258-64.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1384693</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Engelkamp D, Schafer BW, Mattei MG, Erne P, Heizmann CW: Six S100 genes are clustered on human chromosome 1q21: identification of two genes coding for the two previously unreported calcium-binding proteins S100D and S100E. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1993 Jul 15;90(14):6547-51.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8341667</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Tulchinsky E, Ford HL, Kramerov D, Reshetnyak E, Grigorian M, Zain S, Lukanidin E: Transcriptional analysis of the mts1 gene with specific reference to 5' flanking sequences. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1992 Oct 1;89(19):9146-50.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1329089</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ota T, Suzuki Y, Nishikawa T, Otsuki T, Sugiyama T, Irie R, Wakamatsu A, Hayashi K, Sato H, Nagai K, Kimura K, Makita H, Sekine M, Obayashi M, Nishi T, Shibahara T, Tanaka T, Ishii S, Yamamoto J, Saito K, Kawai Y, Isono Y, Nakamura Y, Nagahari K, Murakami K, Yasuda T, Iwayanagi T, Wagatsuma M, Shiratori A, Sudo H, Hosoiri T, Kaku Y, Kodaira H, Kondo H, Sugawara M, Takahashi M, Kanda K, Yokoi T, Furuya T, Kikkawa E, Omura Y, Abe K, Kamihara K, Katsuta N, Sato K, Tanikawa M, Yamazaki M, Ninomiya K, Ishibashi T, Yamashita H, Murakawa K, Fujimori K, Tanai H, Kimata M, Watanabe M, Hiraoka S, Chiba Y, Ishida S, Ono Y, Takiguchi S, Watanabe S, Yosida M, Hotuta T, Kusano J, Kanehori K, Takahashi-Fujii A, Hara H, Tanase TO, Nomura Y, Togiya S, Komai F, Hara R, Takeuchi K, Arita M, Imose N, Musashino K, Yuuki H, Oshima A, Sasaki N, Aotsuka S, Yoshikawa Y, Matsunawa H, Ichihara T, Shiohata N, Sano S, Moriya S, Momiyama H, Satoh N, Takami S, Terashima Y, Suzuki O, Nakagawa S, Senoh A, Mizoguchi H, Goto Y, Shimizu F, Wakebe H, Hishigaki H, Watanabe T, Sugiyama A, Takemoto M, Kawakami B, Yamazaki M, Watanabe K, Kumagai A, Itakura S, Fukuzumi Y, Fujimori Y, Komiyama M, Tashiro H, Tanigami A, Fujiwara T, Ono T, Yamada K, Fujii Y, Ozaki K, Hirao M, Ohmori Y, Kawabata A, Hikiji T, Kobatake N, Inagaki H, Ikema Y, Okamoto S, Okitani R, Kawakami T, Noguchi S, Itoh T, Shigeta K, Senba T, Matsumura K, Nakajima Y, Mizuno T, Morinaga M, Sasaki M, Togashi T, Oyama M, Hata H, Watanabe M, Komatsu T, Mizushima-Sugano J, Satoh T, Shirai Y, Takahashi Y, Nakagawa K, Okumura K, Nagase T, Nomura N, Kikuchi H, Masuho Y, Yamashita R, Nakai K, Yada T, Nakamura Y, Ohara O, Isogai T, Sugano S: Complete sequencing and characterization of 21,243 full-length human cDNAs. Nat Genet. 2004 Jan;36(1):40-5. Epub 2003 Dec 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14702039</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gregory SG, Barlow KF, McLay KE, Kaul R, Swarbreck D, Dunham A, Scott CE, Howe KL, Woodfine K, Spencer CC, Jones MC, Gillson C, Searle S, Zhou Y, Kokocinski F, McDonald L, Evans R, Phillips K, Atkinson A, Cooper R, Jones C, Hall RE, Andrews TD, Lloyd C, Ainscough R, Almeida JP, Ambrose KD, Anderson F, Andrew RW, Ashwell RI, Aubin K, Babbage AK, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Beasley H, Bethel G, Bird CP, Bray-Allen S, Brown JY, Brown AJ, Buckley D, Burton J, Bye J, Carder C, Chapman JC, Clark SY, Clarke G, Clee C, Cobley V, Collier RE, Corby N, Coville GJ, Davies J, Deadman R, Dunn M, Earthrowl M, Ellington AG, Errington H, Frankish A, Frankland J, French L, Garner P, Garnett J, Gay L, Ghori MR, Gibson R, Gilby LM, Gillett W, Glithero RJ, Grafham DV, Griffiths C, Griffiths-Jones S, Grocock R, Hammond S, Harrison ES, Hart E, Haugen E, Heath PD, Holmes S, Holt K, Howden PJ, Hunt AR, Hunt SE, Hunter G, Isherwood J, James R, Johnson C, Johnson D, Joy A, Kay M, Kershaw JK, Kibukawa M, Kimberley AM, King A, Knights AJ, Lad H, Laird G, Lawlor S, Leongamornlert DA, Lloyd DM, Loveland J, Lovell J, Lush MJ, Lyne R, Martin S, Mashreghi-Mohammadi M, Matthews L, Matthews NS, McLaren S, Milne S, Mistry S, Moore MJ, Nickerson T, O'Dell CN, Oliver K, Palmeiri A, Palmer SA, Parker A, Patel D, Pearce AV, Peck AI, Pelan S, Phelps K, Phillimore BJ, Plumb R, Rajan J, Raymond C, Rouse G, Saenphimmachak C, Sehra HK, Sheridan E, Shownkeen R, Sims S, Skuce CD, Smith M, Steward C, Subramanian S, Sycamore N, Tracey A, Tromans A, Van Helmond Z, Wall M, Wallis JM, White S, Whitehead SL, Wilkinson JE, Willey DL, Williams H, Wilming L, Wray PW, Wu Z, Coulson A, Vaudin M, Sulston JE, Durbin R, Hubbard T, Wooster R, Dunham I, Carter NP, McVean G, Ross MT, Harrow J, Olson MV, Beck S, Rogers J, Bentley DR, Banerjee R, Bryant SP, Burford DC, Burrill WD, Clegg SM, Dhami P, Dovey O, Faulkner LM, Gribble SM, Langford CF, Pandian RD, Porter KM, Prigmore E: The DNA sequence and biological annotation of human chromosome 1.  Nature. 2006 May 18;441(7091):315-21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16710414</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Tomida Y, Terasawa M, Kobayashi R, Hidaka H: Calcyclin and calvasculin exist in human platelets.  Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1992 Dec 30;189(3):1310-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1482346</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kriajevska M, Fischer-Larsen M, Moertz E, Vorm O, Tulchinsky E, Grigorian M, Ambartsumian N, Lukanidin E: Liprin beta 1, a member of the family of LAR transmembrane tyrosine phosphatase-interacting proteins, is a new target for the metastasis-associated protein S100A4 (Mts1). J Biol Chem. 2002 Feb 15;277(7):5229-35. Epub 2001 Dec 7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11836260</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Choudhary C, Kumar C, Gnad F, Nielsen ML, Rehman M, Walther TC, Olsen JV, Mann M: Lysine acetylation targets protein complexes and co-regulates major cellular functions. Science. 2009 Aug 14;325(5942):834-40. Epub 2009 Jul 16.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19608861</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Vallely KM, Rustandi RR, Ellis KC, Varlamova O, Bresnick AR, Weber DJ: Solution structure of human Mts1 (S100A4) as determined by NMR spectroscopy. Biochemistry. 2002 Oct 22;41(42):12670-80.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12379109</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Trifluoperazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14969</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Berman HM, Westbrook J, Feng Z, Gilliland G, Bhat TN, Weissig H, Shindyalov IN, Bourne PE: The Protein Data Bank.  Nucleic Acids Res. 2000 Jan 1;28(1):235-42.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>10592235</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Trifluoperazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14969</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Malashkevich VN, Dulyaninova NG, Ramagopal UA, Liriano MA, Varney KM, Knight D, Brenowitz M, Weber DJ, Almo SC, Bresnick AR: Phenothiazines inhibit S100A4 function by inducing protein oligomerization.  Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2010 May 11;107(19):8605-10. Epub 2010 Apr 26.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>20421509</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
