<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 18:59:21 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 18:59:21 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP01777</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>7130</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>CaM</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>CALM1</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in calcium ion binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Calmodulin mediates the control of a large number of enzymes and other proteins by Ca(2+). Among the enzymes to be stimulated by the calmodulin-Ca(2+) complex are a number of protein kinases and phosphatases. Together with CEP110 and centrin, is involved in a genetic pathway that regulates the centrosome cycle and progression through cytokinesis</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB04999</accession>
      <name>Loperamide</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB14668</accession>
      <name>Dibucaine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB14760</accession>
      <name>Nicardipine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB14761</accession>
      <name>Fluphenazine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB14891</accession>
      <name>Isoflurane</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB14969</accession>
      <name>Trifluoperazine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB14988</accession>
      <name>Perphenazine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15061</accession>
      <name>Phenoxybenzamine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15158</accession>
      <name>Felodipine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01389</accession>
      <name>Melatonin</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15202</accession>
      <name>Promethazine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15232</accession>
      <name>Pimozide</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15247</accession>
      <name>Nifedipine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15374</accession>
      <name>Bepridil</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15498</accession>
      <name>Aprindine</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB31456</accession>
      <name>2-Methylpropan-2-ol</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB15589</accession>
      <name>Flunarizine</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>cation binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>metal ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>calcium ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasm</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>cytoskeleton</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>spindle</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasm</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>cytoskeleton</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>spindle pole</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>14q24-q31</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;450 bp
ATGGCTGACCAGCTGACTGAGGAGCAGATTGCAGAGTTCAAGGAGGCCTTCTCCCTCTTT
GACAAGGATGGAGATGGCACTATCACCACCAAGGAGTTGGGGACAGTGATGAGATCCCTG
GGACAGAACCCCACTGAAGCAGAGCTGCAGGATATGATCAATGAGGTGGATGCAGATGGG
AACGGGACCATTGACTTCCCGGAGTTCCTGACCATGATGGCCAGAAAGATGAAGGACACA
GACAGTGAGGAGGAGATCCGAGAGGCGTTCCGTGTCTTTGACAAGGATGGGAATGGCTAC
ATCAGCGCCGCAGAGCTGCGTCACGTAATGACGAACCTGGGGGAGAAGCTGACCGATGAG
GAGGTGGATGAGATGATCAGGGAGGCTGACATCGATGGAGATGGCCAGGTCAATTATGAA
GAGTTTGTACAGATGATGACTGCAAAGTGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>149</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>16837.5</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>3.84</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>efhand</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00036</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Calmodulin
MADQLTEEQIAEFKEAFSLFDKDGDGTITTKELGTVMRSLGQNPTEAELQDMINEVDADG
NGTIDFPEFLTMMARKMKDTDSEEEIREAFRVFDKDGNGYISAAELRHVMTNLGEKLTDE
EVDEMIREADIDGDGQVNYEEFVQMMTAK</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>179888</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P62158</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>CALM_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1IQ5</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>J04046</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>CALM1</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>CALM1</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:1442</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wawrzynczak EJ, Perham RN: Isolation and nucleotide sequence of a cDNA encoding human calmodulin.  Biochem Int. 1984 Aug;9(2):177-85.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6385987</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>SenGupta B, Friedberg F, Detera-Wadleigh SD: Molecular analysis of human and rat calmodulin complementary DNA clones. Evidence for additional active genes in these species. J Biol Chem. 1987 Dec 5;262(34):16663-70.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2445749</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Fischer R, Koller M, Flura M, Mathews S, Strehler-Page MA, Krebs J, Penniston JT, Carafoli E, Strehler EE: Multiple divergent mRNAs code for a single human calmodulin.  J Biol Chem. 1988 Nov 15;263(32):17055-62.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3182832</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Koller M, Schnyder B, Strehler EE: Structural organization of the human CaMIII calmodulin gene.  Biochim Biophys Acta. 1990 Oct 23;1087(2):180-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2223880</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rhyner JA, Ottiger M, Wicki R, Greenwood TM, Strehler EE: Structure of the human CALM1 calmodulin gene and identification of two CALM1-related pseudogenes CALM1P1 and CALM1P2. Eur J Biochem. 1994 Oct 1;225(1):71-82.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7925473</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Toutenhoofd SL, Foletti D, Wicki R, Rhyner JA, Garcia F, Tolon R, Strehler EE: Characterization of the human CALM2 calmodulin gene and comparison of the transcriptional activity of CALM1, CALM2 and CALM3. Cell Calcium. 1998 May;23(5):323-38.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9681195</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Heilig R, Eckenberg R, Petit JL, Fonknechten N, Da Silva C, Cattolico L, Levy M, Barbe V, de Berardinis V, Ureta-Vidal A, Pelletier E, Vico V, Anthouard V, Rowen L, Madan A, Qin S, Sun H, Du H, Pepin K, Artiguenave F, Robert C, Cruaud C, Bruls T, Jaillon O, Friedlander L, Samson G, Brottier P, Cure S, Segurens B, Aniere F, Samain S, Crespeau H, Abbasi N, Aiach N, Boscus D, Dickhoff R, Dors M, Dubois I, Friedman C, Gouyvenoux M, James R, Madan A, Mairey-Estrada B, Mangenot S, Martins N, Menard M, Oztas S, Ratcliffe A, Shaffer T, Trask B, Vacherie B, Bellemere C, Belser C, Besnard-Gonnet M, Bartol-Mavel D, Boutard M, Briez-Silla S, Combette S, Dufosse-Laurent V, Ferron C, Lechaplais C, Louesse C, Muselet D, Magdelenat G, Pateau E, Petit E, Sirvain-Trukniewicz P, Trybou A, Vega-Czarny N, Bataille E, Bluet E, Bordelais I, Dubois M, Dumont C, Guerin T, Haffray S, Hammadi R, Muanga J, Pellouin V, Robert D, Wunderle E, Gauguet G, Roy A, Sainte-Marthe L, Verdier J, Verdier-Discala C, Hillier L, Fulton L, McPherson J, Matsuda F, Wilson R, Scarpelli C, Gyapay G, Wincker P, Saurin W, Quetier F, Waterston R, Hood L, Weissenbach J: The DNA sequence and analysis of human chromosome 14.  Nature. 2003 Feb 6;421(6923):601-7. Epub 2003 Jan 1.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12508121</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hillier LW, Graves TA, Fulton RS, Fulton LA, Pepin KH, Minx P, Wagner-McPherson C, Layman D, Wylie K, Sekhon M, Becker MC, Fewell GA, Delehaunty KD, Miner TL, Nash WE, Kremitzki C, Oddy L, Du H, Sun H, Bradshaw-Cordum H, Ali J, Carter J, Cordes M, Harris A, Isak A, van Brunt A, Nguyen C, Du F, Courtney L, Kalicki J, Ozersky P, Abbott S, Armstrong J, Belter EA, Caruso L, Cedroni M, Cotton M, Davidson T, Desai A, Elliott G, Erb T, Fronick C, Gaige T, Haakenson W, Haglund K, Holmes A, Harkins R, Kim K, Kruchowski SS, Strong CM, Grewal N, Goyea E, Hou S, Levy A, Martinka S, Mead K, McLellan MD, Meyer R, Randall-Maher J, Tomlinson C, Dauphin-Kohlberg S, Kozlowicz-Reilly A, Shah N, Swearengen-Shahid S, Snider J, Strong JT, Thompson J, Yoakum M, Leonard S, Pearman C, Trani L, Radionenko M, Waligorski JE, Wang C, Rock SM, Tin-Wollam AM, Maupin R, Latreille P, Wendl MC, Yang SP, Pohl C, Wallis JW, Spieth J, Bieri TA, Berkowicz N, Nelson JO, Osborne J, Ding L, Meyer R, Sabo A, Shotland Y, Sinha P, Wohldmann PE, Cook LL, Hickenbotham MT, Eldred J, Williams D, Jones TA, She X, Ciccarelli FD, Izaurralde E, Taylor J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Cox DR, Huang X, McPherson JD, Mardis ER, Clifton SW, Warren WC, Chinwalla AT, Eddy SR, Marra MA, Ovcharenko I, Furey TS, Miller W, Eichler EE, Bork P, Suyama M, Torrents D, Waterston RH, Wilson RK: Generation and annotation of the DNA sequences of human chromosomes 2 and 4. Nature. 2005 Apr 7;434(7034):724-31.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15815621</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Sasagawa T, Ericsson LH, Walsh KA, Schreiber WE, Fischer EH, Titani K: Complete amino acid sequence of human brain calmodulin.  Biochemistry. 1982 May 11;21(10):2565-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7093203</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Mayans O, van der Ven PF, Wilm M, Mues A, Young P, Furst DO, Wilmanns M, Gautel M: Structural basis for activation of the titin kinase domain during myofibrillogenesis. Nature. 1998 Oct 29;395(6705):863-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9804419</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kelly S, Yotis J, Macris M, Harley V: Recombinant expression, purification and characterisation of the HMG domain of human SRY. Protein Pept Lett. 2003 Jun;10(3):281-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12871148</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shen C, Ye Y, Robertson SE, Lau AW, Mak DO, Chou MM: Calcium/calmodulin regulates ubiquitination of the ubiquitin-specific protease TRE17/USP6. J Biol Chem. 2005 Oct 28;280(43):35967-73. Epub 2005 Aug 26.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16127172</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Sim H, Rimmer K, Kelly S, Ludbrook LM, Clayton AH, Harley VR: Defective calmodulin-mediated nuclear transport of the sex-determining region of the Y chromosome (SRY) in XY sex reversal. Mol Endocrinol. 2005 Jul;19(7):1884-92. Epub 2005 Mar 3.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15746192</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rush J, Moritz A, Lee KA, Guo A, Goss VL, Spek EJ, Zhang H, Zha XM, Polakiewicz RD, Comb MJ: Immunoaffinity profiling of tyrosine phosphorylation in cancer cells.  Nat Biotechnol. 2005 Jan;23(1):94-101. Epub 2004 Dec 12.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15592455</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Tsang WY, Spektor A, Luciano DJ, Indjeian VB, Chen Z, Salisbury JL, Sanchez I, Dynlacht BD: CP110 cooperates with two calcium-binding proteins to regulate cytokinesis and genome stability. Mol Biol Cell. 2006 Aug;17(8):3423-34. Epub 2006 Jun 7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16760425</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Spektor A, Tsang WY, Khoo D, Dynlacht BD: Cep97 and CP110 suppress a cilia assembly program.  Cell. 2007 Aug 24;130(4):678-90.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17719545</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rikova K, Guo A, Zeng Q, Possemato A, Yu J, Haack H, Nardone J, Lee K, Reeves C, Li Y, Hu Y, Tan Z, Stokes M, Sullivan L, Mitchell J, Wetzel R, Macneill J, Ren JM, Yuan J, Bakalarski CE, Villen J, Kornhauser JM, Smith B, Li D, Zhou X, Gygi SP, Gu TL, Polakiewicz RD, Rush J, Comb MJ: Global survey of phosphotyrosine signaling identifies oncogenic kinases in lung cancer. Cell. 2007 Dec 14;131(6):1190-203.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18083107</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Molina H, Horn DM, Tang N, Mathivanan S, Pandey A: Global proteomic profiling of phosphopeptides using electron transfer dissociation tandem mass spectrometry. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007 Feb 13;104(7):2199-204. Epub 2007 Feb 7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17287340</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wolf-Yadlin A, Hautaniemi S, Lauffenburger DA, White FM: Multiple reaction monitoring for robust quantitative proteomic analysis of cellular signaling networks. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007 Apr 3;104(14):5860-5. Epub 2007 Mar 26.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17389395</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Dephoure N, Zhou C, Villen J, Beausoleil SA, Bakalarski CE, Elledge SJ, Gygi SP: A quantitative atlas of mitotic phosphorylation.  Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2008 Aug 5;105(31):10762-7. Epub 2008 Jul 31.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18669648</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gauci S, Helbig AO, Slijper M, Krijgsveld J, Heck AJ, Mohammed S: Lys-N and trypsin cover complementary parts of the phosphoproteome in a refined SCX-based approach. Anal Chem. 2009 Jun 1;81(11):4493-501.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19413330</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Heibeck TH, Ding SJ, Opresko LK, Zhao R, Schepmoes AA, Yang F, Tolmachev AV, Monroe ME, Camp DG 2nd, Smith RD, Wiley HS, Qian WJ: An extensive survey of tyrosine phosphorylation revealing new sites in human mammary epithelial cells. J Proteome Res. 2009 Aug;8(8):3852-61.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19534553</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Mayya V, Lundgren DH, Hwang SI, Rezaul K, Wu L, Eng JK, Rodionov V, Han DK: Quantitative phosphoproteomic analysis of T cell receptor signaling reveals system-wide modulation of protein-protein interactions. Sci Signal. 2009 Aug 18;2(84):ra46.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19690332</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Choudhary C, Kumar C, Gnad F, Nielsen ML, Rehman M, Walther TC, Olsen JV, Mann M: Lysine acetylation targets protein complexes and co-regulates major cellular functions. Science. 2009 Aug 14;325(5942):834-40. Epub 2009 Jul 16.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19608861</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Siedlecka M, Goch G, Ejchart A, Sticht H, Bierzynski A: Alpha-helix nucleation by a calcium-binding peptide loop.  Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1999 Feb 2;96(3):903-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9927666</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Chou JJ, Li S, Klee CB, Bax A: Solution structure of Ca(2+)-calmodulin reveals flexible hand-like properties of its domains. Nat Struct Biol. 2001 Nov;8(11):990-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11685248</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Chattopadhyaya R, Meador WE, Means AR, Quiocho FA: Calmodulin structure refined at 1.7 A resolution.  J Mol Biol. 1992 Dec 20;228(4):1177-92.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1474585</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Cook WJ, Walter LJ, Walter MR: Drug binding by calmodulin: crystal structure of a calmodulin-trifluoperazine complex. Biochemistry. 1994 Dec 27;33(51):15259-65.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7803388</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Drum CL, Yan SZ, Bard J, Shen YQ, Lu D, Soelaiman S, Grabarek Z, Bohm A, Tang WJ: Structural basis for the activation of anthrax adenylyl cyclase exotoxin by calmodulin. Nature. 2002 Jan 24;415(6870):396-402.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11807546</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shen Y, Lee YS, Soelaiman S, Bergson P, Lu D, Chen A, Beckingham K, Grabarek Z, Mrksich M, Tang WJ: Physiological calcium concentrations regulate calmodulin binding and catalysis of adenylyl cyclase exotoxins. EMBO J. 2002 Dec 16;21(24):6721-32.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12485993</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Yamauchi E, Nakatsu T, Matsubara M, Kato H, Taniguchi H: Crystal structure of a MARCKS peptide containing the calmodulin-binding domain in complex with Ca2+-calmodulin. Nat Struct Biol. 2003 Mar;10(3):226-31.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12577052</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Van Petegem F, Chatelain FC, Minor DL Jr: Insights into voltage-gated calcium channel regulation from the structure of the CaV1.2 IQ domain-Ca2+/calmodulin complex. Nat Struct Mol Biol. 2005 Dec;12(12):1108-15. Epub 2005 Nov 20.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16299511</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shen Y, Zhukovskaya NL, Guo Q, Florian J, Tang WJ: Calcium-independent calmodulin binding and two-metal-ion catalytic mechanism of anthrax edema factor. EMBO J. 2005 Mar 9;24(5):929-41. Epub 2005 Feb 17.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15719022</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Calcium</name>
        <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Sosa V, Carbo R, Guarner V: Participation of glucose transporters on atrial natriuretic peptide-induced glucose uptake by adult and neonatal cardiomyocytes under oxygenation and hypoxia. Eur J Pharmacol. 2007 Jul 30;568(1-3):83-8. Epub 2007 Apr 30.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17537429</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Calcium</name>
        <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Zhou Z, Yin J, Dou Z, Tang J, Zhang C, Cao Y: The calponin homology domain of Vav1 associates with calmodulin and is prerequisite to T cell antigen receptor-induced calcium release in Jurkat T lymphocytes. J Biol Chem. 2007 Aug 10;282(32):23737-44. Epub 2007 Jun 5.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17550897</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Calcium</name>
        <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Schallreuter KU, Gibbons NC, Zothner C, Abou Elloof MM, Wood JM: Hydrogen peroxide-mediated oxidative stress disrupts calcium binding on calmodulin: more evidence for oxidative stress in vitiligo. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 2007 Aug 17;360(1):70-5. Epub 2007 Jun 11.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17592724</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Calcium</name>
        <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Caride AJ, Filoteo AG, Penniston JT, Strehler EE: The plasma membrane Ca2+ pump isoform 4a differs from isoform 4b in the mechanism of calmodulin binding and activation kinetics: implications for Ca2+ signaling. J Biol Chem. 2007 Aug 31;282(35):25640-8. Epub 2007 Jun 26.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17595168</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Calcium</name>
        <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Lo LW, Chen YC, Chen YJ, Wongcharoen W, Lin CI, Chen SA: Calmodulin kinase II inhibition prevents arrhythmic activity induced by alpha and beta adrenergic agonists in rabbit pulmonary veins. Eur J Pharmacol. 2007 Oct 1;571(2-3):197-208. Epub 2007 Jun 13.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17612522</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Dibucaine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14668</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Muto Y, Kudo S, Nozawa Y: Effects of local anesthetics on calmodulin-dependent guanylate cyclase in the plasma membrane of Tetrahymena pyriformis. Biochem Pharmacol. 1983 Dec 1;32(23):3559-63.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>6140014</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Dibucaine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14668</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Volpi M, Sha'afi RI, Epstein PM, Andrenyak DM, Feinstein MB: Local anesthetics, mepacrine, and propranolol are antagonists of calmodulin.  Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1981 Feb;78(2):795-9.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>6262771</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Dibucaine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14668</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Liu SH, Fu WM, Lin-Shiau SY: Studies on the inhibition by chlorpromazine of myotonia induced by ion channel modulators in mouse skeletal muscle. Eur J Pharmacol. 1993 Jan 26;231(1):23-30.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>7680317</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Dibucaine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14668</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Sambandam T, Gunasekaran M: Purification and properties of calmodulin from Phymatotrichum omnivorum.  Microbios. 1993;73(294):61-74.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>8382768</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Nicardipine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14760</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Thayer SA, Fairhurst AS: The interaction of dihydropyridine calcium channel blockers with calmodulin and calmodulin inhibitors. Mol Pharmacol. 1983 Jul;24(1):6-9.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>6865927</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Fluphenazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14761</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Mongin AA, Cai Z, Kimelberg HK: Volume-dependent taurine release from cultured astrocytes requires permissive [Ca(2+)](i) and calmodulin. Am J Physiol. 1999 Oct;277(4 Pt 1):C823-32.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>10516112</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Fluphenazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14761</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Kawai M, Nakashima A, Ueno M, Ushimaru T, Aiba K, Doi H, Uritani M: Fission yeast tor1 functions in response to various stresses including nitrogen starvation, high osmolarity, and high temperature. Curr Genet. 2001 May;39(3):166-74.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>11409178</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Fluphenazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14761</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Edlind T, Smith L, Henry K, Katiyar S, Nickels J: Antifungal activity in Saccharomyces cerevisiae is modulated by calcium signalling. Mol Microbiol. 2002 Oct;46(1):257-68.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>12366848</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Fluphenazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14761</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Nakabayashi H, Komada H, Yoshida T, Takanari H, Izutsu K: Lymphocyte calmodulin and its participation in the stimulation of T lymphocytes by mitogenic lectins. Biol Cell. 1992;75(1):55-9.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>1515867</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Fluphenazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14761</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Kauss H: Sensing of volume changes by poterioochromonas involves a ca-regulated system which controls activation of isofloridoside-phosphate synthase. Plant Physiol. 1981 Aug;68(2):420-4.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>16661928</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Isoflurane</name>
        <accession>HMDB14891</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Fan RS, Jacamo RO, Jiang X, Sinnett-Smith J, Rozengurt E: G protein-coupled receptor activation rapidly stimulates focal adhesion kinase phosphorylation at Ser-843. Mediation by Ca2+, calmodulin, and Ca2+/calmodulin-dependent kinase II. J Biol Chem. 2005 Jun 24;280(25):24212-20. Epub 2005 Apr 21.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>15845548</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Isoflurane</name>
        <accession>HMDB14891</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Bickler PE, Zhan X, Fahlman CS: Isoflurane preconditions hippocampal neurons against oxygen-glucose deprivation: role of intracellular Ca2+ and mitogen-activated protein kinase signaling. Anesthesiology. 2005 Sep;103(3):532-9.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>16129978</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Isoflurane</name>
        <accession>HMDB14891</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Sazonova OV, Blishchenko EY, Tolmazova AG, Khachin DP, Leontiev KV, Karelin AA, Ivanov VT: Stimulation of fibroblast proliferation by neokyotorphin requires Ca influx and activation of PKA, CaMK II and MAPK/ERK. FEBS J. 2007 Jan;274(2):474-84.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17229152</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Trifluoperazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14969</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Berman HM, Westbrook J, Feng Z, Gilliland G, Bhat TN, Weissig H, Shindyalov IN, Bourne PE: The Protein Data Bank.  Nucleic Acids Res. 2000 Jan 1;28(1):235-42.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>10592235</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Trifluoperazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14969</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Torres-Piedra M, Figueroa M, Hernandez-Abreu O, Ibarra-Barajas M, Navarrete-Vazquez G, Estrada-Soto S: Vasorelaxant effect of flavonoids through calmodulin inhibition: Ex vivo, in vitro, and in silico approaches. Bioorg Med Chem. 2011 Jan 1;19(1):542-6. Epub 2010 Nov 4.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>21129983</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Perphenazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14988</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Mongin AA, Cai Z, Kimelberg HK: Volume-dependent taurine release from cultured astrocytes requires permissive [Ca(2+)](i) and calmodulin. Am J Physiol. 1999 Oct;277(4 Pt 1):C823-32.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>10516112</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Perphenazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14988</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Kawai M, Nakashima A, Ueno M, Ushimaru T, Aiba K, Doi H, Uritani M: Fission yeast tor1 functions in response to various stresses including nitrogen starvation, high osmolarity, and high temperature. Curr Genet. 2001 May;39(3):166-74.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>11409178</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Perphenazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14988</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Edlind T, Smith L, Henry K, Katiyar S, Nickels J: Antifungal activity in Saccharomyces cerevisiae is modulated by calcium signalling. Mol Microbiol. 2002 Oct;46(1):257-68.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>12366848</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Perphenazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB14988</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Natochin YuV, Shakhmatova EI, Bakos P: Water and sodium transport: effects of calcium channel blocker and calmodulin antagonists on the apical and basolateral membranes of amphibian epithelia. Gen Physiol Biophys. 1987 Feb;6(1):35-44.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>2885243</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Phenoxybenzamine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15061</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Cimino M, Weiss B: Characteristics of the binding of phenoxybenzamine to calmodulin.  Biochem Pharmacol. 1988 Jul 15;37(14):2739-45.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>3134891</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Phenoxybenzamine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15061</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Suko J, Wyskovsky W, Pidlich J, Hauptner R, Plank B, Hellmann G: Calcium release from calmodulin and its C-terminal or N-terminal halves in the presence of the calmodulin antagonists phenoxybenzamine and melittin measured by stopped-flow fluorescence with Quin 2 and intrinsic tyrosine. Inhibition of calmodulin-dependent protein kinase of cardiac sarcoplasmic reticulum. Eur J Biochem. 1986 Sep 15;159(3):425-34.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>3758070</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Phenoxybenzamine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15061</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Lukas TJ, Marshak DR, Watterson DM: Drug-protein interactions: isolation and characterization of covalent adducts of phenoxybenzamine and calmodulin. Biochemistry. 1985 Jan 1;24(1):151-7.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>3994963</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Phenoxybenzamine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15061</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Earl CQ, Prozialeck WC, Weiss B: Interaction of alpha adrenergic antagonists with calmodulin.  Life Sci. 1984 Jul 30;35(5):525-34.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>6146911</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Phenoxybenzamine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15061</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Kuromi H, Yoshihara M, Kidokoro Y: An inhibitory role of calcineurin in endocytosis of synaptic vesicles at nerve terminals of Drosophila larvae. Neurosci Res. 1997 Feb;27(2):101-13.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>9100252</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Felodipine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15158</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Bostrom SL, Westerlund C, Rochester S, Vogel HJ: Binding of a dihydropyridine felodipine-analogue to calmodulin and related calcium-binding proteins. Biochem Pharmacol. 1988 Oct 1;37(19):3723-8.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>3178884</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Felodipine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15158</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Johnson JD, Andrews CT, Khabbaza EJ, Mills JS: The interaction of felodipine with calcium-binding proteins.  J Cardiovasc Pharmacol. 1987;10 Suppl 1:S53-9.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>2442519</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Felodipine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15158</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Lamers JM, Cysouw KJ, Verdouw PD: Slow calcium channel blockers and calmodulin. Effect of felodipine, nifedipine, prenylamine and bepridil on cardiac sarcolemmal calcium pumping ATPase. Biochem Pharmacol. 1985 Nov 1;34(21):3837-43.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>2933041</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Felodipine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15158</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Lamers JM, Verdouw PD, Mas-Oliva J: The effects of felodipine and bepridil on calcium-stimulated calmodulin binding and calcium pumping ATPase of cardiac sarcolemma before and after removal of endogenous calmodulin. Mol Cell Biochem. 1987 Dec;78(2):169-76.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>2964559</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Felodipine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15158</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Mills JS, Bailey BL, Johnson JD: Cooperativity among calmodulin's drug binding sites.  Biochemistry. 1985 Aug 27;24(18):4897-902.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>4074665</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Felodipine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15158</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Walsh MP, Sutherland C, Scott-Woo GC: Effects of felodipine (a dihydropyridine calcium channel blocker) and analogues on calmodulin-dependent enzymes. Biochem Pharmacol. 1988 Apr 15;37(8):1569-80.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>2833901</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Melatonin</name>
        <accession>HMDB01389</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>del Rio B, Garcia Pedrero JM, Martinez-Campa C, Zuazua P, Lazo PS, Ramos S: Melatonin, an endogenous-specific inhibitor of estrogen receptor alpha via calmodulin. J Biol Chem. 2004 Sep 10;279(37):38294-302. Epub 2004 Jun 30.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>15229223</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Melatonin</name>
        <accession>HMDB01389</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Radogna F, Paternoster L, De Nicola M, Cerella C, Ammendola S, Bedini A, Tarzia G, Aquilano K, Ciriolo M, Ghibelli L: Rapid and transient stimulation of intracellular reactive oxygen species by melatonin in normal and tumor leukocytes. Toxicol Appl Pharmacol. 2009 Aug 15;239(1):37-45. Epub 2009 May 19.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>19463840</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Promethazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15202</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Cohen ME, Sharp GW, Donowitz M: Suggestion of a role for calmodulin and phosphorylation in regulation of rabbit ileal electrolyte transport: effects of promethazine. Am J Physiol. 1986 Nov;251(5 Pt 1):G710-7.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>3022601</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Promethazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15202</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Scott JA, Khaw BA, Fallon JT, Locke E, Rabito CA, Peto CA, Homcy CJ: The effect of phenothiazines upon maintenance of membrane integrity in the cultured myocardial cell. J Mol Cell Cardiol. 1986 Dec;18(12):1243-54.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>3820316</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Promethazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15202</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Lohr KM, Feix JB, Kurth C: Chlorpromazine inhibits neutrophil chemotaxis beyond the chemotactic receptor-ligand interaction. J Infect Dis. 1984 Nov;150(5):643-52.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>6092486</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Promethazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15202</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>DiPaola M, Keith CH, Feldman D, Tycko B, Maxfield FR: Loss of alpha 2-macroglobulin and epidermal growth factor surface binding induced by phenothiazines and naphthalene sulfonamides. J Cell Physiol. 1984 Feb;118(2):193-202.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>6319437</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Promethazine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15202</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Luchowski EM, Yousif F, Triggle DJ, Maurer SC, Sarmiento JG, Janis RA: Effects of metal cations and calmodulin antagonists on [3H] nitrendipine binding in smooth and cardiac muscle. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 1984 Sep;230(3):607-13.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>6433001</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pimozide</name>
        <accession>HMDB15232</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Papadopoulos V, Brown AS, Hall PF: Calcium-calmodulin-dependent phosphorylation of cytoskeletal proteins from adrenal cells. Mol Cell Endocrinol. 1990 Dec 3;74(2):109-23.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>1965307</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pimozide</name>
        <accession>HMDB15232</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Wang XB, Sato N, Greer MA, Greer SE, McAdams S: Role of extracellular calcium and calmodulin in prolactin secretion induced by hyposmolarity, thyrotropin-releasing hormone, and high K+ in GH4C1 cells. Acta Endocrinol (Copenh). 1990 Aug;123(2):218-24.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>2120879</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pimozide</name>
        <accession>HMDB15232</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Strobl JS, Kirkwood KL, Lantz TK, Lewine MA, Peterson VA, Worley JF 3rd: Inhibition of human breast cancer cell proliferation in tissue culture by the neuroleptic agents pimozide and thioridazine. Cancer Res. 1990 Sep 1;50(17):5399-405.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>2386945</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pimozide</name>
        <accession>HMDB15232</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Cimino M, Weiss B: Characteristics of the binding of phenoxybenzamine to calmodulin.  Biochem Pharmacol. 1988 Jul 15;37(14):2739-45.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>3134891</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Pimozide</name>
        <accession>HMDB15232</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Mody I, Baimbridge KG, Miller JJ: Blockade of tetanic- and calcium-induced long-term potentiation in the hippocampal slice preparation by neuroleptics. Neuropharmacology. 1984 Jun;23(6):625-31.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>6146939</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Nifedipine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15247</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Lamers JM, Cysouw KJ, Verdouw PD: Slow calcium channel blockers and calmodulin. Effect of felodipine, nifedipine, prenylamine and bepridil on cardiac sarcolemmal calcium pumping ATPase. Biochem Pharmacol. 1985 Nov 1;34(21):3837-43.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>2933041</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Bepridil</name>
        <accession>HMDB15374</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Lamers JM, Cysouw KJ, Verdouw PD: Slow calcium channel blockers and calmodulin. Effect of felodipine, nifedipine, prenylamine and bepridil on cardiac sarcolemmal calcium pumping ATPase. Biochem Pharmacol. 1985 Nov 1;34(21):3837-43.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>2933041</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Bepridil</name>
        <accession>HMDB15374</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Lamers JM, Verdouw PD, Mas-Oliva J: The effects of felodipine and bepridil on calcium-stimulated calmodulin binding and calcium pumping ATPase of cardiac sarcolemma before and after removal of endogenous calmodulin. Mol Cell Biochem. 1987 Dec;78(2):169-76.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>2964559</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Aprindine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15498</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Levine SN, Hollier B: Aprindine inhibits calmodulin-stimulated phosphodiesterase and Ca-ATPase activities. J Cardiovasc Pharmacol. 1983 Jan-Feb;5(1):151-6.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>6186851</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>2-Methylpropan-2-ol</name>
        <accession>HMDB31456</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Overington JP, Al-Lazikani B, Hopkins AL: How many drug targets are there?  Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2006 Dec;5(12):993-6.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17139284</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>2-Methylpropan-2-ol</name>
        <accession>HMDB31456</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Imming P, Sinning C, Meyer A: Drugs, their targets and the nature and number of drug targets.  Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2006 Oct;5(10):821-34.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17016423</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Flunarizine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15589</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Overington JP, Al-Lazikani B, Hopkins AL: How many drug targets are there?  Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2006 Dec;5(12):993-6.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17139284</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
    <metabolite_reference>
      <metabolite>
        <name>Flunarizine</name>
        <accession>HMDB15589</accession>
      </metabolite>
      <reference>
        <reference_text>Imming P, Sinning C, Meyer A: Drugs, their targets and the nature and number of drug targets.  Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2006 Oct;5(10):821-34.</reference_text>
        <pubmed_id>17016423</pubmed_id>
      </reference>
    </metabolite_reference>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
