<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 19:01:01 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 19:01:01 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP01959</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>7384</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Rho cDNA clone 12</synonym>
    <synonym>h12</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>RHOA</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in GTP binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Regulates a signal transduction pathway linking plasma membrane receptors to the assembly of focal adhesions and actin stress fibers. Serves as a target for the yopT cysteine peptidase from Yersinia pestis, vector of the plague, and Yersinia pseudotuberculosis, which causes gastrointestinal disorders. May be an activator of PLCE1. Activated by ARHGEF2, which promotes the exchange of GDP for GTP</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01273</accession>
      <name>Guanosine triphosphate</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00547</accession>
      <name>Magnesium</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB05007</accession>
      <name>Simvastatin</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB05006</accession>
      <name>Atorvastatin</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>nucleotide binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>purine nucleotide binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>guanyl nucleotide binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>guanyl ribonucleotide binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>gtp binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>biological regulation</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>regulation of biological process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>regulation of cellular process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>signal transduction</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>intracellular signal transduction</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>small gtpase mediated signal transduction</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>cell part</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>intracellular</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Cell membrane</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Lipid-anchor</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasmic side</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasm</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>cytoskeleton</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:3</chromosome_location>
    <locus>3p21.3</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;582 bp
ATGGCTGCCATCCGGAAGAAACTGGTGATTGTTGGTGATGGAGCCTGTGGAAAGACATGC
TTGCTCATAGTCTTCAGCAAGGACCAGTTCCCAGAGGTGTATGTGCCCACAGTGTTTGAG
AACTATGTGGCAGATATCGAGGTGGATGGAAAGCAGGTAGAGTTGGCTTTGTGGGACACA
GCTGGGCAGGAAGATTATGATCGCCTGAGGCCCCTCTCCTACCCAGATACCGATGTTATA
CTGATGTGTTTTTCCATCGACAGCCCTGATAGTTTAGAAAACATCCCAGAAAAGTGGACC
CCAGAAGTCAAGCATTTCTGTCCCAACGTGCCCATCATCCTGGTTGGGAATAAGAAGGAT
CTTCGGAATGATGAGCACACAAGGCGGGAGCTAGCCAAGATGAAGCAGGAGCCGGTGAAA
CCTGAAGAAGGCAGAGATATGGCAAACAGGATTGGCGCTTTTGGGTACATGGAGTGTTCA
GCAAAGACCAAAGATGGAGTGAGAGAGGTTTTTGAAATGGCTACGAGAGCTGCTCTGCAA
GCTAGACGTGGGAAGAAAAAATCTGGTTGCCTTGTCTTGTGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>193</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>21767.9</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>5.89</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Ras</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00071</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Transforming protein RhoA
MAAIRKKLVIVGDGACGKTCLLIVFSKDQFPEVYVPTVFENYVADIEVDGKQVELALWDT
AGQEDYDRLRPLSYPDTDVILMCFSIDSPDSLENIPEKWTPEVKHFCPNVPIILVGNKKD
LRNDEHTRRELAKMKQEPVKPEEGRDMANRIGAFGYMECSAKTKDGVREVFEMATRAALQ
ARRGKKKSGCLVL</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>36030</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P61586</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>RHOA_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1X86</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>X05026</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>RHOA</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>RHOA</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:667</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Yeramian P, Chardin P, Madaule P, Tavitian A: Nucleotide sequence of human rho cDNA clone 12.  Nucleic Acids Res. 1987 Feb 25;15(4):1869.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3822842</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Fagan KP, Oliveira L, Pittler SJ: Sequence of rho small GTP-binding protein cDNAs from human retina and identification of novel 5' end cloning artifacts. Exp Eye Res. 1994 Aug;59(2):235-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7835413</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bechtel S, Rosenfelder H, Duda A, Schmidt CP, Ernst U, Wellenreuther R, Mehrle A, Schuster C, Bahr A, Blocker H, Heubner D, Hoerlein A, Michel G, Wedler H, Kohrer K, Ottenwalder B, Poustka A, Wiemann S, Schupp I: The full-ORF clone resource of the German cDNA Consortium.  BMC Genomics. 2007 Oct 31;8:399.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>17974005</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Moscow JA, He R, Gudas JM, Cowan KH: Utilization of multiple polyadenylation signals in the human RHOA protooncogene. Gene. 1994 Jul 8;144(2):229-36.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8039707</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Nemoto Y, Namba T, Teru-uchi T, Ushikubi F, Morii N, Narumiya S: A rho gene product in human blood platelets. I. Identification of the platelet substrate for botulinum C3 ADP-ribosyltransferase as rhoA protein. J Biol Chem. 1992 Oct 15;267(29):20916-20.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1328215</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Moscow JA, Morrow CS, He R, Mullenbach GT, Cowan KH: Structure and function of the 5'-flanking sequence of the human cytosolic selenium-dependent glutathione peroxidase gene (hgpx1). J Biol Chem. 1992 Mar 25;267(9):5949-58.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1556108</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ishizaki T, Maekawa M, Fujisawa K, Okawa K, Iwamatsu A, Fujita A, Watanabe N, Saito Y, Kakizuka A, Morii N, Narumiya S: The small GTP-binding protein Rho binds to and activates a 160 kDa Ser/Thr protein kinase homologous to myotonic dystrophy kinase. EMBO J. 1996 Apr 15;15(8):1885-93.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8617235</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Matsui T, Amano M, Yamamoto T, Chihara K, Nakafuku M, Ito M, Nakano T, Okawa K, Iwamatsu A, Kaibuchi K: Rho-associated kinase, a novel serine/threonine kinase, as a putative target for small GTP binding protein Rho. EMBO J. 1996 May 1;15(9):2208-16.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8641286</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ren Y, Li R, Zheng Y, Busch H: Cloning and characterization of GEF-H1, a microtubule-associated guanine nucleotide exchange factor for Rac and Rho GTPases. J Biol Chem. 1998 Dec 25;273(52):34954-60.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9857026</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Houssa B, de Widt J, Kranenburg O, Moolenaar WH, van Blitterswijk WJ: Diacylglycerol kinase theta binds to and is negatively regulated by active RhoA. J Biol Chem. 1999 Mar 12;274(11):6820-2.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10066731</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Pastey MK, Crowe JE Jr, Graham BS: RhoA interacts with the fusion glycoprotein of respiratory syncytial virus and facilitates virus-induced syncytium formation. J Virol. 1999 Sep;73(9):7262-70.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10438814</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Reynaud C, Fabre S, Jalinot P: The PDZ protein TIP-1 interacts with the Rho effector rhotekin and is involved in Rho signaling to the serum response element. J Biol Chem. 2000 Oct 27;275(43):33962-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10940294</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Klussmann E, Edemir B, Pepperle B, Tamma G, Henn V, Klauschenz E, Hundsrucker C, Maric K, Rosenthal W: Ht31: the first protein kinase A anchoring protein to integrate protein kinase A and Rho signaling. FEBS Lett. 2001 Nov 2;507(3):264-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11696353</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Arthur WT, Ellerbroek SM, Der CJ, Burridge K, Wennerberg K: XPLN, a guanine nucleotide exchange factor for RhoA and RhoB, but not RhoC. J Biol Chem. 2002 Nov 8;277(45):42964-72. Epub 2002 Sep 6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12221096</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shao F, Merritt PM, Bao Z, Innes RW, Dixon JE: A Yersinia effector and a Pseudomonas avirulence protein define a family of cysteine proteases functioning in bacterial pathogenesis. Cell. 2002 May 31;109(5):575-88.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12062101</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wing MR, Snyder JT, Sondek J, Harden TK: Direct activation of phospholipase C-epsilon by Rho.  J Biol Chem. 2003 Oct 17;278(42):41253-8. Epub 2003 Aug 4.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12900402</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shao F, Vacratsis PO, Bao Z, Bowers KE, Fierke CA, Dixon JE: Biochemical characterization of the Yersinia YopT protease: cleavage site and recognition elements in Rho GTPases. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2003 Feb 4;100(3):904-9. Epub 2003 Jan 21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12538863</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Heibeck TH, Ding SJ, Opresko LK, Zhao R, Schepmoes AA, Yang F, Tolmachev AV, Monroe ME, Camp DG 2nd, Smith RD, Wiley HS, Qian WJ: An extensive survey of tyrosine phosphorylation revealing new sites in human mammary epithelial cells. J Proteome Res. 2009 Aug;8(8):3852-61.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19534553</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Worby CA, Mattoo S, Kruger RP, Corbeil LB, Koller A, Mendez JC, Zekarias B, Lazar C, Dixon JE: The fic domain: regulation of cell signaling by adenylylation.  Mol Cell. 2009 Apr 10;34(1):93-103.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19362538</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Chen Y, Yang Z, Meng M, Zhao Y, Dong N, Yan H, Liu L, Ding M, Peng HB, Shao F: Cullin mediates degradation of RhoA through evolutionarily conserved BTB adaptors to control actin cytoskeleton structure and cell movement. Mol Cell. 2009 Sep 24;35(6):841-55.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19782033</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Yarbrough ML, Li Y, Kinch LN, Grishin NV, Ball HL, Orth K: AMPylation of Rho GTPases by Vibrio VopS disrupts effector binding and downstream signaling. Science. 2009 Jan 9;323(5911):269-72. Epub 2008 Nov 27.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19039103</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wei Y, Zhang Y, Derewenda U, Liu X, Minor W, Nakamoto RK, Somlyo AV, Somlyo AP, Derewenda ZS: Crystal structure of RhoA-GDP and its functional implications.  Nat Struct Biol. 1997 Sep;4(9):699-703.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9302995</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ihara K, Muraguchi S, Kato M, Shimizu T, Shirakawa M, Kuroda S, Kaibuchi K, Hakoshima T: Crystal structure of human RhoA in a dominantly active form complexed with a GTP analogue. J Biol Chem. 1998 Apr 17;273(16):9656-66.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9545299</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Maesaki R, Shimizu T, Ihara K, Kuroda S, Kaibuchi K, Hakoshima T: Biochemical and crystallographic characterization of a Rho effector domain of the protein serine/threonine kinase N in a complex with RhoA. J Struct Biol. 1999 Jun 15;126(2):166-70.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10388627</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shimizu T, Ihara K, Maesaki R, Kuroda S, Kaibuchi K, Hakoshima T: An open conformation of switch I revealed by the crystal structure of a Mg2+-free form of RHOA complexed with GDP. Implications for the GDP/GTP exchange mechanism. J Biol Chem. 2000 Jun 16;275(24):18311-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10748207</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Graham DL, Lowe PN, Grime GW, Marsh M, Rittinger K, Smerdon SJ, Gamblin SJ, Eccleston JF: MgF(3)(-) as a transition state analog of phosphoryl transfer.  Chem Biol. 2002 Mar;9(3):375-81.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11927263</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Snyder JT, Worthylake DK, Rossman KL, Betts L, Pruitt WM, Siderovski DP, Der CJ, Sondek J: Structural basis for the selective activation of Rho GTPases by Dbl exchange factors. Nat Struct Biol. 2002 Jun;9(6):468-75.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12006984</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Longenecker K, Read P, Lin SK, Somlyo AP, Nakamoto RK, Derewenda ZS: Structure of a constitutively activated RhoA mutant (Q63L) at 1.55 A resolution. Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr. 2003 May;59(Pt 5):876-80. Epub 2003       Apr 25.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12777804</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
