<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 19:05:49 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 19:05:49 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP02508</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>8003</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Hepc20</synonym>
    <synonym>Hepc25</synonym>
    <synonym>Hepcidin-20</synonym>
    <synonym>Hepcidin-25</synonym>
    <synonym>LEAP-1</synonym>
    <synonym>Liver-expressed antimicrobial peptide 1</synonym>
    <synonym>PLTR</synonym>
    <synonym>Putative liver tumor regressor</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>HAMP</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in cellular iron ion homeostasis</general_function>
  <specific_function>Has strong antimicrobial activity against E.coli ML35P N.cinerea and weaker against S.epidermidis, S.aureus and group b streptococcus bacteria. Active against the fungus C.albicans. No activity against P.aeruginosa</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00692</accession>
      <name>Fe2+</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>biological regulation</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>regulation of biological quality</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>homeostatic process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>chemical homeostasis</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>ion homeostasis</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>cellular ion homeostasis</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>cellular cation homeostasis</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>cellular di-, tri-valent inorganic cation homeostasis</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>cellular iron ion homeostasis</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>extracellular region</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Secreted</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>19q13.1</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;255 bp
ATGGCACTGAGCTCCCAGATCTGGGCCGCTTGCCTCCTGCTCCTCCTCCTCCTCGCCAGC
CTGACCAGTGGCTCTGTTTTCCCACAACAGACGGGACAACTTGCAGAGCTGCAACCCCAG
GACAGAGCTGGAGCCAGGGCCAGCTGGATGCCCATGTTCCAGAGGCGAAGGAGGCGAGAC
ACCCACTTCCCCATCTGCATTTTCTGCTGCGGCTGCTGTCATCGATCAAAGTGTGGGATG
TGCTGCAAGACGTAG</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>84</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>9408.1</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>8.88</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Hepcidin</name>
        <pfam_id>PF06446</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>1-24</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Hepcidin
MALSSQIWAACLLLLLLLASLTSGSVFPQQTGQLAELQPQDRAGARASWMPMFQRRRRRD
THFPICIFCCGCCHRSKCGMCCKT</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>10863973</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P81172</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>HEPC_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1M4F</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>NM_021175.2</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>HAMP</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>HAMP</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:15598</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Park CH, Valore EV, Waring AJ, Ganz T: Hepcidin, a urinary antimicrobial peptide synthesized in the liver.  J Biol Chem. 2001 Mar 16;276(11):7806-10. Epub 2000 Dec 11.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11113131</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Krause A, Neitz S, Magert HJ, Schulz A, Forssmann WG, Schulz-Knappe P, Adermann K: LEAP-1, a novel highly disulfide-bonded human peptide, exhibits antimicrobial activity. FEBS Lett. 2000 Sep 1;480(2-3):147-50.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11034317</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Clark HF, Gurney AL, Abaya E, Baker K, Baldwin D, Brush J, Chen J, Chow B, Chui C, Crowley C, Currell B, Deuel B, Dowd P, Eaton D, Foster J, Grimaldi C, Gu Q, Hass PE, Heldens S, Huang A, Kim HS, Klimowski L, Jin Y, Johnson S, Lee J, Lewis L, Liao D, Mark M, Robbie E, Sanchez C, Schoenfeld J, Seshagiri S, Simmons L, Singh J, Smith V, Stinson J, Vagts A, Vandlen R, Watanabe C, Wieand D, Woods K, Xie MH, Yansura D, Yi S, Yu G, Yuan J, Zhang M, Zhang Z, Goddard A, Wood WI, Godowski P, Gray A: The secreted protein discovery initiative (SPDI), a large-scale effort to identify novel human secreted and transmembrane proteins: a bioinformatics assessment. Genome Res. 2003 Oct;13(10):2265-70. Epub 2003 Sep 15.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12975309</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Grimwood J, Gordon LA, Olsen A, Terry A, Schmutz J, Lamerdin J, Hellsten U, Goodstein D, Couronne O, Tran-Gyamfi M, Aerts A, Altherr M, Ashworth L, Bajorek E, Black S, Branscomb E, Caenepeel S, Carrano A, Caoile C, Chan YM, Christensen M, Cleland CA, Copeland A, Dalin E, Dehal P, Denys M, Detter JC, Escobar J, Flowers D, Fotopulos D, Garcia C, Georgescu AM, Glavina T, Gomez M, Gonzales E, Groza M, Hammon N, Hawkins T, Haydu L, Ho I, Huang W, Israni S, Jett J, Kadner K, Kimball H, Kobayashi A, Larionov V, Leem SH, Lopez F, Lou Y, Lowry S, Malfatti S, Martinez D, McCready P, Medina C, Morgan J, Nelson K, Nolan M, Ovcharenko I, Pitluck S, Pollard M, Popkie AP, Predki P, Quan G, Ramirez L, Rash S, Retterer J, Rodriguez A, Rogers S, Salamov A, Salazar A, She X, Smith D, Slezak T, Solovyev V, Thayer N, Tice H, Tsai M, Ustaszewska A, Vo N, Wagner M, Wheeler J, Wu K, Xie G, Yang J, Dubchak I, Furey TS, DeJong P, Dickson M, Gordon D, Eichler EE, Pennacchio LA, Richardson P, Stubbs L, Rokhsar DS, Myers RM, Rubin EM, Lucas SM: The DNA sequence and biology of human chromosome 19.  Nature. 2004 Apr 1;428(6982):529-35.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15057824</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kluver E, Schulz A, Forssmann WG, Adermann K: Chemical synthesis of beta-defensins and LEAP-1/hepcidin.  J Pept Res. 2002 Jun;59(6):241-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12010514</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hunter HN, Fulton DB, Ganz T, Vogel HJ: The solution structure of human hepcidin, a peptide hormone with antimicrobial activity that is involved in iron uptake and hereditary hemochromatosis. J Biol Chem. 2002 Oct 4;277(40):37597-603. Epub 2002 Jul 22.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12138110</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Jordan JB, Poppe L, Haniu M, Arvedson T, Syed R, Li V, Kohno H, Kim H, Schnier PD, Harvey TS, Miranda LP, Cheetham J, Sasu BJ: Hepcidin revisited, disulfide connectivity, dynamics, and structure.  J Biol Chem. 2009 Sep 4;284(36):24155-67. Epub 2009 Jun 24.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19553669</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Biasiotto G, Belloli S, Ruggeri G, Zanella I, Gerardi G, Corrado M, Gobbi E, Albertini A, Arosio P: Identification of new mutations of the HFE, hepcidin, and transferrin receptor 2 genes by denaturing HPLC analysis of individuals with biochemical indications of iron overload. Clin Chem. 2003 Dec;49(12):1981-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14633868</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Merryweather-Clarke AT, Cadet E, Bomford A, Capron D, Viprakasit V, Miller A, McHugh PJ, Chapman RW, Pointon JJ, Wimhurst VL, Livesey KJ, Tanphaichitr V, Rochette J, Robson KJ: Digenic inheritance of mutations in HAMP and HFE results in different types of haemochromatosis. Hum Mol Genet. 2003 Sep 1;12(17):2241-7. Epub 2003 Jul 15.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12915468</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Roetto A, Daraio F, Porporato P, Caruso R, Cox TM, Cazzola M, Gasparini P, Piperno A, Camaschella C: Screening hepcidin for mutations in juvenile hemochromatosis: identification of a new mutation (C70R). Blood. 2004 Mar 15;103(6):2407-9. Epub 2003 Nov 20.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14630809</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Jacolot S, Le Gac G, Scotet V, Quere I, Mura C, Ferec C: HAMP as a modifier gene that increases the phenotypic expression of the HFE pC282Y homozygous genotype. Blood. 2004 Apr 1;103(7):2835-40. Epub 2003 Dec 11.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14670915</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Delatycki MB, Allen KJ, Gow P, MacFarlane J, Radomski C, Thompson J, Hayden MR, Goldberg YP, Samuels ME: A homozygous HAMP mutation in a multiply consanguineous family with pseudo-dominant juvenile hemochromatosis. Clin Genet. 2004 May;65(5):378-83.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15099344</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
