<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:04:39 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:04:39 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP07966</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13677</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>ICRF</synonym>
    <synonym>Islet cells regeneration factor</synonym>
    <synonym>Islet of Langerhans regenerating protein</synonym>
    <synonym>PSP</synonym>
    <synonym>PTP</synonym>
    <synonym>Pancreatic stone protein</synonym>
    <synonym>Pancreatic thread protein</synonym>
    <synonym>REG</synonym>
    <synonym>REG-1-alpha</synonym>
    <synonym>Regenerating islet-derived protein 1-alpha</synonym>
    <synonym>Regenerating protein I alpha</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>REG1A</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Might act as an inhibitor of spontaneous calcium carbonate precipitation. May be associated with neuronal sprouting in brain, and with brain and pancreas regeneration</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Secreted</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:2</chromosome_location>
    <locus>2p12</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;501 bp
ATGGCTCAGACCAGCTCATACTTCATGCTGATCTCCTGCCTGATGTTTCTGTCTCAGAGC
CAAGGCCAAGAGGCCCAGACAGAGTTGCCCCAGGCCCGGATCAGCTGCCCAGAAGGCACC
AATGCCTATCGCTCCTACTGCTACTACTTTAATGAAGACCGCGAGACCTGGGTTGATGCA
GATCTCTATTGCCAGAACATGAATTCGGGCAACCTGGTGTCTGTGCTCACCCAGGCCGAG
GGTGCCTTTGTGGCCTCACTGATTAAGGAGAGTGGCACTGATGACTTCAATGTCTGGATT
GGCCTCCATGACCCCAAAAAGAACCGCCGCTGGCACTGGAGCAGTGGGTCCCTGGTCTCC
TACAAGTCCTGGGGCATTGGAGCCCCAAGCAGTGTTAATCCTGGCTACTGTGTGAGCCTG
ACCTCAAGCACAGGATTCCAGAAATGGAAGGATGTGCCTTGTGAAGACAAGTTCTCCTTT
GTCTGCAAGTTCAAAAACTAG</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>166</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>18730.8</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>5.73</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Lectin_C</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00059</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>1-22</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Lithostathine-1-alpha
MAQTSSYFMLISCLMFLSQSQGQEAQTELPQARISCPEGTNAYRSYCYYFNEDRETWVDA
DLYCQNMNSGNLVSVLTQAEGAFVASLIKESGTDDFNVWIGLHDPKKNRRWHWSSGSLVS
YKSWGIGAPSSVNPGYCVSLTSSTGFQKWKDVPCEDKFSFVCKFKN</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>5764555</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P05451</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>REG1A_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1LIT</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AF172331</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>REG1A</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>REG1A</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:9951</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Terazono K, Yamamoto H, Takasawa S, Shiga K, Yonemura Y, Tochino Y, Okamoto H: A novel gene activated in regenerating islets.  J Biol Chem. 1988 Feb 15;263(5):2111-4.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2963000</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Watanabe T, Yonekura H, Terazono K, Yamamoto H, Okamoto H: Complete nucleotide sequence of human reg gene and its expression in normal and tumoral tissues. The reg protein, pancreatic stone protein, and pancreatic thread protein are one and the same product of the gene. J Biol Chem. 1990 May 5;265(13):7432-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2332435</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Giorgi D, Bernard JP, Rouquier S, Iovanna J, Sarles H, Dagorn JC: Secretory pancreatic stone protein messenger RNA. Nucleotide sequence and expression in chronic calcifying pancreatitis. J Clin Invest. 1989 Jul;84(1):100-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2525567</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>De Caro AM, Bonicel JJ, Rouimi P, De Caro JD, Sarles H, Rovery M: Complete amino acid sequence of an immunoreactive form of human pancreatic stone protein isolated from pancreatic juice. Eur J Biochem. 1987 Oct 1;168(1):201-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3665916</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Montalto G, Bonicel J, Multigner L, Rovery M, Sarles H, De Caro A: Partial amino acid sequence of human pancreatic stone protein, a novel pancreatic secretory protein. Biochem J. 1986 Aug 15;238(1):227-32.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3541906</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gross J, Carlson RI, Brauer AW, Margolies MN, Warshaw AL, Wands JR: Isolation, characterization, and distribution of an unusual pancreatic human secretory protein. J Clin Invest. 1985 Dec;76(6):2115-26.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3908481</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>De Caro AM, Adrich Z, Fournet B, Capon C, Bonicel JJ, De Caro JD, Rovery M: N-terminal sequence extension in the glycosylated forms of human pancreatic stone protein. The 5-oxoproline N-terminal chain is O-glycosylated on the 5th amino acid residue. Biochim Biophys Acta. 1989 Feb 23;994(3):281-4.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2493268</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rouimi P, Bonicel J, Rovery M, De Caro A: Cleavage of the Arg-Ile bond in the native polypeptide chain of human pancreatic stone protein. FEBS Lett. 1987 Jun 1;216(2):195-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>3108036</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Zhang Z, Henzel WJ: Signal peptide prediction based on analysis of experimentally verified cleavage sites. Protein Sci. 2004 Oct;13(10):2819-24. Epub 2004 Aug 31.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15340161</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Stewart TA: The human reg gene encodes pancreatic stone protein.  Biochem J. 1989 Jun 1;260(2):622-3.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2764894</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Itoh T, Tsuzuki H, Katoh T, Teraoka H, Matsumoto K, Yoshida N, Terazono K, Watanabe T, Yonekura H, Yamamoto H, et al.: Isolation and characterization of human reg protein produced in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. FEBS Lett. 1990 Oct 15;272(1-2):85-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2226837</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>de la Monte SM, Ozturk M, Wands JR: Enhanced expression of an exocrine pancreatic protein in Alzheimer's disease and the developing human brain. J Clin Invest. 1990 Sep;86(3):1004-13.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2394826</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bertrand JA, Pignol D, Bernard JP, Verdier JM, Dagorn JC, Fontecilla-Camps JC: Crystal structure of human lithostathine, the pancreatic inhibitor of stone formation. EMBO J. 1996 Jun 3;15(11):2678-84.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8654365</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerbaud V, Pignol D, Loret E, Bertrand JA, Berland Y, Fontecilla-Camps JC, Canselier JP, Gabas N, Verdier JM: Mechanism of calcite crystal growth inhibition by the N-terminal undecapeptide of lithostathine. J Biol Chem. 2000 Jan 14;275(2):1057-64.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10625646</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Patard L, Stoven V, Gharib B, Bontems F, Lallemand JY, De Reggi M: What function for human lithostathine?: structural investigations by three-dimensional structure modeling and high-resolution NMR spectroscopy. Protein Eng. 1996 Nov;9(11):949-57.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8961348</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
