<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 20:01:59 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 20:01:59 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP07723</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>13432</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>GCAP 2</synonym>
    <synonym>Guanylate cyclase activator 1B</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>GUCA1B</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in calcium ion binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Stimulates guanylyl cyclase 1 (GC1) and GC2 when free calcium ions concentration is low, and GC1 and GC2 when free calcium ions concentration is elevated. This Ca(2+)-sensitive regulation of GC is a key event in recovery of the dark state of rod photoreceptors following light exposure</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>cation binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>metal ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>calcium ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Cell membrane</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:6</chromosome_location>
    <locus>6p21.1</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;603 bp
ATGGGGCAGGAGTTTAGCTGGGAGGAGGCGGAGGCAGCTGGCGAGATAGATGTGGCGGAG
CTCCAGGAGTGGTACAAGAAGTTTGTGATGGAGTGCCCCAGCGGCACACTCTTTATGCAT
GAGTTTAAGCGCTTCTTCAAGGTCACAGACGATGAGGAGGCCTCCCAGTATGTAGAGGGC
ATGTTCCGAGCCTTCGACAAGAATGGGGACAACACCATCGACTTCCTGGAGTACGTGGCA
GCTCTGAATCTCGTGCTGAGGGGCACCCTGGAGCACAAGCTGAAGTGGACATTCAAGATC
TATGATAAGGATGGCAATGGCTGCATCGACCGCCTGGAGCTACTCAACATTGTGGAGGGA
ATTTACCAGCTGAAGAAAGCCTGCCGGCGAGAGCTACAGACTGAGCAAGACCAGCTGCTC
ACACCCGAGGAGGTCGTGGACAGGATCTTCCTCCTGGTGGATGAGAATGGAGATGGCCAG
CTGTCTCTGAACGAGTTTGTTGAAGGTGCCCGTCGGGACAAGTGGGTGATGAAGATGCTG
CAGATGGACATGAATCCCAGCAGCTGGCTCGCTCAGCAGAGACGGAAAAGTGCCATGTTC
TGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>200</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>23419.5</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>4.47</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Guanylyl cyclase-activating protein 2
MGQEFSWEEAEAAGEIDVAELQEWYKKFVMECPSGTLFMHEFKRFFKVTDDEEASQYVEG
MFRAFDKNGDNTIDFLEYVAALNLVLRGTLEHKLKWTFKIYDKDGNGCIDRLELLNIVEG
IYQLKKACRRELQTEQGQLLTPEEVVDRIFLLVDENGDGQLSLNEFVEGARRDKWVMKML
QMDMNPSSWLAQQRRKSAMF</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>5702369</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>Q9UMX6</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>GUC1B_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AF173229</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>GUCA1B</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>GUCA1B</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:4679</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Surguchov A, Bronson JD, Banerjee P, Knowles JA, Ruiz C, Subbaraya I, Palczewski K, Baehr W: The human GCAP1 and GCAP2 genes are arranged in a tail-to-tail array on the short arm of chromosome 6 (p21.1). Genomics. 1997 Feb 1;39(3):312-22.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9119368</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Mungall AJ, Palmer SA, Sims SK, Edwards CA, Ashurst JL, Wilming L, Jones MC, Horton R, Hunt SE, Scott CE, Gilbert JG, Clamp ME, Bethel G, Milne S, Ainscough R, Almeida JP, Ambrose KD, Andrews TD, Ashwell RI, Babbage AK, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Banerjee R, Barker DJ, Barlow KF, Bates K, Beare DM, Beasley H, Beasley O, Bird CP, Blakey S, Bray-Allen S, Brook J, Brown AJ, Brown JY, Burford DC, Burrill W, Burton J, Carder C, Carter NP, Chapman JC, Clark SY, Clark G, Clee CM, Clegg S, Cobley V, Collier RE, Collins JE, Colman LK, Corby NR, Coville GJ, Culley KM, Dhami P, Davies J, Dunn M, Earthrowl ME, Ellington AE, Evans KA, Faulkner L, Francis MD, Frankish A, Frankland J, French L, Garner P, Garnett J, Ghori MJ, Gilby LM, Gillson CJ, Glithero RJ, Grafham DV, Grant M, Gribble S, Griffiths C, Griffiths M, Hall R, Halls KS, Hammond S, Harley JL, Hart EA, Heath PD, Heathcott R, Holmes SJ, Howden PJ, Howe KL, Howell GR, Huckle E, Humphray SJ, Humphries MD, Hunt AR, Johnson CM, Joy AA, Kay M, Keenan SJ, Kimberley AM, King A, Laird GK, Langford C, Lawlor S, Leongamornlert DA, Leversha M, Lloyd CR, Lloyd DM, Loveland JE, Lovell J, Martin S, Mashreghi-Mohammadi M, Maslen GL, Matthews L, McCann OT, McLaren SJ, McLay K, McMurray A, Moore MJ, Mullikin JC, Niblett D, Nickerson T, Novik KL, Oliver K, Overton-Larty EK, Parker A, Patel R, Pearce AV, Peck AI, Phillimore B, Phillips S, Plumb RW, Porter KM, Ramsey Y, Ranby SA, Rice CM, Ross MT, Searle SM, Sehra HK, Sheridan E, Skuce CD, Smith S, Smith M, Spraggon L, Squares SL, Steward CA, Sycamore N, Tamlyn-Hall G, Tester J, Theaker AJ, Thomas DW, Thorpe A, Tracey A, Tromans A, Tubby B, Wall M, Wallis JM, West AP, White SS, Whitehead SL, Whittaker H, Wild A, Willey DJ, Wilmer TE, Wood JM, Wray PW, Wyatt JC, Young L, Younger RM, Bentley DR, Coulson A, Durbin R, Hubbard T, Sulston JE, Dunham I, Rogers J, Beck S: The DNA sequence and analysis of human chromosome 6.  Nature. 2003 Oct 23;425(6960):805-11.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14574404</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Payne AM, Downes SM, Bessant DA, Plant C, Moore T, Bird AC, Bhattacharya SS: Genetic analysis of the guanylate cyclase activator 1B (GUCA1B) gene in patients with autosomal dominant retinal dystrophies. J Med Genet. 1999 Sep;36(9):691-3.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10507726</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
