<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 18:59:25 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 18:59:25 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP01784</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>7137</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>G25K GTP-binding protein</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>CDC42</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in GTP binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Plasma membrane-associated small GTPase which cycles between an active GTP-bound and an inactive GDP-bound state. In active state binds to a variety of effector proteins to regulate cellular responses. Involved in epithelial cell polarization processes. Causes the formation of thin, actin-rich surface projections called filopodia</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01273</accession>
      <name>Guanosine triphosphate</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01201</accession>
      <name>Guanosine diphosphate</name>
    </metabolite>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB01397</accession>
      <name>Guanosine monophosphate</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>nucleotide binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>purine nucleotide binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>guanyl nucleotide binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>guanyl ribonucleotide binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>gtp binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>biological regulation</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>regulation of biological process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>regulation of cellular process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>signal transduction</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>intracellular signal transduction</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>small gtpase mediated signal transduction</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>cell part</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>intracellular</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Cell membrane</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Lipid-anchor</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Cytoplasmic side (Potential)</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>1p36.1</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;576 bp
ATGCAGACAATTAAGTGTGTTGTTGTGGGCGATGGTGCTGTTGGTAAAACATGTCTCCTG
ATATCCTACACAACAAACAAATTTCCATCGGAATATGTACCGACTGTTTTTGACAACTAT
GCAGTCACAGTTATGATTGGTGGAGAACCATATACTCTTGGACTTTTTGATACTGCAGGG
CAAGAGGATTATGACAGATTACGACCGCTGAGTTATCCACAAACAGATGTATTTCTAGTC
TGTTTTTCAGTGGTCTCTCCATCTTCATTTGAAAACGTGAAAGAAAAGTGGGTGCCTGAG
ATAACTCACCACTGTCCAAAGACTCCTTTCTTGCTTGTTGGGACTCAAATTGATCTCAGA
GATGACCCCTCTACTATTGAGAAACTTGCCAAGAACAAACAGAAGCCTATCACTCCAGAG
ACTGCTGAAAAGCTGGCCCGTGACCTGAAGGCTGTCAAGTATGTGGAGTGTTCTGCACTT
ACACAGAGAGGTCTGAAGAATGTGTTTGATGAGGCTATCCTAGCTGCCCTCGAGCCTCCG
GAAACTCAACCCAAAAGGAAGTGCTGTATATTCTAA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>191</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>21310.4</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>5.83</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Ras</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00071</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Cell division control protein 42 homolog
MQTIKCVVVGDGAVGKTCLLISYTTNKFPSEYVPTVFDNYAVTVMIGGEPYTLGLFDTAG
QEDYDRLRPLSYPQTDVFLVCFSVVSPSSFENVKEKWVPEITHHCPKTPFLLVGTQIDLR
DDPSTIEKLAKNKQKPITPETAEKLARDLKAVKYVECSALTQRGLKNVFDEAILAALEPP
ETQPKRKCCIF</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>182857</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P60953</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>CDC42_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1GRN</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>M35543</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>CDC42</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>CDC42</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:1736</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Munemitsu S, Innis MA, Clark R, McCormick F, Ullrich A, Polakis P: Molecular cloning and expression of a G25K cDNA, the human homolog of the yeast cell cycle gene CDC42. Mol Cell Biol. 1990 Nov;10(11):5977-82.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2122236</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shinjo K, Koland JG, Hart MJ, Narasimhan V, Johnson DI, Evans T, Cerione RA: Molecular cloning of the gene for the human placental GTP-binding protein Gp (G25K): identification of this GTP-binding protein as the human homolog of the yeast cell-division-cycle protein CDC42. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1990 Dec;87(24):9853-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2124704</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gregory SG, Barlow KF, McLay KE, Kaul R, Swarbreck D, Dunham A, Scott CE, Howe KL, Woodfine K, Spencer CC, Jones MC, Gillson C, Searle S, Zhou Y, Kokocinski F, McDonald L, Evans R, Phillips K, Atkinson A, Cooper R, Jones C, Hall RE, Andrews TD, Lloyd C, Ainscough R, Almeida JP, Ambrose KD, Anderson F, Andrew RW, Ashwell RI, Aubin K, Babbage AK, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Beasley H, Bethel G, Bird CP, Bray-Allen S, Brown JY, Brown AJ, Buckley D, Burton J, Bye J, Carder C, Chapman JC, Clark SY, Clarke G, Clee C, Cobley V, Collier RE, Corby N, Coville GJ, Davies J, Deadman R, Dunn M, Earthrowl M, Ellington AG, Errington H, Frankish A, Frankland J, French L, Garner P, Garnett J, Gay L, Ghori MR, Gibson R, Gilby LM, Gillett W, Glithero RJ, Grafham DV, Griffiths C, Griffiths-Jones S, Grocock R, Hammond S, Harrison ES, Hart E, Haugen E, Heath PD, Holmes S, Holt K, Howden PJ, Hunt AR, Hunt SE, Hunter G, Isherwood J, James R, Johnson C, Johnson D, Joy A, Kay M, Kershaw JK, Kibukawa M, Kimberley AM, King A, Knights AJ, Lad H, Laird G, Lawlor S, Leongamornlert DA, Lloyd DM, Loveland J, Lovell J, Lush MJ, Lyne R, Martin S, Mashreghi-Mohammadi M, Matthews L, Matthews NS, McLaren S, Milne S, Mistry S, Moore MJ, Nickerson T, O'Dell CN, Oliver K, Palmeiri A, Palmer SA, Parker A, Patel D, Pearce AV, Peck AI, Pelan S, Phelps K, Phillimore BJ, Plumb R, Rajan J, Raymond C, Rouse G, Saenphimmachak C, Sehra HK, Sheridan E, Shownkeen R, Sims S, Skuce CD, Smith M, Steward C, Subramanian S, Sycamore N, Tracey A, Tromans A, Van Helmond Z, Wall M, Wallis JM, White S, Whitehead SL, Wilkinson JE, Willey DL, Williams H, Wilming L, Wray PW, Wu Z, Coulson A, Vaudin M, Sulston JE, Durbin R, Hubbard T, Wooster R, Dunham I, Carter NP, McVean G, Ross MT, Harrow J, Olson MV, Beck S, Rogers J, Bentley DR, Banerjee R, Bryant SP, Burford DC, Burrill WD, Clegg SM, Dhami P, Dovey O, Faulkner LM, Gribble SM, Langford CF, Pandian RD, Porter KM, Prigmore E: The DNA sequence and biological annotation of human chromosome 1.  Nature. 2006 May 18;441(7091):315-21.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16710414</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kwong CH, Malech HL, Rotrosen D, Leto TL: Regulation of the human neutrophil NADPH oxidase by rho-related G-proteins. Biochemistry. 1993 Jun 1;32(21):5711-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>8504089</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Polakis PG, Snyderman R, Evans T: Characterization of G25K, a GTP-binding protein containing a novel putative nucleotide binding domain. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. 1989 Apr 14;160(1):25-32.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2496687</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Yamane HK, Farnsworth CC, Xie HY, Evans T, Howald WN, Gelb MH, Glomset JA, Clarke S, Fung BK: Membrane-binding domain of the small G protein G25K contains an S-(all-trans-geranylgeranyl)cysteine methyl ester at its carboxyl terminus. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1991 Jan 1;88(1):286-90.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1898776</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Joberty G, Perlungher RR, Macara IG: The Borgs, a new family of Cdc42 and TC10 GTPase-interacting proteins.  Mol Cell Biol. 1999 Oct;19(10):6585-97.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10490598</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Eisenmann KM, McCarthy JB, Simpson MA, Keely PJ, Guan JL, Tachibana K, Lim L, Manser E, Furcht LT, Iida J: Melanoma chondroitin sulphate proteoglycan regulates cell spreading through Cdc42, Ack-1 and p130cas. Nat Cell Biol. 1999 Dec;1(8):507-13.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10587647</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Pirone DM, Fukuhara S, Gutkind JS, Burbelo PD: SPECs, small binding proteins for Cdc42.  J Biol Chem. 2000 Jul 28;275(30):22650-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10816584</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Johansson A, Driessens M, Aspenstrom P: The mammalian homologue of the Caenorhabditis elegans polarity protein PAR-6 is a binding partner for the Rho GTPases Cdc42 and Rac1. J Cell Sci. 2000 Sep;113 ( Pt 18):3267-75.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10954424</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Miki H, Yamaguchi H, Suetsugu S, Takenawa T: IRSp53 is an essential intermediate between Rac and WAVE in the regulation of membrane ruffling. Nature. 2000 Dec 7;408(6813):732-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11130076</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Noda Y, Takeya R, Ohno S, Naito S, Ito T, Sumimoto H: Human homologues of the Caenorhabditis elegans cell polarity protein PAR6 as an adaptor that links the small GTPases Rac and Cdc42 to atypical protein kinase C. Genes Cells. 2001 Feb;6(2):107-19.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11260256</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Meller N, Irani-Tehrani M, Kiosses WB, Del Pozo MA, Schwartz MA: Zizimin1, a novel Cdc42 activator, reveals a new GEF domain for Rho proteins. Nat Cell Biol. 2002 Sep;4(9):639-47.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12172552</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Masuda-Robens JM, Kutney SN, Qi H, Chou MM: The TRE17 oncogene encodes a component of a novel effector pathway for Rho GTPases Cdc42 and Rac1 and stimulates actin remodeling. Mol Cell Biol. 2003 Mar;23(6):2151-61.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12612085</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Worby CA, Mattoo S, Kruger RP, Corbeil LB, Koller A, Mendez JC, Zekarias B, Lazar C, Dixon JE: The fic domain: regulation of cell signaling by adenylylation.  Mol Cell. 2009 Apr 10;34(1):93-103.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19362538</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Yarbrough ML, Li Y, Kinch LN, Grishin NV, Ball HL, Orth K: AMPylation of Rho GTPases by Vibrio VopS disrupts effector binding and downstream signaling. Science. 2009 Jan 9;323(5911):269-72. Epub 2008 Nov 27.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19039103</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Choudhary C, Kumar C, Gnad F, Nielsen ML, Rehman M, Walther TC, Olsen JV, Mann M: Lysine acetylation targets protein complexes and co-regulates major cellular functions. Science. 2009 Aug 14;325(5942):834-40. Epub 2009 Jul 16.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19608861</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Feltham JL, Dotsch V, Raza S, Manor D, Cerione RA, Sutcliffe MJ, Wagner G, Oswald RE: Definition of the switch surface in the solution structure of Cdc42Hs.  Biochemistry. 1997 Jul 22;36(29):8755-66.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9220962</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Guo W, Sutcliffe MJ, Cerione RA, Oswald RE: Identification of the binding surface on Cdc42Hs for p21-activated kinase.  Biochemistry. 1998 Oct 6;37(40):14030-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9760238</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rittinger K, Walker PA, Eccleston JF, Nurmahomed K, Owen D, Laue E, Gamblin SJ, Smerdon SJ: Crystal structure of a small G protein in complex with the GTPase-activating protein rhoGAP. Nature. 1997 Aug 14;388(6643):693-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9262406</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Rudolph MG, Wittinghofer A, Vetter IR: Nucleotide binding to the G12V-mutant of Cdc42 investigated by X-ray diffraction and fluorescence spectroscopy: two different nucleotide states in one crystal. Protein Sci. 1999 Apr;8(4):778-87.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>10211824</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
