<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 18:58:12 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 18:58:12 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP01627</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>6950</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Gamma-1-globin</synonym>
    <synonym>Hb F Agamma</synonym>
    <synonym>Hemoglobin gamma-1 chain</synonym>
    <synonym>Hemoglobin gamma-A chain</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>HBG1</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in iron ion binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Gamma chains make up the fetal hemoglobin F, in combination with alpha chains</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB03178</accession>
      <name>Heme</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>heme binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>oxygen binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>cation binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>metal ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>transition metal ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>iron ion binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>establishment of localization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>gas transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>oxygen transport</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>macromolecular complex</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>protein complex</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>hemoglobin complex</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:1</chromosome_location>
    <locus>11p15.5</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;444 bp
ATGGGTCATTTCACAGAGGAGGACAAGGCTACTATCACAAGCCTGTGGGGCAAGGTGAAT
GTGGAAGATGCTGGAGGAGAAACCCTGGGAAGGCTCCTGGTTGTCTACCCATGGACCCAG
AGGTTCTTTGACAGCTTTGGCAACCTGTCCTCTGCCTCTGCCATCATGGGCAACCCCAAA
GTCAAGGCACATGGCAAGAAGGTGCTGACTTCCTTGGGAGATGCCATAAAGCACCTGGAT
GATCTCAAGGGCACCTTTGCCCAGCTGAGTGAACTGCACTGTGACAAGCTGCATGTGGAT
CCTGAGAACTTCAAGCTCCTGGGAAATGTGCTGGTGACCGTTTTGGCAATCCATTTCGGC
AAAGAATTCACCCCTGAGGTGCAGGCTTCCTGGCAGAAGATGGTGACTGCAGTGGCCAGT
GCCCTGTCCTCCAGATACCACTGA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>147</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>16140.4</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>7.23</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Globin</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00042</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Hemoglobin subunit gamma-1
MGHFTEEDKATITSLWGKVNVEDAGGETLGRLLVVYPWTQRFFDSFGNLSSASAIMGNPK
VKAHGKKVLTSLGDAIKHLDDLKGTFAQLSELHCDKLHVDPENFKLLGNVLVTVLAIHFG
KEFTPEVQASWQKMVTAVASALSSRYH</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>11493500</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>P69891</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>HBG1_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1I3E</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>AF130098</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>HBG1</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>HBG1</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:4831</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Slightom JL, Blechl AE, Smithies O: Human fetal G gamma- and A gamma-globin genes: complete nucleotide sequences suggest that DNA can be exchanged between these duplicated genes. Cell. 1980 Oct;21(3):627-38.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7438203</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Shen SH, Slightom JL, Smithies O: A history of the human fetal globin gene duplication.  Cell. 1981 Oct;26(2 Pt 2):191-203.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7332928</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wilson JB, Brennan SO, Allen J, Shaw JG, Gu LH, Huisman TH: The M gamma chain of human fetal hemoglobin is an A gamma chain with an in vitro modification of gamma 141 leucine to hydroxyleucine. J Chromatogr. 1993 Jul 23;617(1):37-42.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7690768</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Kidd RD, Baker HM, Mathews AJ, Brittain T, Baker EN: Oligomerization and ligand binding in a homotetrameric hemoglobin: two high-resolution crystal structures of hemoglobin Bart's (gamma(4)), a marker for alpha-thalassemia. Protein Sci. 2001 Sep;10(9):1739-49.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>11514664</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Stegink LD, Meyer PD, Brummel MC: Human fetal hemoglobin F 1. Acetylation status.  J Biol Chem. 1971 May 10;246(9):3001-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>5554303</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Altay C, Gurgey A, Wilson JB, Hu H, Webber BB, Kutlar F, Huisman TH: Hb F-Baskent or alpha 2A gamma 128(H6)Ala----Thr.  Hemoglobin. 1988;12(1):87-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2454900</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Chen SS, Wilson JB, Webber BB, Huisman TH: Hb F-Beech Island or alpha 2A gamma 2(53)(D4)Ala----Asp.  Hemoglobin. 1985;9(5):525-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2417989</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Nakatsuji T, Headlee M, Lam H, Wilson JB, Huisman TH: Hb F-Bonaire-Ga or alpha 2 A gamma 2 39(C5) Gln replaced by Arg, characterized by high pressure liquid chromatographic and microsequencing procedures. Hemoglobin. 1982;6(6):599-606.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6186637</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Nakatsuji T, Lam H, Huisman TH: Hb F-Calluna or alpha 2 gamma 2(12 Thr replaced by Arg; 75Ile; 136Ala) in a Caucasian baby. Hemoglobin. 1983;7(6):563-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6199326</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Chen SS, Webber BB, Kutlar A, Wilson JB, Huisman TH: Hb F-Cobb or alpha(2)A gamma(2)37(C3)Trp----Gly.  Hemoglobin. 1985;9(6):617-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2419280</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Al-Awamy BH, Niazi GA, Al-Mouzan MI, Wilson JB, Chen SS, Webber BB, Huisman TH: Hb F-Dammam or alpha 2A gamma 2(79) (EF3) Asp----Asn.  Hemoglobin. 1985;9(2):171-3.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2411679</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Schneider RG, Haggard ME, Gustavson LP, Brimhall B, Jones RT: Genetic haemoglobin abnormalities in about 9000 Black and 7000 White newborns; haemoglobin F Dickinson (Agamma97His-Arg), a new variant. Br J Haematol. 1974 Dec;28(4):515-24.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>4455303</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hidaka K, Iuchi I, Nakahara H, Iwakawa G: Hb F-Fukuyama or A gamma T43(CD2)Asp----Asn.  Hemoglobin. 1989;13(1):93-6.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2467893</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Sacker LS, Beale D, Black AJ, Huntsman RG, Lehmann H, Lorkin PA: Haemoglobin F Hull (gamma-121 glutamic acid--lysine), homologous with haemoglobins O Arab and O Indonesia. Br Med J. 1967 Aug 26;3(5564):531-3.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6038320</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Fuyuno K, Torigoe T, Ohba Y, Matsuoka M, Miyaji T: Survey of cord blood hemoglobin in Japan and identification of two new gamma chain variants. Hemoglobin. 1981;5(2):139-51.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6163752</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wada Y, Hayashi A, Masanori F, Katakuse I, Ichihara T, Nakabushi H, Matsuo T, Sakurai T, Matsuda H: Characterization of a new fetal hemoglobin variant, Hb F Izumi A gamma 6Glu replaced by Gly, by molecular secondary ion mass spectrometry. Biochim Biophys Acta. 1983 Dec 28;749(3):244-8.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6197997</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ahern EJ, Jones RT, Brimhall B, Gray RH: Haemoglobin F Jamaica (alpha-2 gamma-2 61 Lys leads to Glu; 136 Ala).  Br J Haematol. 1970 Mar;18(3):369-75.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>5491586</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Plaseska D, Kutlar F, Wilson JB, Webber BB, Zeng YT, Huisman TH: Hb F-Jiangsu, the first gamma chain variant with a valine----methionine substitution: alpha 2A gamma 2 134(H12)Val----Met. Hemoglobin. 1990;14(2):177-83.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1703137</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Yoshinaka H, Ohba Y, Hattori Y, Matsuoka M, Miyaji T, Fuyuno K: A new gamma chain variant, HB F Kotobuki or AI gamma 6 (A3) Glu leads to Gly. Hemoglobin. 1982;6(1):37-42.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6175602</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Luan Eng LI, Wiltshire BG, Lehmann H: Structural identification of haemoglobin F Kuala Lumpur: alpha2 gamma2 22(B4)Asp leads to Gly; 136 Ala. Biochim Biophys Acta. 1973 Oct 18;322(2):224-30.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>4765089</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Plaseska D, Cepreganova-Krstik B, Momirovska A, Efremov GD: Hb F-Macedonia-I or alpha 2A gamma (2)2(NA2)His- &amp;gt; Gln.  Hemoglobin. 1994 May;18(3):241-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>7928382</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Chen SS, Wilson JB, Huisman TH: Hb F-Pendergrass, an A gamma I variant with a Pro----Arg substitution at position gamma 36(C2). Hemoglobin. 1985;9(1):73-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2581920</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Nakatsuji T, Webber B, Lam H, Wilson JB, Huisman TH, Sciarratta GV, Sansone G, Molaro GL: A new gamma chain variant: Hb F-Pordenone [gamma 6(A3) Glu replaced by Gln: 75ILE: 136ALA]. Hemoglobin. 1982;6(4):397-401.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6183236</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Grifoni V, Kamuzora H, Lehmann H, Charlesworth D: A new Hb variant: Hb F Sardinia gamma75(E19) isoleucine leads to threonine found in a family with Hb G Philadelphia, beta-chain deficiency and a Lepore-like haemoglobin indistinguishable from Hb A2. Acta Haematol. 1975;53(6):347-55.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>808940</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Care A, Marinucci M, Massa A, Maffi D, Sposi NM, Improta T, Tentori L: Hb F-Siena (alpha 2 a gamma t2 121 (GH4) Glu leads to Lys). A new fetal hemoglobin variant. Hemoglobin. 1983;7(1):79-83.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6188719</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Jenkins GC, Beale D, Black AJ, Huntsman GR, Lehmann H: Haemoglobin F Texas I(alpha-2,gamma-2-5glu-lys): a variant of haemoglobin F. Br J Haematol. 1967 Mar;13(2):252-5.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6019034</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ahern E, Holder W, Ahern V, Serjeant GR, Serjeant BE, Forbes M, Brimhall B, Jones RT: Haemoglobin F Victoria Jubilee (alpha 2 A gamma 2 80 Asp-Try).  Biochim Biophys Acta. 1975 May 30;393(1):188-94.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1138921</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Huisman TH, Kutlar F, Gu LH: Gamma chain abnormalities and gamma-globin gene rearrangements in newborn babies of various populations. Hemoglobin. 1991;15(5):349-79.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>1802881</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Ma M, Hu H, Kutlar F, Wilson JB, Huisman TH: Hb F-Xin-Su or A gamma I73(E17)Asp----His: a new slow-moving fetal hemoglobin variant. Hemoglobin. 1987;11(5):473-9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2448269</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hu H, Ma M: Hb F-Xinjiang or A gamma T25(B7)Gly----Arg: a new slow-moving unstable fetal hemoglobin variant. Hemoglobin. 1987;11(5):465-72.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>2448268</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Nakatsuji T, Ohba Y, Huisman TH: HB F-Yamaguchi (gamma 75Thr, gamma 80Asn, gamma 136Ala) is associated with G gamma-thalassemia. Am J Hematol. 1984 Feb;16(2):189-92.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>6198905</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
