<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protein>
  <version>3.5</version>
  <creation_date>2013-01-15 19:00:48 -0700</creation_date>
  <update_date>2013-01-15 19:00:48 -0700</update_date>
  <accession>HMDBP01937</accession>
  <secondary_accessions>
    <accession>7347</accession>
  </secondary_accessions>
  <protein_type>Unknown</protein_type>
  <synonyms>
    <synonym>Histone H2A/e</synonym>
  </synonyms>
  <gene_name>HIST1H2AJ</gene_name>
  <general_function>Involved in DNA binding</general_function>
  <specific_function>Core component of nucleosome. Nucleosomes wrap and compact DNA into chromatin, limiting DNA accessibility to the cellular machineries which require DNA as a template. Histones thereby play a central role in transcription regulation, DNA repair, DNA replication and chromosomal stability. DNA accessibility is regulated via a complex set of post-translational modifications of histones, also called histone code, and nucleosome remodeling</specific_function>
  <pathways>
  </pathways>
  <metabolite_associations>
    <metabolite>
      <accession>HMDB00464</accession>
      <name>Calcium</name>
    </metabolite>
  </metabolite_associations>
  <go_classifications>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>nucleic acid binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>function</category>
      <description>dna binding</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>cellular process</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>cellular component organization at cellular level</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>organelle organization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>chromosome organization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>chromatin organization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>nucleosome organization</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>process</category>
      <description>nucleosome assembly</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>organelle</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>membrane-bounded organelle</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>intracellular membrane-bounded organelle</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>nucleus</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>macromolecular complex</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>protein-dna complex</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
    <go_class>
      <category>component</category>
      <description>nucleosome</description>
      <go_id/>
    </go_class>
  </go_classifications>
  <subcellular_locations>
    <subcellular_location>Nucleus</subcellular_location>
    <subcellular_location>Chromosome</subcellular_location>
  </subcellular_locations>
  <gene_properties>
    <chromosome_location>Chromosome:6</chromosome_location>
    <locus>6p22.1</locus>
    <gene_sequence>&gt;387 bp
ATGTCTGGGCGTGGTAAGCAGGGAGGCAAAGCTCGCGCCAAGGCCAAGACCCGCTCTTCT
CGGGCCGGGCTTCAGTTTCCCGTAGGCCGAGTGCATCGCCTGCTCCGCAAAGGCAACTAT
GCGGAGCGGGTCGGTGCTGGAGCGCCGGTGTACCTGGCGGCGGTGCTGGAGTACCTGACC
GCCGAGATCCTGGAGCTGGCTGGCAACGCGGCCCGCGACAACAAGAAGACTCGCATCATC
CCGCGTCACCTCCAGCTGGCCATCCGCAACGATGAGGAGCTCAACAAGCTTCTGGGCAAA
GTCACCATCGCACAGGGTGGCGTCCTGCCCAACATCCAGGCCGTGCTGCTGCCAAAGAAA
ACTGAGAGCCACCACAAGACTAAGTAA</gene_sequence>
  </gene_properties>
  <protein_properties>
    <residue_number>128</residue_number>
    <molecular_weight>13936.2</molecular_weight>
    <theoretical_pi>11.53</theoretical_pi>
    <pfams>
      <pfam>
        <name>Histone</name>
        <pfam_id>PF00125</pfam_id>
      </pfam>
    </pfams>
    <transmembrane_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </transmembrane_regions>
    <signal_regions>
      <region>None</region>
    </signal_regions>
    <protein_sequence>&gt;Histone H2A type 1-J
MSGRGKQGGKARAKAKTRSSRAGLQFPVGRVHRLLRKGNYAERVGAGAPVYLAAVLEYLT
AEILELAGNAARDNKKTRIIPRHLQLAIRNDEELNKLLGKVTIAQGGVLPNIQAVLLPKK
TESHHKTK</protein_sequence>
  </protein_properties>
  <genbank_protein_id>42542673</genbank_protein_id>
  <uniprot_id>Q99878</uniprot_id>
  <uniprot_name>H2A1J_HUMAN</uniprot_name>
  <pdb_ids>
    <pdb_id>1EQZ</pdb_id>
  </pdb_ids>
  <genbank_gene_id>BC066232</genbank_gene_id>
  <genecard_id>HIST1H2AJ</genecard_id>
  <geneatlas_id>HIST1H2AJ</geneatlas_id>
  <hgnc_id>HGNC:4727</hgnc_id>
  <general_references>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Albig W, Doenecke D: The human histone gene cluster at the D6S105 locus.  Hum Genet. 1997 Dec;101(3):284-94.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>9439656</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Marzluff WF, Gongidi P, Woods KR, Jin J, Maltais LJ: The human and mouse replication-dependent histone genes.  Genomics. 2002 Nov;80(5):487-98.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>12408966</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Mungall AJ, Palmer SA, Sims SK, Edwards CA, Ashurst JL, Wilming L, Jones MC, Horton R, Hunt SE, Scott CE, Gilbert JG, Clamp ME, Bethel G, Milne S, Ainscough R, Almeida JP, Ambrose KD, Andrews TD, Ashwell RI, Babbage AK, Bagguley CL, Bailey J, Banerjee R, Barker DJ, Barlow KF, Bates K, Beare DM, Beasley H, Beasley O, Bird CP, Blakey S, Bray-Allen S, Brook J, Brown AJ, Brown JY, Burford DC, Burrill W, Burton J, Carder C, Carter NP, Chapman JC, Clark SY, Clark G, Clee CM, Clegg S, Cobley V, Collier RE, Collins JE, Colman LK, Corby NR, Coville GJ, Culley KM, Dhami P, Davies J, Dunn M, Earthrowl ME, Ellington AE, Evans KA, Faulkner L, Francis MD, Frankish A, Frankland J, French L, Garner P, Garnett J, Ghori MJ, Gilby LM, Gillson CJ, Glithero RJ, Grafham DV, Grant M, Gribble S, Griffiths C, Griffiths M, Hall R, Halls KS, Hammond S, Harley JL, Hart EA, Heath PD, Heathcott R, Holmes SJ, Howden PJ, Howe KL, Howell GR, Huckle E, Humphray SJ, Humphries MD, Hunt AR, Johnson CM, Joy AA, Kay M, Keenan SJ, Kimberley AM, King A, Laird GK, Langford C, Lawlor S, Leongamornlert DA, Leversha M, Lloyd CR, Lloyd DM, Loveland JE, Lovell J, Martin S, Mashreghi-Mohammadi M, Maslen GL, Matthews L, McCann OT, McLaren SJ, McLay K, McMurray A, Moore MJ, Mullikin JC, Niblett D, Nickerson T, Novik KL, Oliver K, Overton-Larty EK, Parker A, Patel R, Pearce AV, Peck AI, Phillimore B, Phillips S, Plumb RW, Porter KM, Ramsey Y, Ranby SA, Rice CM, Ross MT, Searle SM, Sehra HK, Sheridan E, Skuce CD, Smith S, Smith M, Spraggon L, Squares SL, Steward CA, Sycamore N, Tamlyn-Hall G, Tester J, Theaker AJ, Thomas DW, Thorpe A, Tracey A, Tromans A, Tubby B, Wall M, Wallis JM, West AP, White SS, Whitehead SL, Whittaker H, Wild A, Willey DJ, Wilmer TE, Wood JM, Wray PW, Wyatt JC, Young L, Younger RM, Bentley DR, Coulson A, Durbin R, Hubbard T, Sulston JE, Dunham I, Rogers J, Beck S: The DNA sequence and analysis of human chromosome 6.  Nature. 2003 Oct 23;425(6960):805-11.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>14574404</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Gerhard DS, Wagner L, Feingold EA, Shenmen CM, Grouse LH, Schuler G, Klein SL, Old S, Rasooly R, Good P, Guyer M, Peck AM, Derge JG, Lipman D, Collins FS, Jang W, Sherry S, Feolo M, Misquitta L, Lee E, Rotmistrovsky K, Greenhut SF, Schaefer CF, Buetow K, Bonner TI, Haussler D, Kent J, Kiekhaus M, Furey T, Brent M, Prange C, Schreiber K, Shapiro N, Bhat NK, Hopkins RF, Hsie F, Driscoll T, Soares MB, Casavant TL, Scheetz TE, Brown-stein MJ, Usdin TB, Toshiyuki S, Carninci P, Piao Y, Dudekula DB, Ko MS, Kawakami K, Suzuki Y, Sugano S, Gruber CE, Smith MR, Simmons B, Moore T, Waterman R, Johnson SL, Ruan Y, Wei CL, Mathavan S, Gunaratne PH, Wu J, Garcia AM, Hulyk SW, Fuh E, Yuan Y, Sneed A, Kowis C, Hodgson A, Muzny DM, McPherson J, Gibbs RA, Fahey J, Helton E, Ketteman M, Madan A, Rodrigues S, Sanchez A, Whiting M, Madari A, Young AC, Wetherby KD, Granite SJ, Kwong PN, Brinkley CP, Pearson RL, Bouffard GG, Blakesly RW, Green ED, Dickson MC, Rodriguez AC, Grimwood J, Schmutz J, Myers RM, Butterfield YS, Griffith M, Griffith OL, Krzywinski MI, Liao N, Morin R, Palmquist D, Petrescu AS, Skalska U, Smailus DE, Stott JM, Schnerch A, Schein JE, Jones SJ, Holt RA, Baross A, Marra MA, Clifton S, Makowski KA, Bosak S, Malek J: The status, quality, and expansion of the NIH full-length cDNA project: the Mammalian Gene Collection (MGC). Genome Res. 2004 Oct;14(10B):2121-7.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15489334</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Aihara H, Nakagawa T, Yasui K, Ohta T, Hirose S, Dhomae N, Takio K, Kaneko M, Takeshima Y, Muramatsu M, Ito T: Nucleosomal histone kinase-1 phosphorylates H2A Thr 119 during mitosis in the early Drosophila embryo. Genes Dev. 2004 Apr 15;18(8):877-88. Epub 2004 Apr 12.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15078818</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Zhang Y, Griffin K, Mondal N, Parvin JD: Phosphorylation of histone H2A inhibits transcription on chromatin templates. J Biol Chem. 2004 May 21;279(21):21866-72. Epub 2004 Mar 9.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15010469</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Wang H, Wang L, Erdjument-Bromage H, Vidal M, Tempst P, Jones RS, Zhang Y: Role of histone H2A ubiquitination in Polycomb silencing.  Nature. 2004 Oct 14;431(7010):873-8. Epub 2004 Sep 22.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15386022</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Hagiwara T, Hidaka Y, Yamada M: Deimination of histone H2A and H4 at arginine 3 in HL-60 granulocytes.  Biochemistry. 2005 Apr 19;44(15):5827-34.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>15823041</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Cao R, Tsukada Y, Zhang Y: Role of Bmi-1 and Ring1A in H2A ubiquitylation and Hox gene silencing.  Mol Cell. 2005 Dec 22;20(6):845-54.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16359901</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bergink S, Salomons FA, Hoogstraten D, Groothuis TA, de Waard H, Wu J, Yuan L, Citterio E, Houtsmuller AB, Neefjes J, Hoeijmakers JH, Vermeulen W, Dantuma NP: DNA damage triggers nucleotide excision repair-dependent monoubiquitylation of histone H2A. Genes Dev. 2006 May 15;20(10):1343-52.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16702407</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Bonenfant D, Coulot M, Towbin H, Schindler P, van Oostrum J: Characterization of histone H2A and H2B variants and their post-translational modifications by mass spectrometry. Mol Cell Proteomics. 2006 Mar;5(3):541-52. Epub 2005 Nov 30.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16319397</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Boyne MT 2nd, Pesavento JJ, Mizzen CA, Kelleher NL: Precise characterization of human histones in the H2A gene family by top down mass spectrometry. J Proteome Res. 2006 Feb;5(2):248-53.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>16457589</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Mailand N, Bekker-Jensen S, Faustrup H, Melander F, Bartek J, Lukas C, Lukas J: RNF8 ubiquitylates histones at DNA double-strand breaks and promotes assembly of repair proteins. Cell. 2007 Nov 30;131(5):887-900. Epub 2007 Nov 20.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18001824</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Huen MS, Grant R, Manke I, Minn K, Yu X, Yaffe MB, Chen J: RNF8 transduces the DNA-damage signal via histone ubiquitylation and checkpoint protein assembly. Cell. 2007 Nov 30;131(5):901-14. Epub 2007 Nov 20.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>18001825</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Stewart GS, Panier S, Townsend K, Al-Hakim AK, Kolas NK, Miller ES, Nakada S, Ylanko J, Olivarius S, Mendez M, Oldreive C, Wildenhain J, Tagliaferro A, Pelletier L, Taubenheim N, Durandy A, Byrd PJ, Stankovic T, Taylor AM, Durocher D: The RIDDLE syndrome protein mediates a ubiquitin-dependent signaling cascade at sites of DNA damage. Cell. 2009 Feb 6;136(3):420-34.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19203578</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <reference_text>Doil C, Mailand N, Bekker-Jensen S, Menard P, Larsen DH, Pepperkok R, Ellenberg J, Panier S, Durocher D, Bartek J, Lukas J, Lukas C: RNF168 binds and amplifies ubiquitin conjugates on damaged chromosomes to allow accumulation of repair proteins. Cell. 2009 Feb 6;136(3):435-46.</reference_text>
      <pubmed_id>19203579</pubmed_id>
    </reference>
  </general_references>
  <metabolite_references>
  </metabolite_references>
</protein>
